<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>science &amp; medicine &#8211; JAMES THE OBSCURE</title>
	<atom:link href="https://james-the-obscure.github.io/category/science-medicine/feed" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://james-the-obscure.github.io/</link>
	<description>essays on culture, politics and technology</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Sat, 08 Feb 2025 03:29:31 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.7.2</generator>

<image>
	<url>https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/fav1-150x150.png</url>
	<title>science &amp; medicine &#8211; JAMES THE OBSCURE</title>
	<link>https://james-the-obscure.github.io/</link>
	<width>32</width>
	<height>32</height>
</image> 
	<item>
		<title>A QUANTUM OF DESPAIR</title>
		<link>https://james-the-obscure.github.io/a-quantum-of-despair</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[JtO]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 14 Dec 2024 23:36:35 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[doom]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[politics & culture]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[science & medicine]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://james-the-obscure.github.io/?p=529</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[What if science is becoming toxic to human society? &#160; In the summer of 1950, Nobel-winning nuclear physicist Enrico Fermi didn’t understand the scale of the cosmos as we understand it today. But he knew that it was at least hundreds of millions of light-years across, encompassing thousands of galaxies and more than a trillion<p><a class="readmore" href="https://james-the-obscure.github.io/a-quantum-of-despair"><span class="arrow-right icon"></span>Read More</a></p>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><em>What if science is becoming toxic to human society?</em></p>
<p><span id="more-529"></span></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>In the summer of 1950, Nobel-winning nuclear physicist Enrico Fermi didn’t understand the scale of the cosmos as we understand it today. But he knew that it was at least hundreds of millions of light-years across, encompassing thousands of galaxies and more than a trillion stellar systems. Unless Earth was a vanishingly rare exception, the universe should be teeming with life-forms, whose civilizations often would be far more advanced than ours.</p>
<p>And yet, as he asked his lunchmates at Los Alamos one day that summer, “where <em>is</em> everybody?” ET visitations to Earth seemed either absent entirely, or—even if some might be marked by UFO sightings—impossible to pin down as such. This discrepancy between the theoretical abundance of ETs and their observed scarcity or elusiveness became known as the Fermi Paradox.</p>
<p>Ponderers of this supposed conundrum have devised dozens if not hundreds of potential solutions. The most popular, unsurprisingly, are those that echo contemporary human concerns over climate change, nuclear war, rogue AI, etc., positing that such self-made disasters—and maybe also natural disasters like asteroid strikes and supervolcano eruptions—tend to extinguish civilizations before they can reach the star-faring stage. Elon Musk has made clear that he worries deeply about such hazards and hopes to minimize their impacts by making humans “multiplanetary,” for example by colonizing Mars.</p>
<p>The popular, accident-centered conjectures explaining the Fermi Paradox generally assume that in the absence of such cataclysms, civilizations will continue to advance scientifically and technologically, eventually venturing out to the stars. This premise also underlies the contemporary talk of a science- and tech-driven “Golden Age,” in which space travel will become routine.</p>
<p>But what if civilizations normally do <em>not</em> continue to advance beyond a stage of very limited and local space travel? What if the very process of scientific advancement in understanding the cosmos creates a toxic byproduct, analogous to pollutants from industrialization but psychological rather than chemical, such that people inevitably lose the will to explore that cosmos—and ultimately can survive only by regressing to static, relatively pre-scientific social forms?</p>
<p><strong>A Bizarre Conceit</strong></p>
<p>Although at first this might come across as unhinged doomerism, the idea that at least some important parts of science are psychologically toxic is an old and somewhat respectable one. Humans, plausibly as a condition of their civilization-building dynamism, tend to cling to a worldview in which they are very intelligent and special, there is higher “meaning” and “purpose” to their existence, and the universe is somehow about them. As philosophers have been pointing out for hundreds of years, science’s most consistent theme has been the refutation of this grandiose self-image: ”dissuading man from his former respect for himself, as if this had been nothing but a piece of bizarre conceit,” in the words of <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Genealogy-Morals-Ecce-Homo/dp/0679724621">Nietzsche</a>, who certainly did consider this a bizarre conceit:</p>
<p style="padding-left: 40px;"><a href="https://www.amazon.com/Daybreak-Thoughts-Prejudices-Cambridge-Philosophy/dp/0521599636">However</a> high mankind may have evolved &#8211; and perhaps at the end it will stand even lower than at the beginning! &#8211; it cannot pass over into a higher order, as little as the ant and the earwig can at the end of its &#8216;earthly course&#8217; rise up to kinship with God and eternal life. The becoming drags the has-been along behind it: why should an exception to this eternal spectacle be made on behalf of some little star or for any little species upon it! Away with such sentimentalities!</p>
<p>But can humanity survive without such sentimentalities, as science smashes them one by one?</p>
<p>It’s a tough question to answer, since it concerns an influence that probably works mostly beneath conscious awareness, in a psychosocial environment that is complex, to put it mildly. But one thing that seems obviously true of pretension-puncturing scientific discoveries is that they can take generations to “sink in.” Even evolutionary theory, which was already broadly accepted by scientists more than 150 years ago, does not yet seem to have fully replaced our ancient picture of ourselves as creatures made in God’s image. That delay may be attributable to powerful mechanisms of “denial,” to simple ignorance of science, to the residual competing influence of religion, and presumably also to various other socioeconomic factors that tend to counter or crowd out existential questions.</p>
<p>In any case, scientific advances that can create such “existential dissonance” tend to be relatively recent developments on the human timeline. Neuroscience’s refutation of our “free will” illusion occurred only in the last two decades, so unsurprisingly it has hardly begun to be assimilated into our self-image and our moral structures.</p>
<p>Among the sciences, cosmology is plausibly the greatest producer of existential dissonance, and in that sense its influence too has developed only recently. While it is often said that Copernicus demoted us from the center of the universe in the 1500s, his theory was not as revolutionary as it is commonly portrayed. The traditional, pre-Copernican model of the cosmos held that the Earth with its God-chosen beings lay at the center of existence, while all else revolved around it. Copernicus’s model made just one change, putting our sun at the center, which allowed a simpler, more elegant account of celestial motions even as it kept our stellar system in its place of supreme privilege. Thus, a fundamentally anthropocentric view of the universe continued to dominate cosmology—and as late as a century ago, astronomers still believed that the cosmos was very small and tidy, consisting of just our galaxy, with our solar system at or near the center.</p>
<p>It was only with the development, in the 1920s, of better techniques for measuring stellar distances that astronomers finally understood that the universe was much, much larger, consisting of multiple galaxies, among which ours held no special status—just as our Sun, in a spiral arm far from the Milky Way’s center, held no special status among its galactic peers.<a href="#_ednref1" name="_edn1"></a></p>
<p><img fetchpriority="high" decoding="async" class="aligncenter wp-image-538" src="https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/hubble.jpg" alt="" width="408" height="351" srcset="https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/hubble.jpg 476w, https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/hubble-300x258.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 408px) 100vw, 408px" /></p>
<p>That was a major change. Even so, when I was coming of age a half-century later, the scale of the universe still seemed somewhat manageable. Like millions of other children, I watched Carl Sagan’s <em>Cosmos</em> documentary series in the early 1980s, learning that the universe contains not just a handful of galaxies but at least tens of thousands of them, yet I wouldn’t say that that put an irreparable dent in my belief in human potential. It still seemed conceivable that mankind, with exponentially improving scientific knowledge and technology, could spread outward and someday comprehend—maybe even “conquer”—it all.</p>
<p>The expansion of our cosmic model was still just getting started, though. By the turn of the millennium, with the help of tools like the Hubble Telescope, standard models assumed billions of galaxies. Astronomers also were starting to use the term “observable universe” to delineate the space their telescopes could reach, which, despite its vastness, was apparently incomplete. Indeed, they increasingly embraced the idea that the universe is ever-expanding, and is not just tens or hundreds of billions of light years across but <em>infinite</em>—in all dimensions, presumably including dimensions we can’t perceive.</p>
<p>In a truly infinite cosmos, any local reality would have essentially identical variants elsewhere: “parallel worlds.” As physicist Brian Greene put it in his 2011 book <em>The Hidden Reality</em>, “I find it both curious and compelling that numerous developments in physics, if followed sufficiently far, bump into some variation on the parallel-universe theme.”</p>
<p><strong>MWI</strong></p>
<p>The best-known and most widely held parallel-world theory these days is the “Many Worlds Interpretation” (MWI), initially devised by Hugh Everett III (1930-1982) in the mid-1950s while he was a physics PhD student under John Wheeler at Princeton. Everett’s work was mostly ignored while he was alive, though other physicists, notably Bryce DeWitt and David Deutsch, did much to popularize it later among physicists and the general public—and to extend it and give it its present name.</p>
<p>MWI is called an “interpretation” because it tries to make sense of a conundrum at the heart of quantum mechanics: In certain types of experiment, any quantum-scale particle such as an electron or a photon seems to possess an innate <em>multiplicity</em>. In other words, it manifests as a ghostly ensemble of particles (with different positions and velocities) and only when an experimenter tries to detect it more directly does it stop acting like a ghostly ensemble and resolve to just one particle. The leading interpretation in quantum mechanics’ first half-century or so was that this “collapse” to just one state is induced by the experimenter’s act of observation, and that the other, left-behind states are somehow not real. Everett proposed instead that all these states are real and essentially represent <em>different versions</em> of the particle that end up being captured—by different versions of the experimenter—in different universes. In short, MWI holds that reality consists of multiple universes, in which, collectively, anything that can happen does happen.</p>
<p>Everett’s idea was rejected at first, as new ideas that threaten the status quo and its defenders typically are. But the reaction to MWI wasn’t just the usual circling of the wagons by the old guard. Even many who admired the theory’s elegance were discomfited by it. As Oxford philosopher of physics Simon Saunders said to a reporter in 2007, “The multiverse will drive you crazy if you really think about how it affects your life, and I can’t live like that. I’ll just accept Everett and then think about something else, to save my sanity.”</p>
<p>Still, MWI was and remains elegant and consistent with experimental results. As alternative interpretations of quantum mechanics have fallen by the wayside, it has risen steadily in popularity, not just among physicists but also among science popularizers—and popular audiences, as suggested by the success of the MWI-themed 2023 movie <em>Everything Everywhere All at Once</em>.</p>
<p>MWI recently received further support when Google reported a “quantum supremacy” demonstration by its experimental quantum computer Willow. A feat of quantum supremacy is a feat that a quantum computer—whose computational bits exist not as discrete 0 or 1 bits but in ghostly superpositions of both—can achieve that an ordinary “classical” computer can never match. It is regarded as an empirical proof that quantum computing is real, which for many physicists also bolsters the validity of MWI, because the idea of quantum computing—first developed by Deutsch in the mid 1980s—is that such computers gain their advantage in effect by performing computations across different universes.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-530" src="https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/hn-quote.jpg" alt="" width="764" height="165" srcset="https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/hn-quote.jpg 764w, https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/hn-quote-300x65.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 764px) 100vw, 764px" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">—from Google Quantum AI blog post 9 Dec 2024</p>
<p><strong>A Concealed Toxicity</strong></p>
<p>The scientific and technical elites who have brought us these developments have been, at best, silent about their implications, and at worst, actively deceptive—although maybe they have been deceiving themselves too. As I was rewatching <em>Cosmos</em> (1980) recently, I noticed it was now prefaced by Ann Druyan, Sagan’s widow and a writer and director on the series, who invokes the “soaring spiritual high” of science’s “central revelation: our oneness with the universe.” Essentially every mainstream author or commentator on cosmology has had similarly upbeat things to say—about the beauty of the universe, and/or the cleverness of humans in their recent leaps of discovery. This is not <em>just</em> self-deception—these experts have to sell books and other media content, and publishers want positive themes.</p>
<p>But it <em>is</em> all deceptive. Why? Because, again, science’s central revelation—cosmology’s especially—is the insignificance of humanity, and for MWI and other infinite-cosmos theories this is not just a relative insignificance but an <em>absolute</em>, one-over-infinity insignificance.</p>
<p>The MWI cosmos is, in a technical sense, more splendid and elegant than anything found in human religion. What could be more perfect, what could be more complete, than an infinitude in which everything that can happen does happen? The problem is that this perfect completeness, or maybe unendingness, leaves no room for “purpose,” “meaning,” or “achievement” in any substantive sense. It also mocks our childish notion that we could somehow explore and/or “conquer” it all.</p>
<p>In fact, MWI implies that there is no higher purpose or meaning to any human being’s actions or existence, other than by filling out, in an infinitesimal way, the infinite space of possibility. Are you a good person in this universe? Are you “successful”? How can this be substantially meaningful (from the perspective of a Creator who transcends the multiverse), if otherwise indistinguishable variants of you are bad and unsuccessful in other universes—and presumably average to a mediocrity across all instances? When you combine this “MWI view” with the modern neuroscientific view of behavior—as being determined moment-to-moment by innumerable, mostly subconscious factors while our conscious selves stand by as purblind spectators—you start to get a picture of humans as “non-player-character” (NPC) automata in a sort of video game with infinite parallel playthroughs.</p>
<p>To the extent that people see themselves and their lives from this perspective, they are likely to lose a lot of their motivations for doing things—and not just the great and ambitious things but also the ordinary, pro-social behaviors that keep societies from coming unglued. Such behaviors are rooted in concepts of good and bad, meaning and purpose, and MWI erodes all that as completely as would a revelation that we live in a simulation.</p>
<p>MWI defies our traditional self-image so starkly and extensively that it also calls into question the “<em>sapiens sapiens</em>” label we have given ourselves. Perhaps, when compared to other civ-building species in our galaxy, we aren’t very smart at all. Perhaps our simple ape brains are already nearing the limits of what they can do—limits that fall well short of what even the most basic star-faring endeavors require.</p>
<p><strong>Signs of Despair</strong></p>
<p>Again, big changes in our understanding of our place in the cosmos can take generations to sink in, and MWI and other infinite-cosmos notions began seeping into the popular mind only recently. It may be that only children born in this millennium are being—and have been—forced to confront these ideas in a substantial way during the impressionable years when their models of the world and moral structures come together. If so, it may take another decade or two for this particular form of despair to be recognized as a mass phenomenon, distinguishable from all the other forms of despair out there.</p>
<p>In the meantime, despair is undoubtedly prevalent in our materially prosperous civilization, particularly among the young. “Adolescent mental health continues to worsen” <a href="https://www.cdc.gov/healthy-youth/mental-health/index.html">reads</a> a recent CDC headline, over a story that notes that in 2023 about 40% of American students had “persistent feelings of sadness or hopelessness.” A commission set up by <em>Lancet Psychiatry</em> issued a <a href="https://www.thelancet.com/commissions/youth-mental-health">report</a> last summer concluding that “in many countries, the mental health of young people has been declining over the past two decades, signalling a warning that global megatrends and changes in many societies are increasing mental ill health.” Whatever is driving this pandemic of despair and depression seems also to be promoting “nihilism” and “doomerism&#8221; among the same youthful demographic.<img decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-531" src="https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/nihil-trend.jpg" alt="" width="769" height="226" srcset="https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/nihil-trend.jpg 769w, https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/nihil-trend-300x88.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 769px) 100vw, 769px" /></p>
<p><a href="#_ednref1" name="_edn1"></a><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="aligncenter wp-image-540" src="https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/nihil2.jpg" alt="" width="580" height="76" srcset="https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/nihil2.jpg 504w, https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/nihil2-300x39.jpg 300w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 580px) 100vw, 580px" /></p>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-539" src="https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/nihilism-1.jpg" alt="" width="776" height="331" srcset="https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/nihilism-1.jpg 776w, https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/nihilism-1-300x128.jpg 300w, https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/nihilism-1-768x328.jpg 768w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 776px) 100vw, 776px" /></p>
<p>While this putative trend may be attributable mostly to other social and economic disruptions of recent decades—from electronic media overexposure to the high cost of family formation—perhaps some is being driven by science, which after all has been moving in the same direction, displacing religiously based beliefs and ethics, for centuries now. In any case, despair caused by other factors is treatable in principle, whereas the one served up by science seems incurable.</p>
<p>One of my premises here is that the people who built Western civilization couldn’t have done so without believing, at least subconciously, that there is (or probably is) meaning and purpose in life and the universe. If so, then removing that sense of meaning and purpose would likely remove that civ-building dynamism our ancestors had, and the only way to recover meaning and purpose—perhaps the only way for humans to survive, in the long-term—would be to renounce and suppress most science and technology and revert to more primitive social forms.</p>
<p>One would expect to see this cultural arrest and regress play out first in the Western societies that have been the most diligent in jettisoning religion. And indeed, the essentially post-Christian societies of Northwestern Europe now look pretty moribund in most respects compared to their peers; certainly, they lack the “ad astra” energy of the contemporary USA.</p>
<p>The current hoopla over AI raises the question: Couldn’t we create advanced robots and robotic starships that self-replicate and relentlessly explore outer space, without regard for the apparent pointlessness of the endeavor—in fact, without any emotion at all? Yes, in principle, if we could remain motivated long enough to develop the necessary AI and robotics tech. But autonomous robot exploration is not the same as human exploration. Moreover, it’s not hard to imagine these clever creations eventually finishing off their depressed, listless, impotent creators, in a perfect and final example of a “cure” that kills the patient.</p>
<p>The idea that cosmology and other key branches of science eventually become toxic to a technological society offers a solution to Fermi’s Paradox because it is plausible that not only humans but also other intelligent species that emerge in the cosmos and start venturing into space face this same problem—this fundamental conflict between, on the one hand, the self-delusions needed for basic civilization-building and progress, and on the other, the delusion-bursting science needed to reach the stars.</p>
<p>Incidentally, cosmology’s hint about our relative inferiority as a species suggests another, complementary solution: The few star-faring civs that do exist in our vicinity either do not care about us, or, even if they are curious enough to visit, don’t waste time trying to communicate—firstly because we are too primitive to process what they would have to say, and secondly because almost anything they <em>could</em> convey, particularly regarding the nature of the cosmos, would injure us.<strong> </strong></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">***</p>
<p><a href="#_ftnref1" name="_ftn1"></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>ACTORS AND ADDICTION</title>
		<link>https://james-the-obscure.github.io/actors-and-addiction</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[JtO]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 12 Feb 2011 05:58:09 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[science & medicine]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://james-the-obscure.github.io/?p=172</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Some thoughts on the &#8220;celebrities&#8217; disease&#8221; Originally published February 12, 2011 &#160; I&#8217;d be sitting in a big beach house in Malibu, living the Charlie Harper life, if I had a nickel for every time I read about a celebrity who’s allegedly or admittedly hooked on booze or pills or coke or meth or some<p><a class="readmore" href="https://james-the-obscure.github.io/actors-and-addiction"><span class="arrow-right icon"></span>Read More</a></p>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><em>Some thoughts on the &#8220;celebrities&#8217; disease&#8221;<br />
</em></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-175" src="https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/lilo-in-court.jpg" alt="" width="260" height="373" srcset="https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/lilo-in-court.jpg 260w, https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/lilo-in-court-209x300.jpg 209w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 260px) 100vw, 260px" /></p>
<p><span id="more-172"></span></p>
<p><span style="color: #ff6600;"><em>Originally published February 12, 2011</em></span></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>I&#8217;d be sitting in a big beach house in Malibu, living the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Charlie_Harper_%28Two_and_a_Half_Men%29">Charlie Harper</a> life, if I had a nickel for every time I read about a celebrity who’s allegedly or admittedly hooked on booze or pills or coke or meth or some such substance. What is it about these people that makes them so inordinately likely to get addicted? If half the stories in the media are true, substance abuse among actors and rock stars is basically pandemic&#8212;certainly much more prevalent than the roughly one-in-eight rate recorded among <a href="http://www.oas.samhsa.gov/2k7/popDensity/popDensity.htm">Native Americans</a>, who are the most addiction-prone demographic group identified in official stats (probably because no one has thought to consider celebrities as a separate demographic group).</p>
<p>The more I ponder this question, though, the more I wonder how some actors and other performers <em>resist</em> addiction&#8212;considering how many factors there are in their lives that push them into that behavioral trap.</p>
<p>From the most obvious (to me), to the least obvious:</p>
<p><strong>#1. Asynchronous lives</strong></p>
<p>Successful actors rarely have normal working routines. Their schedules bring to mind that saying about the lot of soldiers in war&#8212;brief moments of intensity punctuating long stretches of boredom. That boredom has to be endured somehow, and drugs and booze are the classic tools for making time pass swiftly.</p>
<p><strong>#2. Surrounded by enablers</strong></p>
<p>Being rich and famous usually means getting your way ~100% of the time. People just don’t say “no” to a celebrity. So in addition to having a greater need for drugs, they have less trouble getting them. Even when they run up against the law, they tend to get extra slack&#8212;not just because they can afford expensive lawyers but because they are who they are.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-176" src="https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/easy-does-it-miss-hilton.jpg" alt="" width="200" height="296" /></p>
<p><strong>#3. Capacity for self-control grows weaker.</strong></p>
<p>Self-control, mediated largely through prefrontal cortex (PFC) structures in the brain, is now <a href="http://www.nature.com/news/2009/090304/full/458025a.html">recognized </a>as one of the keys to resisting addiction. But self-control is like a muscle&#8212;you gotta use it or lose it. Living a pampered, empowered celebrity life as an adult means <a href="http://online.wsj.com/article/SB10001424052748704407804575425561952689390.html">losing</a> it.</p>
<p><strong>#4. Development of adult self-control may be blocked if you were/are a child celebrity.</strong></p>
<p>Childhood and early adulthood comprise the period of life when your basic capacity for self-control is still being formed, via the development of the PFC, the last brain region to mature. If you go through that period with little need to exercise self-control, and frequently hit your brain with alcohol and lots of recreational drugs (which tend to weaken the PFC&#8217;s restraining influence on behavior), then by the time you reach adulthood, you and your functionally impaired PFC might be permanently incapable of ever having a normal, modern, adult level of self-control&#8212;just as a childhood polio victim with underdeveloped legs will never run a marathon.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-177" src="https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/drew-barrymore-all-growed-up.jpg" alt="" width="320" height="488" srcset="https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/drew-barrymore-all-growed-up.jpg 320w, https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/drew-barrymore-all-growed-up-197x300.jpg 197w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 320px) 100vw, 320px" /></p>
<p><strong>#5. Exposure to a hugely powerful gateway drug: fame.</strong></p>
<p>Shortly after Michael Jackson died, I heard someone&#8212;Liz Taylor?&#8212;quote something he had told her once about being on stage in front of thousands of screaming fans: It had given him a bigger rush than any drug.</p>
<p>I can believe it. But even celebs can’t be on stage, in front of the fans and the paps and getting that intense fame rush, every day. For some of them, the fame-lulls must be hard to endure without artificial stimulation.</p>
<p>I’d guess that the hardest fame-lull of all to endure is the one that comes with the final, permanent slide into obsolescence, when the fame rush can no longer be attained in the normal way, and one&#8217;s agent won&#8217;t return one&#8217;s calls, and drugs (or reality-TV infamy?) are the only options. Drugs are often blamed for ending celebrities’ careers, but I&#8217;d guess that in many cases the career slide starts first, prompting more and more drug use, and then the vicious, quickening spiral of personal and money and legal troubles, bad press, rehab, and career oblivion.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-178" src="https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/hoff.jpg" alt="" width="222" height="227" /></p>
<p><strong>#6. Low self-control is probably already in their genes.</strong></p>
<p>The development of a high capacity for self-control is arguably one of the proudest achievements of Western peoples and their culture. Even for small children a high degree of self control is a remarkably strong <a href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/20855294">predictor </a>of future success in the modern world. But there seem to be a few narrow areas of modern life in which low-self-control people still thrive.</p>
<p>I’m referring to performers&#8212;actors and musicians, mainly, but also some athletes&#8212;and it seems plausible that when they are performing, their innate lack of inhibition or their ability to switch it off at will becomes a bonus. It enables them to access and develop talents that the rest of us can only dream about.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-179" src="https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/Darryl-Strawberry-Mug-Shot.jpg" alt="" width="184" height="262" /></p>
<p>David Foster Wallace touched on this in an essay, “<a href="https://www.scribd.com/doc/134106158/How-Tracy-Austin-Broke-My-Heart-David-Foster-Wallace">How Tracy Austin Broke My Heart</a>:”</p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px;">It is not an accident that great athletes are often called “naturals” because they can, in performance, be totally present: they can proceed on instinct and muscle-memory and autonomic will such that action and agent are one.</p>
<p>As far as I can tell, there is hardly any empirical evidence for this idea, although that may be only because hardly anyone has formally and rigorously looked into it. <a href="http://scholarworks.umass.edu/dissertations/AAI3136735/">This</a> 2004 U-Mass PhD dissertation on football players and impulsivity reported that:</p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px;">Players’ scores of functional impulsivity related to their athletic success; players who reported that they like to make split-second decisions and take advantage of unexpected opportunities were also more likely to be rated positively by a professional scout, play and start in games, and survive in the NFL.</p>
<p>The idea that people with ADHD&#8212;closely related to impulsivity&#8212;have an edge in sports has also been <a href="http://www.huffingtonpost.com/garret-loporto/secret-to-us-olympic-gold_b_471670.html">bouncing</a> around, although, again, more as a common-sense observation than as an experimentally tested scientific finding.</p>
<p>It may be hard for us ordinary folks to see at first why innate impulsivity could be so important in these public performance contexts. We in the modern West are so used to watching pro ballgames and Hollywood feature films that I think we are largely unaware of the surreal intensity of what is going on, physically and emotionally, on the field and on the screen. It&#8217;s just not easy for most of us to operate at that level, though. We would hold back or freeze up.</p>
<p>Here&#8217;s Wallace on his own inhibitory issues during minor competitive tennis matches:</p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px;">Ever try to concentrate on doing something difficult with a crowd of people watching? &#8230; worse, with a crowd of spectators maybe all vocally hoping you fail so that their favorite will beat you? In my own comparatively low-level junior matches, before audiences that rarely hit three digits, it used to be all I could do to manage my sphincter. I would drive myself crazy: &#8220;&#8230;but what if I double-fault here and go down a break with all these folks watching?&#8221;&#8230;</p>
<p>Now, obviously, some actors and athletes have had to exert a substantial amount of self-control&#8212;e.g., in being disciplined enough to practice their skills&#8212;to get where they wanted to go, and in that sense they should be less impulsive and more resistant to addiction. Yet there may be something about repeated performance, in which the usual prefrontal restraints are forced to fall away and action becomes efficient and instinctive, that has the opposite effect. Check out this passage from an acting coach’s <a href="http://acting-blog.com/tag/acting-on-impulse/">blog</a>:</p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px;">If the actor is to allow themselves to follow their impulses without blockages, then the self-editing, self-criticism and self-abuse of self-consciousness must be sidestepped. The actor must respond freely within the truth of the moment.</p>
<p>I.e., <em>just do it</em>, and don&#8217;t get all prefrontal and inhibited about it. Logically, if you practice this sort of thing enough, it will, so to speak, come naturally, and you will follow your impulses without blockages, and maybe without being able to get those &#8220;blockages&#8221; back again, even when you need them.</p>
<p>Stimulant drugs actually force this disinhibitory process in the brain, and in that sense can be a performance-enhancer. That&#8217;s probably why cocaine traditionally has been so popular among actors and other performers, particularly those doing live shows. As a kid I used to wonder why top comedians doing stand-up&#8212;e.g., Tim Allen, Robin Williams, Steve Martin&#8212;so often looked watery-eyed.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-409" src="https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/tim-allen-mugshot.jpg" alt="" width="439" height="524" srcset="https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/tim-allen-mugshot.jpg 439w, https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/tim-allen-mugshot-251x300.jpg 251w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 439px) 100vw, 439px" /></p>
<p>The key point here, though, and the sad irony, is that even without practicing impulsivity or forcing it with drugs, an <em>inborn</em> impulsivity, in the right environment and with the right mix of other talents, may lift a person to the realm of fame and fortune&#8212;yet leave him or her defenseless against the life-ruining temptations that lie in wait there.</p>
<p>Why isn&#8217;t this studied more? Why don&#8217;t the researchers who currently study, say, the causes of Native Americans&#8217; high addiction rates, turn their attention to the Hollywood tribe or to former elite athletes? How about substance-use prevalence analyses, and genome-wide association studies, among these celebrities and their offspring? I suspect that if such studies could ever be done, we&#8217;d conclude from them that celebrity, at least medically speaking, is something to be feared more than desired.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-180" src="https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/tara-reid.jpg" alt="" width="170" height="296" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="aligncenter wp-image-182" src="https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/rip-torn-and-smushed.jpg" alt="" width="158" height="158" srcset="https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/rip-torn-and-smushed.jpg 450w, https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/rip-torn-and-smushed-150x150.jpg 150w, https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/rip-torn-and-smushed-300x300.jpg 300w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 158px) 100vw, 158px" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-183" src="https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/Charlie-Sheen-mug-shot.jpg" alt="" width="150" height="150" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-184" src="https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/Paris-Hilton1.jpg" alt="" width="250" height="167" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-185" src="https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/Kirsten-Dunst.jpg" alt="" width="200" height="449" srcset="https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/Kirsten-Dunst.jpg 200w, https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/Kirsten-Dunst-134x300.jpg 134w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 200px) 100vw, 200px" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-thumbnail wp-image-186" src="https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/Miley-Cyrus-with-bong-150x150.jpg" alt="" width="150" height="150" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-thumbnail wp-image-187" src="https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/Robert-Downey-Jr-mug-shot-150x150.jpg" alt="" width="150" height="150" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-188" src="https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/Britney-Spears.jpg" alt="" width="320" height="324" srcset="https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/Britney-Spears.jpg 320w, https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/Britney-Spears-296x300.jpg 296w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 320px) 100vw, 320px" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-189" src="https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/James-Brown-mug-shot.jpg" alt="" width="200" height="200" srcset="https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/James-Brown-mug-shot.jpg 200w, https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/James-Brown-mug-shot-150x150.jpg 150w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 200px) 100vw, 200px" /></p>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="aligncenter wp-image-190 size-full" src="https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/Heather-Locklear-mug-shot.jpg" alt="" width="200" height="250" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-191" src="https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/Mickey-Rourke.jpg" alt="" width="234" height="261" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-192" src="https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/Nick-Nolte-mug-shot.jpg" alt="" width="189" height="267" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-193" src="https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/Glenn-Campbell-mug-shot.jpg" alt="" width="200" height="300" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-194" src="https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/Mischa-Barton.jpg" alt="" width="175" height="301" srcset="https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/Mischa-Barton.jpg 175w, https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/Mischa-Barton-174x300.jpg 174w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 175px) 100vw, 175px" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-195" src="https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/Winona-Ryder.jpg" alt="" width="175" height="255" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-196" src="https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/Randy-Quaid-mug-shot.jpg" alt="" width="190" height="260" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-197" src="https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/Amy-Winehouse.jpg" alt="" width="200" height="145" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-198" src="https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/Nicole-Snooki-Polizzi.jpg" alt="" width="240" height="240" srcset="https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/Nicole-Snooki-Polizzi.jpg 240w, https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/Nicole-Snooki-Polizzi-150x150.jpg 150w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 240px) 100vw, 240px" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-199" src="https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/Nicole-Ritchie-mug-shot.jpg" alt="" width="200" height="250" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-200" src="https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/Courtney-Love.jpg" alt="" width="225" height="225" srcset="https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/Courtney-Love.jpg 225w, https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/Courtney-Love-150x150.jpg 150w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 225px) 100vw, 225px" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-201" src="https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/Kate-Moss.jpg" alt="" width="228" height="300" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-202" src="https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/La-Dolce-Vita.jpg" alt="" width="220" height="288" /></p>
<p><span style="color: #ff0000;"><em> </em></span></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>JACQUES VALLEE AND THE PROBLEMS OF UFOLOGY</title>
		<link>https://james-the-obscure.github.io/jacques-vallee-and-the-problems-of-ufology</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[JtO]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 20 Jan 2011 15:49:51 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[science & medicine]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[woo woo]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://james-the-obscure.github.io/?p=483</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[A few close criticisms of the constructive kind … Originally published 20 January 2011 I was just a kid when Close Encounters came out, but I remember thinking, even then, how cool it would be to have a serious, well-equipped government operation like the one depicted in the film. A bit unusually for its time,<p><a class="readmore" href="https://james-the-obscure.github.io/jacques-vallee-and-the-problems-of-ufology"><span class="arrow-right icon"></span>Read More</a></p>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><em>A few close criticisms of the constructive kind …</em></p>
<p><span id="more-483"></span></p>
<p><span style="color: #ff0000;"><em>Originally published 20 January 2011</em></span></p>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-97" src="https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/vallee.jpg" alt="" width="167" height="221" /></p>
<p>I was just a kid when <em>Close Encounters</em> came out, but I remember thinking, even then, how cool it would be to have a serious, well-equipped government operation like the one depicted in the film. A bit unusually for its time, <em>Close Encounters</em> created a sort of ideal world in which the Feds were reasonably competent and benign, had good reasons for keeping their secrets, and approached the UFO phenomenon with a wonderfully organized, can-do spirit.</p>
<p>Spielberg’s film also created an ideal top ufologist, the Claude Lacombe character, who was played in the movie by Francois Truffaut. I remember being particularly interested to learn that he was based on a real person, Jacques Vallee, whose writings evidently had impressed Spielberg.</p>
<p>Years later I looked into the burgeoning “alien abduction” scene in America, but concluded that most of what was happening there was happening on the couches of abduction “therapists” and in the fertile imaginations of “abductees.” I never really got into what I considered the more serious and interesting side of ufology, the study of sightings and close encounters: the Jacques Vallee stuff.</p>
<p>Nearly two decades on, I’ve started to delve into the ufology literature again in my spare time, beginning with two of Vallee’s best-known books, <em>Dimensions</em> and <em>Confrontations</em>. I hope soon to read his new one, <em>Wonders in the Sky</em>, which I understand is an updated version of <em>Passport to Magonia</em>, his 1969 classic. But already I have a few critical observations about Vallee and ufology (and even about Spielberg), and if someone else hasn’t raised these points already, maybe some ufologists will find them useful.</p>
<p><strong>1. Beware the lone scientist</strong></p>
<p>The Frenchness of the <em>Close Encounters</em> character Claude Lacombe made him seem a man apart&#8212;a lone, heroic scientist. But in the reality of the film, he wasn’t alone; he was surrounded by other scientists as well as by engineers, doctors and other technical people. So it is in real life with normal scientists. They work on teams, in effect, in vast leagues with lots of rules, and just about everything they do can be, and frequently is, questioned by their fellow scientists&#8212;in the lab, via e-mail, at conferences, in the peer-review gauntlet before publication, in the commentaries after publication, and in the to-ings and fro-ings of the grant-proposal process. You know that expression, “it takes a village”? Well, modern scientists live in something like a village, where nosy people are always looking over their shoulders, watching for mistakes. In that world, mistakes can bring very serious professional consequences.</p>
<p>Naturally, that intense critical culture tends to keep modern scientists on their toes. But the lone scientist doesn’t have that assistance. The lone scientist often doesn&#8217;t even address his writings to fellow scientists, but instead addresses a popular audience. Thus the lone scientist has to rely, for the most part, on his own internalization of scientific culture. And for most of us, over a long stretch, that just isn’t going to be enough.</p>
<p>I think that explains why, as I read Vallee’s writings on UFOs, I was almost immediately reminded of Terence Meaden and &#8216;crop circles&#8217;.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-94" src="https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/meaden.jpg" alt="" width="378" height="341" srcset="https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/meaden.jpg 378w, https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/meaden-300x271.jpg 300w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 378px) 100vw, 378px" /></p>
<p>Meaden had been a physics professor at a Canadian university before coming home to the UK and, among other things, taking up his crop circles investigations. He tried to interest other researchers in the circles phenomenon&#8212;he reached out to professional atmospheric physicists as far away as Tokyo and Oklahoma. But he was basically on his own, a lone scientist, and we all know what happened: A bit of methodological laxity crept in, a bit of hubris&#8212;that “trust me, I’m a scientist” stuff&#8212;and before he knew it, he was being led down the proverbial garden path by two old guys with ropes and planks.</p>
<p>And just so it’s clear, I’m not really blaming Meaden. I think that what happened to him might well have happened to any scientist in his shoes&#8212;any scientist brave enough to pursue one of these offbeat phenomena with little or no cultural support.</p>
<p>For the same reason, I don’t really blame Vallee for what I see as the shortcomings of his own work. I just think it’s worth pointing out that he was operating in an intellectually hazardous, “lone scientist” situation, especially after the US government officially gave up on its UFO investigations in 1968.</p>
<p>What are the shortcomings of Vallee’s work? I don’t think a full list is necessary, but the gist is pretty much the same as in Meaden’s case: Vallee emphasizes his scientific background and claims to use scientific methods, but then he routinely holds up, as “evidence,” cases that, in my opinion, an ordinary scientist would not even consider&#8212;because they rest on very-lightly-confirmed or even unconfirmed testimony, often rendered years after the supposed event. For example:</p>
<p style="padding-left: 40px;">An Army officer who served during the Korean war has described an even more remarkable incident in which an orange luminous object came over a village that was being shelled by a whole artillery unit in the Iron Triangle area. It hovered at low altitude, apparently unharmed by the powerful explosions…. The next day the entire artillery unit was violently ill and had to be removed from duty, but no formal report was ever submitted to identify the source of the strange illness.</p>
<p>Apparently neither Vallee nor the original <a href="http://www.rense.com/ufo/1korea.htm">investigator</a> thought it necessary to confirm this tale with other members of the unit before publishing it.</p>
<p>And that is an almost random example I have selected by flipping through the pages. Vallee also gives his readers many inherently dubious witness-testimony stories from South America. In fact, the Brazilian case with which Vallee grandly leads off <em>Confrontations </em>comes across not as a likely UFO encounter but as a likely UFO-cult suicide. He spends some pages, too, on the famous Dr. X case in France, which does not seem to have unequivocal evidence of UFO involvement, but seems to belong more in the spirit-possession/shamanic-transformation genre. (Frankly, some of the adventures of Dr. X, to which Dr. X is almost always the sole witness, remind me of the antics of the notorious &#8220;UFO abductee&#8221; <a href="http://www.unexplainable.net/artman/publish/article_2573.shtml">Linda &#8220;Cortile&#8221;</a>.)</p>
<p>In <em>Dimensions </em>there are quite a few historic accounts, and many are interesting, but again, they don&#8217;t always provide much in the way of conclusive or even useful evidence. Vallee for some reason includes such tales as the so-called “miracle of Guadeloupe.” Speaking of which, just consider the “miraculous” image below; does it look like something that was made by UFO beings and thus belongs in the ufological literature? Or does it look like something painted by an all-too-human 16th century artist, presumably with Church support?</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-93" src="https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/guadeloupe.jpg" alt="" width="300" height="513" srcset="https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/guadeloupe.jpg 300w, https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/guadeloupe-175x300.jpg 175w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /></p>
<p>This pattern of rather soft thinking seems to continue in Vallee’s writings today, e.g., in his recent <a href="http://boingboing.net/2010/03/23/in-search-of-alien-g.html#previouspost">musings </a>on the causes of crop circles&#8212;next to which, Terence Meaden’s own hypotheses about linearly-sweeping atmospheric plasma vortices seem conservative.</p>
<p>On the whole, I&#8217;m glad that Vallee took the trouble to do all his research, much of which is fascinating and thought-provoking. His non-ET hypothesis about the UFO phenomenon certainly seems worth bearing in mind. But it’s important to understand that, though we might wish to believe otherwise (check out this <a href="http://boingboing.net/2009/11/18/jacques-vallee-on-bo.html">homage </a>to him on Boing-Boing), Vallee never was a Claude-Lacombe-type scientist, and, in his relatively lonely situation, maybe never could have been. If there’s a constructive lesson here it’s that ufology, ideally, should not look to such lone, “heroic” researchers but instead to the development of a society of researchers&#8212;a society bound by a fairly strict culture, and by regular interactions that help them maintain that strictness in their work.</p>
<p><strong>2. The TMI problem</strong></p>
<p>By far the largest problem with Vallee’s work, as I see it, is the lack of “editing” of cases. And I think it’s fair to say that that same lack of editing is practiced in the rest of ufology. I’m not channelling Phil Klass here; I’m not suggesting that all UFO cases should be dumped out and that the whole phenomenon’s a crock. I’m saying that there are plenty of very good UFO cases, and that they shouldn’t be crowded out by the weak and dubious ones.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-95" src="https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/rouen-saucer-1957.jpg" alt="" width="175" height="120" /></p>
<p>I guess that ufologists will always want to note down almost every UFO-related claim in their databases, and there is nothing wrong with that. But if I could get them to do just one thing differently, it would be to confine their published analyses and the majority of their resources to cases that involve <em>multiple, independent witnesses&#8212;</em>and especially independently obtained film, photos or radar records. Otherwise, they run an unacceptably high risk that their conception of the phenomenon will be (and is being) distorted by hoaxes, hallucinations, and so forth&#8212;in addition to the fact that promoting weak cases makes ufologists look unserious. (Maybe in another post, I will go over some of the evidence regarding hallucinations, which are much more common in the population than ufologists seem to realize.)</p>
<p>The value of having multiple witnesses is obvious, but the value of having <em>independent </em>witnesses seems to be overlooked much of the time. Years ago, some friends and I went out one night and made a crop circle near Avebury in England. The next day, campers in the area reported having seen “strange lights” over the hill where we made the circle. I have the advantage of knowing that no such lights appeared in connection with the making of the circle, but even without that advantage, ufologists should give little weight to such after-the-fact reports, because they are <em>not independent&#8212;</em>they are connected to, and very possibly triggered by, the initial event in question. Unfortunately, Vallee’s caseload, and the UFO lore generally, are full of questionable reports like these.</p>
<p><strong>3. Attempt Less, Achieve More</strong></p>
<p>Vallee’s listed “reasons” for believing in his non-ET hypothesis often read as non-sequiturs, e.g.:</p>
<p>The total number of close encounters far exceeds the requirements for a sophisticated survey of our planet.</p>
<p>Of course, for all we know, UFO sightings could mark the arrivals of millions of distinct, highly developed species, travelling by a variety of modes and with a variety of motives&#8212;from surveying to tourism and even joke-playing (<em>hey, let’s have some fun and start a religion among these dumb savages</em>). But I imagine that other ufologists by now have pointed out the obvious flaws in Vallee’s theorizing. And in any case, I doubt that ufologists should even bother with ambitious analyses of their data and the development of grand theories.</p>
<p>The first reason has to do with our limitations as a species. As one of Stanislaw Lem’s characters puts it in <em>Solaris</em>, “Any attempt to understand the motivation of these occurrences is blocked by our own anthropomorphism. Where there are no men, there cannot be motives accessible to men.”</p>
<p>The second reason has to do with ufology’s particular limitations. Ufologists today generally do not have the sophisticated resources needed to collect a lot of data about the nature of alien spacecraft, if that is what these objects are. On the other hand, the scientific community <em>does </em>have these resources. Yet the scientific community has long been scared away from the UFO subject.</p>
<p>Therefore, as I see it, modern, amateur-driven ufology would accomplish a great deal simply by persuading the scientific community to get involved. They could do that by focussing on a few, unimpeachable cases (which in my view, definitely excludes Roswell), and even moreso by gathering new unimpeachable evidence, for example multiple, independent video recordings&#8212;preferably fine-grained enough to resolve shapes and structural details. With such evidence, they should simply get in Congress’s face, and in the scientific community’s face, until attention is paid and resources are devoted. Easier said than done, I know! But it seems to me that if this becomes their main focus, they have a greater likelihood of achieving something than they do at present.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-99" src="https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/et.jpg" alt="" width="399" height="299" srcset="https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/et.jpg 399w, https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/et-300x225.jpg 300w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 399px) 100vw, 399px" /></p>
<p><strong>4. The Spielberg Effect</strong></p>
<p>One last quick thing I want to mention: Thanks largely to Spielberg, the world of Hollywood movies is one in which politicians and scientists tend to take&#8212;and are often abruptly forced to take&#8212;the UFO phenomenon seriously. I have seen other writers comment to the effect that Spielberg and other filmmakers have thereby helped the world to accept this phenomenon.</p>
<p>I disagree. In the early part of <em>Close Encounters</em>, and in his later films, Spielberg showed his frustration with the official, government, sweep-the-stuff-under-the-rug attitude towards UFOs. So partly his work has been a reaction to a trend that was already in place at least from the late 1960s. But I think the popular phenomenon he has stoked has also worsened the situation, by making it harder for the scientific community to take UFOs seriously again.</p>
<p>Scientists start out as kids too, and enjoy watching films such as <em>Close Encounters</em>. I suspect that a lot of them would secretly love to do some serious ufology. In the days when UFOs were taken halfway seriously at official levels in the US, ufology might even have been a plausible career choice. As I understand it, ufology then was much more of a “techie” activity, involving lots of aerospace and physics guys with horn-rimmed glasses and slide rules. But since then, thanks largely to Spielberg and others in Hollywood, ufology&#8212;or UFO &#8220;enthusiasm&#8221; anyway&#8212;has become surrounded by a less technical, more popular, New Agey, <em>just-gotta-believe</em> culture, which I think is essentially repellent to scientists and other technically trained people.</p>
<p>Thus mainstream science may never pay attention to UFOs, until perhaps, as in so many movies, it is suddenly forced to by the phenomenon itself. If that happens, all the contributions of Vallee and other ufologists could end up being simply ignored, and ultimately forgotten.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><em> </em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>THE BANDWAGON EFFECT</title>
		<link>https://james-the-obscure.github.io/the-bandwagon-effect</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[JtO]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 12 Mar 2008 15:30:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[politics & culture]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[science & medicine]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://james-the-obscure.github.io/?p=71</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[A mental contagion that afflicts our politics more than ever. Originally published March 12, 2008 &#160; &#160; Decades ago, at the dawn of the television age, Marshall McLuhan described what was happening as Western society overhauled its 500-year-old nervous system, replacing print with electronic media. “The new electronic interdependence,” he wrote in The Gutenberg Galaxy,<p><a class="readmore" href="https://james-the-obscure.github.io/the-bandwagon-effect"><span class="arrow-right icon"></span>Read More</a></p>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><span style="font-size: 14pt;"><em>A mental contagion that afflicts our politics more than ever</em>.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: 14pt;"><span id="more-71"></span></span></p>
<p><span style="color: #ff0000;"><em>Originally published March 12, 2008</em></span></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><span style="font-size: 14pt;">Decades ago, at the dawn of the television age, Marshall McLuhan described what was happening as Western society overhauled its 500-year-old nervous system, replacing print with electronic media. “The new electronic interdependence,” he wrote in The <em>Gutenberg Galaxy</em>, “recreates the world in the image of a global village.” McLuhan did not see this as progress; indeed he foresaw Western culture entering “a phase of panic terrors, exactly befitting a small world of tribal drums, total interdependence, and superimposed co-existence.”</span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: 14pt;">But the fact that our brains are practically hardwired to electronic media these days makes us susceptible to all kinds of social contagion, not just “panic terrors.” One of these contagion phenomena, known to social scientists as “the bandwagon effect,” is particularly relevant in primary-election season.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: 14pt;">The bandwagon effect refers to the tendency of voters to be supportive of a candidate purely because he or she is perceived as popular. Thus a small or local success for a candidate – a good outcome in an early primary, or a jump in a local poll – can lead infectiously to a broader popularity, however undeserved by other criteria. After his wins in Iowa and New Hampshire in early 2004, for example, John Kerry moved up sharply in the polls and became the front-runner.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: 14pt;">The effect is far from being the only influence on voter decision-making. But its existence has been demonstrated in several well-known social science experiments, and the importance that candidates, journalists and voters now deliberately place on early primary contests.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: 14pt;">Perhaps because of the unflattering light it sheds upon the electoral process, the bandwagon effect is seldom called by its right name. George H.W. Bush celebrated it as <em>momentum&#8212;</em>“the big Mo”&#8212;after unexpectedly winning the Iowa Republican caucuses in the 1980 presidential campaign. Others have called it “the Iowa bounce.” Hillary Clinton’s surging poll numbers a year ago had commentators talking about her newly-perceived “electability.”</span></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-72" src="https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/bandwagon-graphic.jpg" alt="" width="274" height="338" srcset="https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/bandwagon-graphic.jpg 274w, https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/bandwagon-graphic-243x300.jpg 243w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 274px) 100vw, 274px" /></p>
<p><span style="font-size: 14pt;">If the bandwagon effect is merely about electability, then in a sense it is less worrisome. To the extent that a voter is decidedly partisan, and merely wants to choose the most electable candidate to lead his party to victory in the nationwide contest, his sensitivity to other voter choices during the primaries would be perfectly rational.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: 14pt;">But the experimental data tend to contradict the notion of the bandwagon effect as a rational partisan strategy. A <a href="http://links.jstor.org/sici?sici=0022-3816%28199408%2956%3A3%3C802%3ATVMTBA%3E2.0.CO%3B2-N">study</a> in 1994, by researchers from the University of Southwestern Louisiana and the University of Kentucky, found the effect to be particularly strong among “independent” voters not affiliated with any party. A <a href="http://ijpor.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/abstract/8/3/266">study</a> in 1996 blamed “particularly unsophisticated independent voters” for the effect in a German election. A UCLA <a href="http://www.blackwell-synergy.com/doi/abs/10.1111/j.1559-1816.1998.tb01363.x">study</a> published in the <em>Journal of Applied Social Psychology</em> in 1998 hinted that the effect was rooted in traits similar to suggestibility:</span></p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px;"><span style="font-size: 14pt;">Bandwagon effects were stronger for women compared with men, and for 2 of 3 PAD (pleasantness, arousability, dominance) basic temperament factors; that is, for individuals with more arousable and less dominant temperaments.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: 14pt;">All this ought to be unsettling. But should it really surprise us, given that political candidates are sold using some of the same irrational, mood-altering techniques – wavy flags, smiling children, stirring music, flannel shirts – that advertisers use to sell consumer products?</span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: 14pt;">A few weeks ago, reading about Obama’s surge in the polls, I sensed my own inner readjustment: Before, when he’d had only half Hillary Clinton’s poll numbers, Obama had seemed little more than a smooth-talking political queue-jumper. After his post-Oprah surge he seemed … less objectionable somehow. Even Mike Huckabee, as he exploded in the polls, earned a twinge of acceptance. Maybe he’s not as ridiculous as I’d always thought. I should mention that I am not at all partisan, and have not registered as a Republican or Democrat. Neither Obama nor Huckabee fits into any political category that I find appealing. In other words, “electability” is not their only problem, in my eyes. Nevertheless I felt better about them, knowing that others did. This shift in thinking, by the way, felt perfectly normal and natural. But it felt better to recognize it as an instinct and reject it.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: 14pt;">Assuming that the bandwagon effect is a basic instinct, we might ask why it exists. Did it have some adaptive function during our early cultural development? Was the tendency to “pick a winner” a necessary survival trait when politics was more brutal than it is today? Or was it merely part of a general mental interdependence that held early human society together? And could it date back further still, to the very basic mammalian instinct to stay safely within the herd?</span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: 14pt;">Whatever the answer turns out to be, there is no shortage of evidence that in modern societies human opinions remain deeply interdependent. Social psychologists have <a href="http://psp.sagepub.com/cgi/content/abstract/23/9/928">found</a> this even in the romantic market, where “romantic popularity” turns out to be a key factor in people’s mating preferences: In other words, to a person in the mood for love, a prospective mate will seem more attractive than otherwise if it is perceived that the crowd finds her attractive too. (Small wonder that our culture places such high value on celebrity.)</span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: 14pt;">Conceivably, such a trait could have evolved as a way of leveraging one’s individual decision-making with the summed “<a href="http://www.amazon.com/exec/obidos/tg/detail/-/0385503865/ref=pd_sl_aw_jset-1_low-book_40783888_1">wisdom of the crowd</a>.” But the wisdom-of-the-crowd effect, described by James Surowiecki in his book of the same name, requires that opinions be relatively independent of each other. The more tightly interwired and interdependent a crowd becomes, the more its opinions amount not to wisdom but to herd-like madness.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: 14pt;">One can view this process as a contagion, but arguably it is better seen as a runaway autofeedback phenomenon, in which our collective judgement comes to depend more and more upon itself, thereby becoming less stable, more subject to sudden movements, and less connected to reality — in other words, more “volatile,” as pollsters and pundits now routinely observe of public opinion.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: 14pt;">Periodically, it is recognized that Iowa’s caucuses and New Hampshire’s primaries have a disproportionate effect on the presidential race. Typically it is suggested that all the state primaries be held on or near the same day. But Iowa and New Hampshire are only parts of the problem. Literally every revelation of public opinion prior to the national election feeds back into that opinion and distorts it. And because that feedback effect can cause strange, sudden movements, upward or downward, in a candidate’s popularity, the management of political campaigns is now largely about the management of those irrational swings – damping the slumps, boosting the surges, and getting the candidate’s poll numbers to peak at election time.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: 14pt;">The logical way to prevent these herdlike movements is not only to condense elections to the fewest possible dates, but to hide poll results from the public, at least until all votes are cast. In the world of commerce, information is routinely kept secret to prevent unwanted feedback effects. But in a society with a bedrock faith in free speech, the censorship of poll results seems unlikely at best.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: 14pt;">Even an acknowledgement of this issue is culturally problematic. We humans have a deep need to see not chaos but order, to find patterns and to navigate by them. We are inclined to rationalize the swings of public opinion as if they were driven entirely by real-world events. Thus the opinion bubble that <a href="http://www.usaelectionpolls.com/2008/candidates/Mike-Huckabee.html">lifted</a> Huckabee from single-digits to the top GOP spot in the space of a few slow-news weeks has been explained as the product of “Huck’s” aw-shucks style, his Christian principles, the weakness of Giuliani and so forth. In a like manner we explain the to-ings and fro-ings of the stock market, sports teams, fads and fashions, the fortunes of celebrities and more or less everything else in life: We are instinctively, irrationally bent on rationalizing what is never fully rational.</span></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><em><span style="color: #ff0000;">***<br />
</span></em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>CAN WE HANDLE THE QUANTUM TRUTH?</title>
		<link>https://james-the-obscure.github.io/can-we-handle-the-quantum-truth</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[JtO]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 10 Mar 2008 16:21:20 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[politics & culture]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[science & medicine]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[woo woo]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://james-the-obscure.github.io/?p=59</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[What Copernicus, Galileo and Darwin did to disturb our self-centered view of the universe was nothing compared to Hugh Everett’s theory of quantum reality. &#160; &#160; Originally published March 10, 2008 Modern existence is a constant affirmation of faith in quantum theory&#8212;or at least, faith in the theory’s ability to predict the behavior of light<p><a class="readmore" href="https://james-the-obscure.github.io/can-we-handle-the-quantum-truth"><span class="arrow-right icon"></span>Read More</a></p>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><span style="font-size: 14pt;"><em>What Copernicus, Galileo and Darwin did to disturb our self-centered view of the universe was nothing compared to Hugh Everett’s theory of quantum reality.</em></span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: 14pt;"><span id="more-59"></span></span></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><span style="color: #ff6600;"><em>Originally published March 10, 2008</em></span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: 14pt;">Modern existence is a constant affirmation of faith in quantum theory&#8212;or at least, faith in the theory’s ability to predict the behavior of light and matter. The semiconductors in computer chips, the diode lasers in DVD players, even the ticks and tocks of atomic clocks are all based on this 90-year old branch of science.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: 14pt;">Quantum theory also gives hints about the basic fabric of reality, but these hints conflict so much with our intuitive view of things that we ignore them in everyday life. If we truly took these hints to heart, we might feel as Neo did when he took the red pill and woke up to the harsh reality of the Matrix. Like the Matrix, the current quantum model of the universe implies that our intuitive view of existence is illusory, our hunger for meaning a cosmic joke.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: 14pt;">A basic idea of quantum theory is that the properties of particles naturally exist in a haze of uncertainty. One cannot predict the precise location of an electron, for instance; one can predict only the set of its possible locations and the probabilities of experimentally finding it at these locations. In essence, it seems that the electron exists in a ghostly multiplicity of states until one of those states interacts robustly with its surroundings, for example by the measurement process.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: 14pt;">The “Copenhagen Interpretation” of quantum theory, which dominated from the 1930s until recently, held that the observed collapse of this multiplicity of possible states to one state – to the sharp reality that we normally perceive – means the simple disappearance of the other possible states.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: 14pt;">However, it seems that most physicists now favor the “Everett Interpretation,” developed by a Princeton graduate student, Hugh Everett III, in the 1950s. Also known as the Many Worlds Interpretation (MWI), Everett’s concept implies that the other possible states in such cases don’t really go away. They continue to exist in other, inaccessible universes populated by other you’s and me’s.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: 14pt;">In this view, the you that exists at the moment of your birth splits or differentiates into a near-infinitude of you’s with every possible life history – consistent with the physical laws that pertain in your area of reality. The history of Earth and its species also move along every possible trajectory. Across the cosmos – across the “multiverse”&#8212;everything that <em>can</em> happen <em>does</em> happen.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: 14pt;">Professional theorists and popularizers have been writing about MWI since the 1980s. Perhaps believing that downbeat themes sell fewer books, these writers have tended to soft-pedal the implications, portraying this profound shift in thinking as merely part of the grand adventure of science: Thus, Copernicus dethroned us humans from the center of the universe; and Darwin dethroned us from our privileged space in the animal kingdom; and both times we coped; and so we shall cope again with this new and stronger existential relativism.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: 14pt;">But the relativism of MWI is not merely stronger; it is, so to speak, absolute&#8212;and it absolutely mocks our intuitive sense of agency, responsibility and meaning. How can we condemn or praise an action that someone has taken, when we know that that action, from an MWI view, <em>had</em> to be taken, in order to fill out the vast space of possibility? How can we celebrate a hero in our world, knowing that he or she must be a villain in another? How can we find meaning in the minutiae of our history, knowing that that history is but one random branch in a vast cosmic tree?</span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: 14pt;">It is some consolation that MWI is not a sure thing. But there is currently no feasible way to disprove it, and so we must live under its shadow indefinitely. Perhaps we shall just continue to take the “blue pill” and ignore its implications. As Simon Saunders, an Oxford University philosopher and MWI theorist, told a reporter several years ago, “I’ll just accept Everett and then think about something else, to save my sanity.”</span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: 14pt;">But MWI is also a stark reminder of something that Nietzsche and other philosophers warned about long ago: Science is not an unshakeable institution. It is a cultural choice, requiring faith in the value of its truths. When those truths fail to “set us free,” and instead deliver existential poison, science’s own existence may become precarious.</span></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><span style="font-size: 14pt;">***</span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: 14pt;"> </span></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>THE ROBOT MENACE</title>
		<link>https://james-the-obscure.github.io/the-robot-menace</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[JtO]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 04 Dec 2007 14:24:08 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[politics & culture]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[science & medicine]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://james-the-obscure.github.io/?p=67</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[The subtle threat from smart machines. &#160; Originally published December 4, 2007 &#160; In this morning’s NYT, John Tierney had one of those gee, the future’s coming pieces on robotic “smart cars.” He concluded with the prediction that: even if humans stubbornly cling to the steering wheel, they could still end up sharing the road<p><a class="readmore" href="https://james-the-obscure.github.io/the-robot-menace"><span class="arrow-right icon"></span>Read More</a></p>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><span style="font-size: 14pt;"><em>The subtle threat from smart machines.</em></span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: 14pt;"><span id="more-67"></span></span></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><span style="color: #ff6600;"><em>Originally published December 4, 2007</em></span></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><span style="font-size: 14pt;">In this morning’s <em>NYT</em>, John Tierney had one of those <em>gee, the future’s coming </em><a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/12/04/science/04tier.html?ref=science">pieces</a> on robotic “smart cars.” He concluded with the prediction that:</span></p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px;"><span style="font-size: 14pt;">even if humans stubbornly cling to the steering wheel, they could still end up sharing the road with smart cars. By around 2030, according to some believers in Moore’s Law, there will be computers more powerful than the human brain, leading to the emergence of superintelligent “post-humans.” If these beings do appear, I have no doubt how they’ll get around. They’d never be stupid enough to get in a car driven by a member of Mr. Magoo’s species.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: 14pt;">Yeah, funny. But come to think of it, isn’t the prospect of “superintelligent ‘post-humans’” really a lot more inkworthy than the prospect of safe-driving robot cars?</span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: 14pt;">And isn’t it a lot less appealing?</span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: 14pt;">It certainly used to be. When Karel Capek wrote his 1921 play, <em>R.U.R.</em> (Rossum’s Universal Robots), thereby introducing the term <em>robot</em> to the language, it probably seemed natural to his audience that his machine-men ultimately rebelled and snuffed out their human creators. Rebellion and havoc-making was what creatures made by hubristic mortals always <em>did,</em> from Frankenstein’s monster back to the Hebrew Golem<em>.</em> Even God had his problems with those wayward kids, Adam and Eve.</span></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-69" src="https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/robot.jpg" alt="" width="341" height="316" srcset="https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/robot.jpg 341w, https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/robot-300x278.jpg 300w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 341px) 100vw, 341px" /></p>
<p><span style="font-size: 14pt;">By the 1930s, robots had become standard monster-figures in pulp sci-fi. But by the early 1940s, Isaac Asimov had begun to refer in his stories to the restraining “Three Laws of Robotics,” and lawful robots began to mingle with rebellious ones.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: 14pt;">To anyone who works in AI these days, the Three Laws must seem absurdly naive&#8212;just the sort of thing a sci-fi writer would have come up with back in the early Forties. But the “Laws” did what Asimov had wanted them to do. They got sci-fi out of the robophobe rut it had been in, by persuading readers that smart machines could be sympathetic, peaceful characters, even trustworthy, Tonto-like companions to humans.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: 14pt;">The “good robot” theme hasn’t always prevailed since then in Western culture. Films like <em>Westworld</em>, <em>2001: A Space Odyssey</em>, <em>The Terminator</em> and <em>The Matrix</em> occasionally have brought our deeper fears to the surface. On the non-fiction side, writers including <a href="http://www.wired.com/wired/archive/8.04/joy.html">Bill Joy</a> and <a href="http://www.billmckibben.com/enough.html">Bill McKibben</a> have raised warning flags, too. But since the turn of the century, it seems to me, the robophiles have been stomping the competition in the mass media. The three big robot films of this decade so far&#8212;<em>AI, I Robot</em> and<em> Transformers&#8212;</em>have all featured good robots who prevail in the end.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: 14pt;">How did the robophiles gain the upper hand in this culture war?</span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: 14pt;">One big reason, I suspect, is that <em>there are now robots</em>, even if mostly in toy form, and people are starting to think seriously of all the roles in which they might be useful, from housekeeping to construction work to sex work. For related reasons, the advertising industry also now has an interest in portraying robots positively.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: 14pt;">Yet for all our newfound enthusiasm for robots, the existential threat they pose hasn’t gone away. In fact, that threat now seems closer and less hypothetical than ever.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: 14pt;">I don’t mean that robots necessarily threaten us with violence. To me it’s plausible that the humanoid machines living and working among us twenty years from now will all be as gentle and unassuming as the C3PO character from <em>Star Wars</em>. They might even have such lifelike “skin” that they visually fit right in. But their presence would still be cataclysmic.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: 14pt;">Merely by their low cost and utility, they would make human labor obsolete. Working constantly, never complaining, consuming only electric power and the occasional spare part, they would be, dollar for dollar, more productive by far than the cheapest Third World sweatshop toiler. And they would evolve their way up the labor value chain too swiftly for any human to stay in the game.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: 14pt;">A few years ago, <em>Salon</em> ran a <a href="http://dir.salon.com/story/tech/feature/2003/09/18/automation/">piece</a> on this topic, and among others interviewed Robert Reich, a former Secretary of Labor. Reich’s point was that “There are all sorts of jobs that can’t be done by robots because the essence of the job is providing personal attention.” And that was essentially the conclusion of the piece: that robots in the foreseeable future would merely hasten the labor market tilt, in America and other developed countries, towards personal-service and high-creativity jobs, and away from jobs that machines and cheap foreign workers can do.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: 14pt;">This concept would be bleak enough even if it were correct, given the labor market upheaval it predicts. But I think Reich’s idea is actually wrong, in a way that is probably typical of people who don’t know much about robots or AI. He assumes that the robots of tomorrow will be like the computer-driven automated systems of today. Even Tierney’s comment about Moore’s Law illuminates a common misunderstanding.</span></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><span style="font-size: 14pt;">*</span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: 14pt;">“Moore’s Law” was just Gordon Moore’s observation that the computer chip industry tends to advance quickly enough to double the maximum density of chip elements every 18-24 months. To some extent the widespread faith in this “law” ensures its accuracy. But there is no guarantee that will continue to hold. In any case, Moore’s Law refers to computer chips, not to the vastly different, brain-like architecture needed to make recognizably “smart” robots and AI systems.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: 14pt;">Brain-like architecture is essentially parallel-processing and hyper-interconnected, not serial-processing and centralized like computer CPUs. It is true that AI researchers now often use traditional computer chips to run software modelling how brains work, and with this inefficient architecture, brain-modelling does require great processing power. But researchers are already beginning to experiment with more “neural” hardware, which is enormously more efficient at performing animal-like tasks.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: 14pt;">True neural hardware could be scalable in ways that modern computer chips aren’t. Mammalian brains consist to a great extent of repeating structures known as neocortical columns, so if the basic architecture is right, and the initial wiring/programming is right, most of the ground between small robot brains and big ones could be covered with more neurons and more interconnections.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: 14pt;">Obviously, some further design changes would be needed to turn, for example, a mouselike brain (~15 million neurons) into a humanlike brain (~100 billion neurons), but those changes could prove to be relatively minor, and in any case, given that they apply to a totally different architecture, they are unlikely to be limited by the state of traditional computer-chip technology.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: 14pt;">The point is that walking, talking (or at least chirping or barking) robots could become a reality very quickly&#8212;long before “Moore’s Law” gives traditional computers the power to model brain processes at human-like scale and speed.</span></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><span style="font-size: 14pt;">*</span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: 14pt;">Robots and AI systems with artificial brains won’t seem like the automated systems we have today. They won’t even seem like machines at all. They will seem like the living, sentient creatures in whose images they are made.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: 14pt;">Will they be conscious? Probably not&#8212;but they <em>won’t have to be conscious</em> to perform virtually all the economic functions of humans, from building houses to writing novels and doing advanced theoretical physics.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: 14pt;">And waiting on tables. And assisting shoppers in retail stores. And serving as executive assistants. The idea that these artificial creatures would necessarily be inept at personal services is ludicrous; it seems to rest on nothing more than the old stereotype of the “emotionless” robot. From a neuro-engineering standpoint, the ability to recognize emotions appropriately is not inherently more difficult than, say, the ability to recognize faces or words or terrain patterns. So robots should soon be able to exceed humans in this department as well as all the others.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: 14pt;">Personal services already represent a huge growth area for robotics. Even before the technology is really in place, the Japanese are <a href="http://www.economist.com/world/asia/displaystory.cfm?story_id=5323427">making</a> a major push to build personal-service robots&#8212;housekeepers, butlers, receptionists, street-corner direction-givers, hospital orderlies, trashmen, home companions for the elderly, even prostitutes&#8212;because their population is declining and they would rather not import workers from “lower” countries and risk cultural dilution.</span></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><span style="font-size: 14pt;">*</span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: 14pt;">Even if we were to assume, conservatively, that robots and AI systems with a broad range of human or superhuman abilities won’t be around until 2030, we’d have to believe that lesser but still useful automatons will be available much sooner. With robots, even a little utility is likely to go a long way. Any product&#8212;for example&#8212;that can walk reliably, can recognize a few hundred faces and objects and words, can hold things as dexterously as we, and in addition can interface directly and rapidly with computers and the Internet, will be able to do what waiters and waitresses do, what counter clerks do, what office staff do, what pilots do, and what common laborers do, only at far lower cost. How far are we from such a prospect? Fifteen years? I doubt it will be even that long.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: 14pt;">And again, taking this still-relatively-crude robot technology and scaling up its brain and skillset could turn out to be a relatively simple matter. In any case it seems a fair bet that a child born today, even a gifted child with the best possible education, will graduate from college, about 21 years from now, into a labor market where humans have become a decidedly inferior product.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: 14pt;">Conceivably we humans will be able to earn money in a robot-worker economy by running our own businesses or otherwise managing assets. But as robots march into the upper reaches of the labor market, they will start to compete even with human entrepreneurs. Operating from huge robot-worker conglomerates, controlled by dwindling numbers of colossally wealthy human CEOs and senior managers, they will be able to exterminate smaller, human-run businesses all the way down the “long tail.” In a free market, there will be nowhere for expensive, high-maintenance humans to run.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: 14pt;">And robots will be able to achieve this conquest while remaining the passive, gentle chattel of humans&#8212;appliances with legs! Should they go on to acquire the same civil rights as ours, we’ll be out of political options too. Think this won’t happen? The post-humanists consider it <a href="http://books.google.com/books?id=_QB5P20Ro9gC&amp;dq=citizen+cyborg&amp;pg=PP1&amp;ots=NJcvjD_zn7&amp;sig=9XiImOMwFP5EkdvrLyESuwNzWx8&amp;hl=en&amp;prev=http://www.google.com/search?q=Citizen+Cyborg&amp;ie=utf-8&amp;oe=utf-8&amp;rls=org.mozilla:en-US:official&amp;client=firefox-a&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=print&amp;ct=title&amp;cad=one-book-with-thumbnail">inevitable</a>. And they have a point: The more sympathy robots evoke in us, the more rights we will want to cede to them. Believe me, there will be money in it for anyone who designs robots to evoke sympathy.</span></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-416" src="https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/ai-osment-1.jpg" alt="" width="347" height="270" srcset="https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/ai-osment-1.jpg 347w, https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/ai-osment-1-300x233.jpg 300w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 347px) 100vw, 347px" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><span style="font-size: 14pt;">*</span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: 14pt;">Like global warming, the functional obsolescence of humans, and their consequent demoralization and cultural decay, would be one of those “unintended consequences” of our more or less freely-evolving market system. Unlike global warming, this self-destruct process would not be solvable by technological innovation. Technological innovation would be the problem, not the solution.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: 14pt;">Roboticists, unsurprisingly, tend to see technological innovation&#8212;“evolution”&#8212;as sacred, unquestionable, unstoppable. Carnegie Mellon professor Hans Moravec, one of the pioneers of modern robotics, has argued that we should accept the obsolescence of humanity the way we have always accepted our demises as individuals. In other words, we should “silently fade away,” passing on the torch of existence to robots as if they were our children. “We have very little choice, if our culture is to remain viable,” he wrote in his 1988 book <em>Mind Children</em>. “Societies and economies are surely as subject to competitive evolutionary processes as are biological organisms.”</span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: 14pt;">Seemingly less suicidal, but not really, is the proposal of the post-humanists, whose most prominent representative these days is an inventor and futurist named Ray Kurzweil. In his recent book, <em>The Singularity is Near</em>, Kurzweil whooped and cheered about the technologies that would soon “enable us to transcend our biological limitations,&#8221; i.e., by turning ourselves into robots. Kurzweil saw this happening in the next two or three decades.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: 14pt;">There are a few shortcomings to this approach. One is that humans have “human” needs, for other people and so on, whereas a robot wired for economic superiority wouldn’t be held back by such needs. To become such a creature, totally inhuman, merely to keep up with a supposedly “inexorable” technological evolution, strikes me as even more idiotic, suicidal and inhumane than Moravec’s idea&#8212;and Moravec set the bar pretty high. Yet we seem to be chasing this insane goal already.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: 14pt;">There is also the consciousness problem. We don’t know&#8212;and so far we have no good reason to believe&#8212;that the circuitry of a robot brain can generate the sense of conscious awareness that humans and other animals experience. </span><span style="font-size: 14pt;">Kurzweil nevertheless blithely suggests that we&#8217;ll all be able to transfer the contents of our old, fragile, wetware brains to new, solid-state brains and live happily ever after.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: 14pt;">Apart from the murky issue of consciousness, a brain-state “transfer” from one medium to another would, at best, represent a copying process. Whether or not self-awareness could be generated in the new brain, the old self would remain and die in the old brain. Conceivably, if non-biological material could generate consciousness (and again, there is zero evidence for this), one could transform a wetware brain, slowly and in place, into solid-state robot-stuff, and the subject of this freakish experiment might feel enough continuity with his old self, throughout this process, to believe that he had lived through it.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: 14pt;">But wouldn’t it be a lot easier, and more sane, and a lot more humane, simply to take control of our cultural and technological development, and to block it where appropriate, before this creeping dystopia overwhelms us?</span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: 14pt;">That, of course, is the third possible solution to the problem posed by “post-human” robots. It has been suggested already by others, including Bill Joy, Bill McKibben and <a href="http://books.google.com/books?id=lN5-tJ-Y1nsC&amp;dq=Francis+Fukuyama&amp;hl=en&amp;prev=http://www.google.com/search?q=Francis+Fukuyama&amp;ie=utf-8&amp;oe=utf-8&amp;rls=org.mozilla:en-US:official&amp;client=firefox-a&amp;sa=X&amp;oi=print&amp;ct=result&amp;cd=2&amp;cad=author-navigational">Francis Fukuyama</a>.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: 14pt;">To no avail. Theirs have been the proverbial voices crying in the wilderness&#8212;mocked for their archaic notion that “progress” could ever be stopped.</span></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>AL GORE: STILL PHONY AFTER ALL THESE YEARS</title>
		<link>https://james-the-obscure.github.io/al-gore-still-phony</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[JtO]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 07 Jul 2007 04:42:12 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[politics & culture]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[science & medicine]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://james-the-obscure.github.io/?page_id=345</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Thoughts on the recent Gore re-inflation&#8230; &#160; Originally published 7 July 2007. &#160; Remember those first few years after the 2000 election, when it seemed that no one, not even Democrats, wanted Al Gore around anymore? To the New York Times’  Bill Keller, Americans had rightly written him off as “an opportunist, a phony.” Joe<p><a class="readmore" href="https://james-the-obscure.github.io/al-gore-still-phony"><span class="arrow-right icon"></span>Read More</a></p>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><em>Thoughts on the recent Gore re-inflation&#8230;</em></p>
<p><span id="more-345"></span></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><span style="color: #ff0000;"><em>Originally published 7 July 2007.</em></span></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>Remember those first few years after the 2000 election, when it seemed that no one, not even Democrats, wanted Al Gore around anymore? To the <em>New York Times’</em>  Bill Keller, Americans had rightly written him off as “<a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2002/08/10/opinion/we-love-you-you-re-perfect-goodbye.html">an opportunist, a phony</a>.” Joe Klein <a href="http://www.slate.com/id/2063770/">called</a> him “stiff and synthetic and multifarious,” a “dreadful candidate” who “never seemed reliable enough to be president.”</p>
<p>When Gore refused to go away, the catcalls became worse. In 2004 he made a 6,600 word <a href="http://www.commondreams.org/views04/0527-01.htm">speech</a> about Abu Ghraib, referring to “Bush’s Gulag,” demanding the resignations of Rice, Rumsfeld and Tenet, and saying things like: “One of the clearest indications of the impending loss of intimacy with one’s soul is the failure to recognize the existence of a soul in those over whom power is exercised.” <em>Washington Post</em> columnist Charles Krauthammer <a href="http://dir.salon.com/story/opinion/right_hook/2004/06/02/gore/index.html">said</a> on Fox, “It looks as if Al Gore has gone off his lithium again.” Dennis Miller <a href="http://dir.salon.com/story/opinion/right_hook/2004/06/02/gore/index.html">told</a> his CNBC audience, “At one point I respected Al Gore, but I think he’s lost his mind.”</p>
<p>Since then a number of circumstances, from accelerating Arctic melting to America’s struggles in Iraq, have helped bring Gore and his causes back into public esteem. His resurgent popularity has inspired comparisons (<a href="http://www.sierraclub.org/sierrasummit/coverage/r016.asp">by himself</a> among <a href="http://www.time.com/time/nation/article/0,8599,1622009-1,00.html">others</a>) to Churchill’s triumphal political re-emergence in the late 1930s – except that Gore now has a star status only a modern media could have pumped to life.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-127" src="https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/gore.png" alt="" width="197" height="245" /></p>
<p>According to a <a href="http://nymag.com/news/politics/17065/">profile</a> earlier this year in <em>New York</em> magazine, Gore “has sounded nothing like the Gore we remember – calculating, chameleonic, soporific – from the 2000 campaign. He has sounded like a man, in the words of a top Republican strategist, who ‘found his voice in the wilderness.’”</p>
<p>Not to be outdone, Time recently <a href="http://www.time.com/time/nation/article/0,8599,1622009-1,00.html">called</a> Gore “a natural born teacher,” and an “improbably charismatic, Academy Award-winning, Nobel Prize-nominated environmental prophet with an army of followers and huge reserves of political and cultural capital at his command” – a description almost unimaginable a few years ago.</p>
<p>Gore has been asked to run for president in 2008, but he says he prefers to stay where he is, opinionating, consciousness-raising, making bundles of <a href="http://www.fastcompany.com/magazine/117/features-gore.html">money</a>, and basking in the warmth of global adulation. As his unabashedly worshipful <em>Time </em>profiler, Eric Pooley, put it, “There’s an even deeper issue here, and with Gore, it’s always the deepest issue that counts. What’s at stake is not just Gore losing another election. It’s Gore losing himself – returning to politics and, in the process, losing touch with the man he has become.” Google CEO Eric Schmidt assured Pooley that Gore had gone “through a difficult personal transformation in order to achieve greatness.”</p>
<p style="text-align: center;">●</p>
<p>Considering how swiftly the air was forced out of the Gore balloon six and a half years ago, it seems only right to wonder at this sudden reinflation. Are we are now seeing a “new” Al Gore, unhampered by all the constraints of politics, an Al Gore who says smart things and uncompromisingly sticks by them? Or is he the same old multifarious opportunist who says one thing and <a href="http://www.realchange.org/gore.htm#pollution">does another</a>?</p>
<p>It isn’t hard to find evidence of Gore’s continuing hypocrisy. Although he has long been urging Americans to reduce their energy use, it was <a href="http://www.tennesseepolicy.org/main/article.php?article_id=367">discovered</a> recently that his huge house outside Nashville has been consuming power at twenty times the rate of the average American home. (The Gores also have a big house in suburban Virginia, plus an apartment in San Francisco.) Gore has been chided, too, for his involvement in the Live Earth concerts. Their massive carbon footprints, and the spectacle of colossal energy hogs like Madonna preaching about conservation, caused even some <a href="http://news.yahoo.com/s/afp/20070705/wl_uk_afp/entertainmentmusicclimatewarmingarcticmonkeys_070705025637">pop groups</a> to stay away.</p>
<p>Perhaps understandably, Gore’s supporters have been apt to <a href="http://www.salon.com/ent/music/feature/2007/07/08/live_earth/index.html">dismiss</a> these criticisms as politically motivated, and Gore’s lapses as minor aberrations. But a case can be made that with Gore, hypocrisy isn’t an aberration&#8212;it is his standard operating procedure.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;">●</p>
<p>“What politics has become,” Gore loftily told an <a href="http://www.fastcompany.com/magazine/117/features-gore.html">interviewer</a> recently, “is something that requires a kind of tolerance for artifice and manipulative communications strategies that I just find I have in very short supply. I just don’t have the patience for things that seem to be greatly rewarded in today’s political system.”</p>
<p>Gore has turned this sentiment into a thesis, in his recent bestselling book, <em>The Assault on Reason</em>. He claims that America makes big mistakes, such as failing to elect him in 2000, removing Saddam Hussein from power, and “ignoring” global warming, because its political culture has become steeped in propagandistic manipulation.</p>
<p>The relative vividness of televisual media, according to Gore, allows it more easily to activate our brains’ primitive arousal networks, stimulating emotions like fear, greed, and sexual desire, and bypassing our more rational faculties. All this stimulation creates a neurochemical rush to which we can become addicted, he says, along the way losing our ability to think critically about what we are seeing and hearing. In his book he compares “the political economy supported by the television industry” to “the feudalism that thrived on the ignorance of the masses of people in the Dark Ages.” He also solemnly warns that the “systematic exposure to … arousal stimuli on television can be exploited by the clever public relations specialist, advertiser, or politician.”</p>
<p>Not exactly a new idea, of course. But an odd one coming from Gore, considering that as a politician he was notorious for his use of “artifice and manipulative communications strategies.” These ranged from his periodic good-old-boy affectation to his televised tongue-lock with Tipper at the Democratic convention.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-128" src="https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/tongue-lock-with-tipper.jpg" alt="" width="250" height="172" /></p>
<p>Gore says now he regrets some of the things he did to play the game, back then. But he is still playing this game, as blatantly as ever. To take one of the most obvious examples: Although he says he condemns the practice of “ratcheting up public anxieties and fears, distorting public discourse and reason,” his global warming film, <em>An Inconvenient Truth</em> bills itself as “by far the most terrifying film you will ever see” according to its posters.</p>
<p>Gore’s film makes blatant use of visual propaganda techniques, and grossly distorts the science on which it is ostensibly based. All this was elaborated in an eye-opening <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/03/13/science/13gore.html">article </a>in March by science reporter William Broad at the <em>New York Times</em>. As Broad made clear, the inaccuracies in Gore’s film are not minor, random ones. They all concern the big issues in global warming research, and they are all biased to produce more fear, not less.</p>
<p>The film, for example, misleadingly links hurricanes like Katrina to global warming. Even its poster depicts a cyclonic storm coming out of a factory’s smokestacks – a classic use of scare-imagery of the kind Gore says he abhors. The reality is that global warming and storms are not very well connected in current atmospheric models. “We need to be more careful in describing the hurricane story than [Gore] is,” NASA climate physicist James Hansen admitted to Broad&#8212;and Hansen is one of Gore’s <a href="http://www.time.com/time/magazine/article/0,9171,1187255,00.html">heroes</a>.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-129" src="https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/inconvenienttruth.jpg" alt="" width="300" height="442" srcset="https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/inconvenienttruth.jpg 300w, https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/inconvenienttruth-204x300.jpg 204w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /></p>
<p>Gore’s film also plays fast and loose with predictions about the most dramatic physical effect of global warming, a rising sea level. “Mr. Gore,” wrote Broad, “citing no particular time frame, envisions rises of up to 20 feet and <em>depicts parts of New York, Florida and other heavily populated areas as sinking beneath the waves, implying, at least visually, that inundation is imminent</em>.”</p>
<p>The italics I have added to emphasize, again, that Gore here has used blatant visual propaganda. The current models actually suggest that global warming’s major side-effect will be relatively slow in coming, producing sea level rises on the order of only a foot or two by century’s end if nothing is done – and on the order of only inches during the next few decades, arguably giving us plenty of time to shift to non-polluting energy sources and to devise carbon-reduction technologies.</p>
<p>Gore’s film deceived in a number of other ways, for example by failing to place the current warming trend in the context of historical climate shifts, by falsely claiming that global warming has intensified malaria, and by suggesting that the scientists who question Gore’s alarmism are in the pay of oil companies (I’ve never been paid a nickel by an oil company,” Broad quoted one professor saying. “And I’m not a Republican”).</p>
<p>Gore’s propagandizing has not been limited to televisual media. The recent “Live Earth” concerts, inspired and promoted by him, were clearly not exercises in “public discourse and reason.” They were, instead, designed to hook young people on the “arousal stimuli” inherent in a pop music concert, so that they would accept his environmental message uncritically. (“If you want to save the planet, I want you to start jumping up and down,” <a href="http://article.nationalreview.com/?q=MzBiNDJhNzc2MWVjZmVlYjBmOTc3M2M1ZWUzODk5YzY=">shouted</a> Madonna at one point. “Come on, mother-fuckers!”)</p>
<p>Gore has said he will follow up the Live Earth spectacle with a create-an-ad contest, which he hopes will generate still more enthusiasm for his global warming cause. <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/07/13/business/media/13green.html?_r=1&amp;oref=slogin">According to the <em>New York Times</em>:</a></p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px;">Mr. Gore, through his environmental group, the Alliance for Climate Protection, has sent invitations to advertising agencies to submit 15-, 30- and 60-second “ecospots” explaining the global warming phenomenon and urging action to address it, at either the local or national level. The alliance is soliciting entries from anyone with a camera or video-editing capabilities.</p>
<p>It doesn’t seem to embarrass Gore that campaigns like this one utterly contradict his book-length fulmination against mass-manipulation techniques. “The way nations and societies make up their minds in the modern age has much more to do with mass advertising than many of us purists would like, but that’s the reality,” he told the <em>Times</em>. “Since we face a true planetary emergency, we have to give the planet a P.R. agent.”</p>
<p>Connoisseurs of Gore’s duplicity will love his use of the phrase <em>that’s the reality</em>, because it is an excuse he has explicitly rejected in the past. During the 2000 campaign, at a “town meeting” of young people ginned up for him on MTV, he piously <a href="http://www.thenation.com/doc/20050516/berman/2">condemned</a> hip-hop music as a seductive but harmful cultural influence:</p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px;">Gandhi once said you must become the change you wish to see in the world. I don’t think it’s good enough to say, ‘Well, we’re just reflecting a reality.’</p>
<p style="text-align: center;">●</p>
<p>After condemning the misuse of television and similar media by unscrupulous advertisers and politicians, Gore goes on to argue, in <em>The Assault on Reason,</em> that television as we know it is fundamentally incompatible with a healthy democratic society. A laudatory reviewer of Gore’s book in <em>The Atlantic</em> <a href="http://www.theatlantic.com/doc/200705u/gore-television">wrote</a> that “We can have television or we can have democracy. The evidence Gore adduces suggests that we cannot have both.”</p>
<p>Needless to say, Gore himself is having it both ways. His argument that the TV industry is at the heart of our cultural decay hasn’t stopped him from hobnobbing in Hollywood with friends like actor Bradley Whitford (from <em>The West Wing</em> and <em>Studio 60</em>), Larry David (creator of <em>Seinfeld</em>) and Laurie David (co-producer of <em>An Inconvenient Truth</em>, and a long-time worker in the TV industry). It also hasn’t stopped Gore from joining the industry himself. In 2004 he and several other investors, including Whitford and businessman Joel Hyatt, bought a cable network, for which Gore serves as chairman of the board.</p>
<p>Ostensibly Current TV, as this network is now called, is meant to produce a good kind of TV, not the bad kind. Gore <a href="http://www.time.com/time/nation/article/0,8599,1622015-2,00.html">explains</a>:</p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px;">In the world of television, the massive flows of information are largely in only one direction, which makes it virtually impossible for individuals to take part in what passes for a national conversation. Individuals receive, but they cannot send. They hear, but they do not speak. The “well-informed citizenry” is in danger of becoming the “well-amused audience.”</p>
<p>Current TV is supposed to “democratize” TV content, by letting viewers produce it. “We are about empowering” – <a href="http://www.thenation.com/doc/20050516/berman/2">said</a> Gore, two years ago – “this generation of young people in the 18-to-34 population to engage in a dialogue of democracy and to tell their stories of what’s going on in their lives, in the dominant medium of our time.”</p>
<p>Specifically, Current TV encourages viewers to submit the videos – “each just a few minutes long,” says the Current TV <a href="http://www.current.tv/about">website</a> – that the network will broadcast.</p>
<p>However, two years after it started, less than a third of Current TV’s content is produced by amateurs; the rest is produced professionally. Apparently the network’s audience, which has 100+ cable channels, tens of thousands of DVDs and video games, and the video universe of the world wide web to choose from, is not exactly clamoring for more viewer-created content. It seems that the “viewer-created content” angle is helpful to Current primarily because it holds down production costs. The real hook for its (young) audience is its shallow, tidbit-sized content, which is seldom political. Many of the better videos supplied by amateurs are ads for consumer products, whose producers hope for a deal with the products’ manufacturers.</p>
<p>“This is an audience that has become ‘media grazers,’” CurrentTV’s head of programming, ex-CNN executive David Neuman, <a href="http://www.thenation.com/doc/20050516/berman/2">admitted</a> in 2005 to writer Ari Berman, “and we decided to create a network that didn’t fight that but rather facilitated that.”</p>
<p>“Less and less they’re trying to run a company with a social mission,” Orville Schell, dean of the Berkeley School of Journalism and a CurrentTV board member <a href="http://www.thenation.com/doc/20050516/berman/2">told</a> Berman. “They want something that’s new and interesting and economically viable.”</p>
<p style="text-align: center;">●</p>
<p>On the whole, Gore’s sellout of his supposed beliefs about television seems about as thorough as it could be. In addition to being chairman of a TV network that produces YouTube-ish pap, he is a prominent, active member of the board of directors of Apple, Inc. – formerly called Apple Computer, but <a href="http://www.azstarnet.com/sn/printDS/163940">renamed</a> earlier this year to emphasize that it is now also a media company. With its iTunes store Apple distributes a vast amount of media content; and all the iPods, video iPods, Apple TV boxes, and now iPhones that it sells represent hundreds of millions of devices for playing that content. Apple on its website exclaims that “You can feast your eyes on movies and TV shows for up to six-and-a-half hours” with an iPod. The company’s new iPhone, in its function as a “wide screen iPod,” can keep this moveable feast going for about as long, with its own web connection to supply the content. In other words, the company encourages the kind of TV-dependency that Gore <a href="http://www.time.com/time/nation/article/0,8599,1622015-2,00.html">laments</a> in his book:</p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px;">Radio, the Internet, movies, cell phones, iPods, computers, instant messaging, video games and personal digital assistants all now vie for our attention—but it is television that still dominates the flow of information. According to an authoritative global study, Americans now watch television an average of 4 hours and 35 minutes every day – 90 minutes more than the world average. When you assume eight hours of work a day, six to eight hours of sleep and a couple of hours to bathe, dress, eat and commute, that is almost three-quarters of the discretionary time the average American has.</p>
<p>Obviously, Gore has done nothing at Apple to turn this situation around. In fact he is known for only two significant accomplishments at the company, neither of which reflects well on him.</p>
<p>The first is Gore’s apparent inaction in the face of pressure from environmentalist <a href="http://articles.moneycentral.msn.com/Investing/Extra/IsAppleAsGreenAsItClaims.aspx">groups</a>, who <a href="http://www.computertakeback.com/news_and_resources/letter_to_gore.cfm">complained</a> about toxic chemicals like lead and mercury in iPods. “Why,” a writer at <em>Fortune</em> <a href="http://money.cnn.com/2007/04/02/news/companies/pluggedin_Gunther_Gore.fortune/index.htm">asked</a> a few months ago, “would Al Gore, America’s best-known environmentalist and a member of the board of directors of Apple, oppose shareholder resolutions that ask the computer maker to become more green? That’s what Greenpeace, Friends of the Earth, Consumers Union, the National Environmental Trust and the Computer TakeBack Campaign want to know.”</p>
<p>Recently, Apple caved and announced “Greener Apple” policies. Unsurprisingly Gore has spun this his way. Through <em>Time</em>’s Eric Pooley, <a href="http://www.time.com/time/nation/article/0,8599,1622009-3,00.html">he let it be known</a> that he had “patiently nudged the CEO to adopt a new Greener Apple program that will eliminate toxic chemicals from the company’s products by next year.”</p>
<p>Probably few of those who have complained about Gore’s past stonewalling will find such a claim credible. Jim Puckett, of the Basel Action Network, <a href="http://articles.moneycentral.msn.com/Investing/Extra/IsAppleAsGreenAsItClaims.aspx">describes</a> the “Greener Apple” scheme as deceptive anyway, falling well short of the environmental responsibility that his and other groups had expected: “Apple’s statement was craftily designed to obfuscate and ‘greenwash’ what they were doing. They made a statement that sounds really good to the general audience that doesn’t know the issues.”</p>
<p>Gore’s other achievement at Apple was his leadership of a board committee tasked with investigating grants of backdated stock options to Apple executives. Such backdating amounts to tax evasion, of course, and Jobs admitted knowing of the practice. Moreover Jobs, who avoids paying income tax by taking his compensation as stock options (taxed at the lower capital-gains rate), was found to have received options a few years ago, for a chunk of 7.5 million Apple shares, that were backed by a phony board authorization with a probably phony date. Somehow neither Jobs nor any other member of his senior management team could recall the circumstances under which the phony board authorizations had been produced. Yet Jobs was <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2006/12/29/business/30applecnd.html?ex=1325048400&amp;en=59c8ec703de30b5f&amp;ei=5088">exonerated</a> by Gore’s committee, the excuse being that he had managed to avoid cashing in any of those questionable options.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;">●</p>
<p>Around this time, perhaps unsurprisingly, Steve Jobs was encouraging Gore to run for president again. He <a href="http://www.time.com/time/nation/article/0,8599,1622009-3,00.html">told</a> Eric Pooley “there’s no question in my mind that he would be elected.”</p>
<p>But Gore says he has almost certainly left politics behind. As he modestly explained to Pooley, “I’m not convinced the presidency is the highest and best role I could play.” Plus, says Tipper, he is now “free and liberated and doing exactly what he wants to do. And that is fabulous.”</p>
<p>Fabulous indeed – in the old, straightforward sense of being like a fable. For although Gore is no longer constrained to adopt the phony poses of formal politics, his new milieu of media and entertainment, mass-persuasion and making money, involves its own constraints. It appears that whatever his ideals are, he cannot afford to annoy Steve Jobs and other people with money and status, who could seriously wound him if they ever turned on him. He cannot really turn his back on the TV industry without costing himself money and friends, including fellow investors. And he cannot really eschew the use of manipulative mass-persuasion techniques without, as he sees it, weakening the messages he want to put out. He seems as constrained to betray his own professed ideals as he would have been were he a politician, if not moreso.</p>
<p>Some may believe that Gore at any rate is saying things that do need to be said, and are backed up with some scientific rigor. His book, for example, is liberally salted with quotes from scientists and philosophers, and Eric Pooley referred to his “intellectual firepower.”</p>
<p>Speaking of which, no one seems to have remembered the story the <em>Washington Post</em> <a href="http://www.freerepublic.com/forum/a38dcfe0d392e.htm">broke</a> early in the 2000 election campaign, about Gore’s astonishingly low grades in high school and college, and at the postgraduate schools (divinity, then law) he never finished. In his sophomore year at Harvard, according to the <em>Pos</em>t, “Gore’s classmates remember him spending a notable amount of time in the Dunster House basement lounge shooting pool, watching television, eating hamburgers and occasionally smoking marijuana.”</p>
<p>None of that background would matter, if there was evidence that Gore had acquired some intellectual rigor later in life. But one of the reasons his speeches, essays, books, and documentaries have been mocked so often in the past is that they have not been very carefully put together. On the subject of global warming, his posturings have so distorted the science that he has embarrassed the very scientists whose work he cites and praises – and this despite having had more than a decade to study the subject, with personal access to the top researchers in the field.</p>
<p>His arguments about media and culture are unoriginal, to put it mildly, and despite salting his discussions with various supportive quotations he omits a vast amount of research conducted over the past several decades. He also manages to come up with conclusions — such as his equation of amateur TV content with democratic dialogue — that seem harebrained. Obviously television or any other media content may propagandize or exploit viewers, by appealing to their baser, shorter-term impulses at the expense of the more judicious and “rational” parts of their minds. But in the ferocious Darwinian arena of a free media, most content wouldn’t survive if it didn’t push consumers’ emotional buttons in some way. The availability of those emotional buttons guarantees that, and whether the content is “viewer created” or professionally created makes little difference – except that an amateur production almost by definition will be less watchable.</p>
<p>To really change the character of television content, making it supportive (instead of corrosive) of civic and social institutions, would mean operating television wholly as a non-commercial public service, as many countries still do. But clearly Gore is not about to propose abolishing the commercial TV industry, with all his friendships and investments there.</p>
<p>There are other holes in Gore’s argument, such as his narrow emphasis on the political harm from television and relative neglect of the broader social harm. The past few decades have seen huge erosions in age-old institutions such as marriage, the two-parent family, friendships, and civic associations, and much of the blame for this has been <a href="http://www.bowlingalone.com/">pinned</a> on television. But Gore would rather gripe about TV’s influence on the political culture, i.e., on the culture that inflicted on him the “<a href="http://www.newstatesman.com/200706250019">terrible emotional whiplash</a>” of the 2000 election, and then chased him into the wilderness with ridicule.</p>
<p>In any case, there is hardly any point now in distinguishing “television” from other electronic media. All forms of media content – TV shows, films, music, short videos, video games, web pages, books, blogs, newspapers and magazines – can exploit our animal weaknesses in their own ways, and all are now deliverable by the Internet. How this “multimedia” environment will shape our culture is already becoming clear: The current trend, which Gore’s own TV network has followed, is towards shallower, faster-paced, more swiftly consumable content. And given the much, much greater competition inherent in the Internet’s multimedia environment, we should expect to be have our arousal circuits jolted harder than ever – in other words, we should expect more of the stuff Gore says is harmful.</p>
<p>You would think that Gore, who as a Senator was an early promoter of the Internet, would grasp some of this. But he fatuously contends that the Internet is some kind of electronic savior:</p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px;">It’s a platform for pursuing the truth, and the decentralized creation and distribution of ideas, in the same way that markets are a decentralized mechanism for the creation and distribution of goods and services. It’s a platform, in other words, for reason.</p>
<p>Yes, for “reason,” whatever that means, and also for fake Viagra, spyware and phishing scams, downloadable hip-hop and pop-up ads that buzz like mosquitos, pictures of atrocities and wayward celebrities, a mammoth porn industry, and a fast-growing population of <a href="http://www.sciencedaily.com/upi/index.php?feed=Entertainment&amp;article=UPI-1-20070602-16392300-bc-us-internetporn.xml">amateur exhibitionists</a> with webcams.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;">●</p>
<p>The sophomoric flimsiness of Gore’s ideals, and the consistency with which he betrays them, make it hard to escape the conclusion that Gore, fundamentally, is not about lessening CO2 in our atmosphere, or TV in our living rooms, as much as he is about giving us more Al Gore.</p>
<p>In this sense, it is absurd to talk of his being “liberated” or “unpackaged” or “unscripted.” His mask is still there, just better crafted this time; and circumstances have made his audience more susceptible. But his artificiality is still evident, especially when he tries, as he has for years, to sell himself to that all-important market of 18 to 34 year-olds.</p>
<p>Here he is, for example, clutching a mike and hyping CurrentTV to an arranged audience of young people:</p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px;">How many of y’all would like to see an opportunity to talk about what’s going on in your world that you can participate in with television?</p>
<p>And here he is confiding to Eric Pooley:</p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px;">Did some grilling last night with my friend Jon Bon Jovi. His new record is <em>great</em>.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-130" src="https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/ISO-the-18-34-year-old-market.jpg" alt="" width="239" height="211" /></p>
<p>Gore’s relentless popularity-seeking is in one sense predictable. After Jimmy Carter’s own electoral heartbreak, exactly twenty years before Gore’s, he set out to restore his public reputation with a number of earnest books and pious good works, and was eventually rewarded with the Nobel Peace Prize and the Albert Schweitzer Prize for Humanitarianism. Bill Clinton eagerly followed, setting up a foundation like Carter’s, and embarking on several humanitarian campaigns, for example to make HIV treatment more affordable.</p>
<p>Gore’s arc is similar, but perhaps in part because he never made it to the presidency, there is an emotional neediness about his actions that demands not just acclaim but superstardom. His relentless hypocrisy, his heavy use of self-promoting propagandistic techniques, and his hints that he is an American Churchill, suggest a narcissism that surpasses even Clinton’s.</p>
<p>The Gore comeback story does bear a superficial resemblance to Churchill’s. However, there is in some ways a better resemblance to the political comeback of one of Churchill’s contemporaries. While in his own political wilderness (spent largely in Landsberg prison) Adolf Hitler wrote a bestselling book that, like Gore’s, was much concerned with the decline of political culture and the power of propagandistic mass-persuasion techniques. He would later make deliberate, skillful, and above all deceitful use of those same techniques, somewhat as Gore does now, to create a social contagion of apocalyptic fear and thereby empower himself.</p>
<p>Gore, no Gandhi, is of course no Hitler either. But given his Hitlerian fixation on media and the manipulations of crowds, we might count some of his personal shortcomings – his spinelessness, his phoniness, his still-callow intellect – as our blessings.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><em><span style="color: #ff0000;"> </span></em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
