<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>economics &#8211; JAMES THE OBSCURE</title>
	<atom:link href="https://james-the-obscure.github.io/category/economics/feed" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://james-the-obscure.github.io/</link>
	<description>essays on culture, politics and technology</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 08 Aug 2025 03:04:24 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.7.3</generator>

<image>
	<url>https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/fav1-150x150.png</url>
	<title>economics &#8211; JAMES THE OBSCURE</title>
	<link>https://james-the-obscure.github.io/</link>
	<width>32</width>
	<height>32</height>
</image> 
	<item>
		<title>FINANCIALIZATION: AN ECONOMIC MALIGNANCY</title>
		<link>https://james-the-obscure.github.io/financialization-an-economic-malignancy</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[JtO]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 08 Aug 2025 03:04:24 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[economics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[politics & culture]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[science & medicine]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://james-the-obscure.github.io/?p=587</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Why healthcare, housing and college tuition are now so expensive The United States by any money-based standard is a wealthy country. Yet much of its population struggles financially—and this struggling subset extends well beyond the demographic groups that are traditionally dependent on handouts. Around 50 million people in the US use food banks, implying that<p><a class="readmore" href="https://james-the-obscure.github.io/financialization-an-economic-malignancy"><span class="arrow-right icon"></span>Read More</a></p>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><em>Why healthcare, housing and college tuition are now so expensive</em></p>
<p><span id="more-587"></span></p>
<p>The United States by any money-based standard is a wealthy country. Yet much of its population struggles financially—and this struggling subset extends well beyond the demographic groups that are traditionally dependent on handouts. Around 50 million people in the US use food banks, implying that they couldn’t feed themselves otherwise. A third of citizens and legal residents earn so little that they pay no federal income tax. A third—perhaps the same third—live paycheck-to-paycheck without savings. Meanwhile about nine million Americans work more than one job, presumably in a desperate attempt to make ends meet.</p>
<p>I could go on citing stats, but everyone knows that the “struggling class” is very large now, and struggles not so much because they can’t find work but because the prices for important things in their lives keep rising, while their wages fail to keep up.</p>
<p>Why their wages have failed to keep up is not hard to grasp. Mass immigration—including the legal immigration of skilled and semi-skilled foreigners—has put downward pressure on wages, as has the weakening of labor unions, DEI-based preferences (especially in years past) for blacks and browns over whites, offshoring, and automation/AI.</p>
<p>Why prices for important items keep going up—and up and up—also should not be hard to grasp, though it has been a remarkably under-covered story, as if the beneficiaries of those prices don’t want consumers to understand what has been happening.</p>
<p>What has been happening is that, mainly over the last century, American markets for healthcare goods and services, for housing, for college tuition and other big-ticket items have been modified from their traditional forms, <em>financialized</em>, in order to boost demand.</p>
<p><strong>Financed Purchasing</strong></p>
<p>Expanding credit has been the main form of financialization. Consumers like to think of expanding credit as a development that benefits them—empowers them to buy more stuff. But in an easy-credit society, it is really the business owners who are empowered. The business owners have no downside—they simply get more customers into their stores. The customers, on the other hand, while they can “buy” more stuff, are apt to be burdened increasingly by debt. More importantly, the advantage that customers <em>think</em> they have, in terms of buying power, is largely fleeting.</p>
<p>More customers means more demand, and we all know from Econ 101 that more demand, all else being equal, means higher prices. Conceivably in the long-term higher prices invite an increase in supply, which then brings prices down again. What they don’t teach in Econ 101, or at least don’t emphasize enough, is that the ramp in prices from expanded credit and other demand-boosting measures is not necessarily temporary.</p>
<p>Suppliers of goods and services <em>don’t like to lower prices</em> once they have raised them. Public companies tend to be punished in capital markets if their revenue ever drops. But even privately held companies in a given industry tend to adhere to their own industry culture or set of standard practices, and those practices, including pricing, can be very “sticky” once they are widely adopted. (Most American industries are effectively cartels in this loose sense.)</p>
<p>There are also technical, structural, and/or legal factors that can make it harder for producers to create enough supply to meet excess demand, even when they want to do so. Real estate is an obvious example: For decades now, there has been a finite and probably dwindling supply of real property in the vicinity of desirable places with good jobs and good schools. Even when there has been undeveloped land available for new home-building, states often have blocked such construction—or, worse, have devoted it to “low-income” or “multi-family” construction that dooms the quality of local schools and jobs. Moreover, corporations [link] can and often do buy up much of the scarce stock of available housing, forcing would-be home buyers to rent from them instead. Meanwhile, mass immigration, the rise of two-earner families, and ultra-low mortage rates during 2009-2022 have helped keep demand on the boil.</p>
<p>The story of the American housing market and its levitation away from affordability thus illustrates that financialization in the form of expanded credit can, over time, paradoxically weaken consumers by reducing their buying power and burdening them with increasing debt. On the positive side of the ledger, businesses and their investors are enriched, overall economic activity (GDP) is expanded, and the stock market goes up and up—all of which tends to discourage any talk of harmful side effects.</p>
<p>There is another, more intuitive way of looking at this issue, which focuses on the actual payments made by the consumer. Actual payments are, after all, what the consumer is considering as he or she mulls over a potential purchase. When the price is a simple cash price and there is no credit in the picture, the buyer considers whether that full cash amount will excessively draw down (or exceed) his or her savings, whether the purchase represents good value in that context, and so on. When the price is, instead, not a lump sum but a string of much smaller payments including interest—let’s assume monthly payments—the buyer starts to consider how the size of each monthly payment relates to his or her monthly disposable income. The net price, in other words, stops being the principal basis for the buyer’s decision, which means that there is no longer much, if any, direct and downward pressure on it, and <em>it can float upwards</em>. Only when the size of each <em>monthly payment</em> becomes unmanageable in the context of monthly income, other credit sources, liquid savings, etc., does resistance start to intensify meaningfully.</p>
<p>We have seen this phenomenon at work not only in the real estate market but also in the credit-goosed market for college tuition. Both of these markets are, of course, notorious for their price inflation in excess of CPI. The market for automobiles is well on its way to the same destination, though cars are not <em>yet</em> as badly overpriced because the switch to a credit-based norm for buying cars has begun relatively recently, and the used-car market is still largely cash-based.</p>
<p>This idea or hypothesis that financialization drives prices higher we can test with a simple thought-experiment: What would happen to real estate, college tuition and car prices if loan-based purchasing were suddenly <em>outlawed</em>? Obviously, prices in all three of those markets would have to come down dramatically, and stay down, due to the disappearance of a large subset of buyers. It should also be obvious that regaining <em>and sustaining</em> the previous levels of per-capita sales would require these industries to redesign their products and services so that selling them would be profitable at much lower prices.</p>
<p><strong>Leasingization and Insurancization</strong></p>
<p>Credit-based purchasing is not the only form of financialization. Another is to replace purchasing altogether with “leasing” or “subscribing,” as has been occuring, for example, in the markets for cars and higher-priced software. Both leasing and subscription replace lump-sum cash-on-the-barrel payments with long-term streams of monthly, quarterly or annual payments, and in that sense have the same magical effect as credit-based financialization: expanding the pool of buyers while raising effective prices.</p>
<p>Nowhere in the American economy is the malignancy of financialization more evident than in the market for healthcare goods and services. Here, of course, the old-fashioned practice of simply paying cash for doctors, hospital procedures, pharmaceuticals, etc. has been replaced by a system of “insurance”—which deserves to be in scare-quotes because it increasingly resembles a leasing or subscription-based system rather than a true insurance system.</p>
<p>The modern American health-insurance disaster originated, of course, from the understandable desire to insure people against medical costs that their savings could not cover. Health insurance in that sense was compellingly analogous to home insurance against a catastrophic fire or flood. Over time, of course, the insurancization of healthcare has come to cover not just catastrophic medical costs but virtually <em>all</em> medical costs. “What insurance do you have?” is the first question any American medical receptionist or pharmacist will ask a customer these days, even for small things like checkups or generic pills, and (as I know all too well from my own profession) academic discussions of how to fix the American healthcare system universally assume that healthcare <em>must</em> be insurance-based—it is never an object of debate, other than in the context of advocacy for 100% socialized medicine.</p>
<p>Insurancization lifts costs just as other forms of financialization do: by replacing traditional cash prices with a stream of usually monthly payments. If that was as far as it went, the situation wouldn’t be so dire. However, the potent ability of healthcare-cost-related tragedies and anxieties to move American lawmakers and voters has meant that there are now many layers of law and regulation that disrupt the insurance model. Typically, these look like moves in the direction of socialized medicine; in any case, their occurence in an insurancization context makes the price-escalation problem much, much worse.</p>
<p>One clear example is the <a href="https://www.cms.gov/priorities/your-patient-rights/emergency-room-rights">law</a> that hospitals must treat patients with health emergencies regardless of whether the patients can pay. The entirely predictable result is that hospital ERs become free primary care centers for the tens of millions of indigent people (chiefly illegal immigrants) who are not covered by other insurance schemes. Moreover, also predictably, the availability of these free centers staffed with highly trained healthcare providers acts as one of the big magnets for illegal immigration. Thus, for decades now, there has been a vicious spiral at work, in which hospitals have to charge paying customers (via insurers and premiums) more and more to cover their forced and ever-escalating <em>pro bono</em> care.</p>
<p>The set of laws that limit healthcare insurers’ ability to deny coverage for pre-existing conditions  is another example, for these laws destroy the core risk-pooling concept of insurance, allowing high-risk (typically 100% risk) individuals to crowd in, with predictably skyward pressures on premiums. The policies and traditions that make employers cover some or all healthcare insurance premiums has the same price-lifting effect, since it disperses any price-<em>lowering</em> pressure that might otherwise build up on the demand side—in other words, effectively makes it easier for people to “pay” healthcare insurance premiums that are now routinely in excess of $2,500 monthly.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-589" src="https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/pet-insurance.jpg" alt="" width="324" height="119" srcset="https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/pet-insurance.jpg 324w, https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/pet-insurance-300x110.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 324px) 100vw, 324px" /></p>
<p>This isn’t the place for me to go into all the ways by which American healthcare has become fantastically overpriced. (This 2009 <a href="https://www.theatlantic.com/magazine/archive/2009/09/how-american-health-care-killed-my-father/307617/">piece</a> in the <em>Atlantic</em> does a decent job with that, even though it was written before the ruinous Obamacare law took effect.) My main point here is just that insurancization was and is the <em>sine qua non</em> for the current American healthcare cost situation—a situation that I guess will never be fixed unless the country officially or effectively<a href="#_edn1" name="_ednref1">[1]</a> reverts to a traditional no-insurance model, presumably combining cash-basis medical centers with charitable private or state-run centers for the poor.</p>
<p>The American healthcare fiasco also serves as the ultimate cautionary tale of how financialization inflates prices, hurts consumers, and widens economic inequality. These effects, incidentally, extend well beyond the economic realm. When young people can’t afford to buy a house and start a family, they are, for example, less likely to marry and have children. When citizens are overburdened with long-term financial obligations (“I have mortgage payments, car loan payments, college loan payments and insurance premiums to pay every month”) they also are made much weaker relative to corporations and the state. In that sense, of course, corporations and the state have a strong interest in continuing and expanding financialization, and in discouraging discussions such as this one. Still, it is not hard to imagine that the vicious chain-reactions set in motion by financialization must eventually reach a point of crisis.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;">***</p>
<p><a href="#_ednref1" name="_edn1">[1]</a> The current proliferation of no-insurance primary care centers, and doctors’ practices that refuse to treat patients with certain types of insurance, shows that the system is being forced to move in this direction.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>A SURFEIT OF COMPASSION</title>
		<link>https://james-the-obscure.github.io/a-surfeit-of-compassion</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[JtO]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 19 May 2025 21:05:41 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[doom]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[economics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[politics & culture]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[women]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://james-the-obscure.github.io/?p=570</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[The &#8220;empathy economy&#8221; has become dangerously unbalanced The term “empathy economy” has been used to describe the practice, in our feminized age, of appealing to or claiming “empathy”—usually meaning empathetic compassion—in business advertising. I think it is more useful to consider the term in a different sense, that of a resource that flows in its<p><a class="readmore" href="https://james-the-obscure.github.io/a-surfeit-of-compassion"><span class="arrow-right icon"></span>Read More</a></p>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><em>The &#8220;empathy economy&#8221; has become dangerously unbalanced</em></p>
<p><span id="more-570"></span></p>
<p>The term “empathy economy” has been used to describe the practice, in our feminized age, of appealing to or claiming “empathy”—usually meaning empathetic compassion—in business advertising. I think it is more useful to consider the term in a different sense, that of a resource that flows in its own system or economy.</p>
<p>The idea here is not complicated. Humans have various resources they spend, or employ as catalysts, to obtain things for themselves and others. The resource that dominates discussions is, of course, the external resource we call <em>money</em>. But humans in their quests also routinely draw on their personal stores of energy, intelligence, inventiveness, wit and charm, social status, “a sense of style,” acting ability, psychological stability, and many other traits and characteristics. Empathy—the ability to understand another’s mindset or emotional state, not in a detached way but by feeling, to some degree, what the other is feeling—is another one of these resources.</p>
<p>Men do not lack empathy, but women on average have a stronger capacity for it, not least in regard to empathy that triggers feelings of compassion for the poor, the hungry, migrants, etc. This trait presumably has deep biological roots as an adaptation for women’s traditional roles centering on child-rearing.</p>
<p>Since women, just in the past several decades, have begun venturing from their traditional domestic domain to become <a href="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/the-great-feminization/">present and powerful in all public domains and institutions</a>, their greater capacity for and tendency towards empathetic compassion has made this sentiment more important in the shaping of policy and culture. That’s putting it mildly—the shift has been massive. Western societies since the 1960s, the period of women’s rapid ascension to power, have embraced policies that would have been hard to imagine in the 1940s or 50s. Politicians often had low partisan motivations for these policies, e.g. liberalizations of immigration law brought in new voters, while more generous welfare programs kept poorer minorities on side. But they were able to justify such policies with unprecedented ease, thanks to women—by framing them as compassionate and therefore virtuous.</p>
<p>The cultural ascent of women has brought another strong albeit not-too-surprising trend: the decline of marriage, childbearing and the stay-at-home mom. The feminist movement, which both drove and was driven by women’s new power, encouraged this trend by telling women and even girls to attach less value to marriage and homemaking, and more value to career-oriented lifestyles. By the 1990s, Western societies were essentially saturated with this messaging, which could be found even in books and TV shows for toddlers. This had many knock-on effects, of course. For example, as it became the norm for women to have careers and to add their salaries to their husbands’, home prices rose—creating an ever-higher barrier to the formation of families, and limiting the average size of families that did manage to form.</p>
<p>What does all this have to do with the empathy economy? My suggestion here is that the ascension of women to cultural and political power, and the related trend towards a more atomized, low-marriage, low-fertility society, have greatly reduced the traditional use or absorption of empathetic compassion within the family-centered domestic sphere. Since this ancient, instinctual resource is produced naturally and automatically in women—it cannot easily be shut off—it must flow somewhere; thus, it has overflowed into the public sphere.</p>
<p>To put it more crudely: childless “cat ladies” and “wine aunts” have natural womanly stores of empathetic compassion, and tend to spend it on (apart from their cats and their wine) “starving African children” or “the homeless” or “undocumented immigrants”—both directly and by steering government policy—if they don’t have loved ones to absorb it instead.</p>
<p>It&#8217;s not hard to see as well that, as the demographic presence and cultural power of these compassion-givers have expanded, society has catered increasingly to their needs, e.g. by making it ever easier for these women to pour succor over the world’s unfortunates. And, of course, politicians, businessmen and their marketing experts have sought to exploit the sentiments and sentimentality of this important group.</p>
<p>By now, moreover, greater flows of empathetic compassion in the public sphere have become very much the norm. In that “cultural norm” sense—and cultural norms appear to bind women more strongly, on average compared to men—we should expect these sentiments to be prominent not only among single, childless women but even among women who have children.</p>
<p>My central point here, then, is simply that Western and other societies in which women have strong public presence and power are necessarily awash in empathetic compassion, which at least helps to explain many new and remarkable cultural and policy trends.</p>
<p>I haven’t attached a “value judgment” to all this. But the fixation on short-term emotional payoff that is typical of compassion-driven or compassion-justified new policies and cultural traits seems inherently dangerous, due to its<a href="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/mistresses-of-misrule/"> relative blindness to long-term consequences</a>. It is also dangerous, and frankly stupid, to assume that a trait evolved for the domestic sphere (or a relatively simple <a href="https://thoughtsofstone.github.io/women-inclusivity-and-the-paleolithic/">paleolithic social sphere</a>) will work well in a modern complex social setting.</p>
<p>In any case, it follows from my argument here that, <em>ceteris paribus</em>, increasing fertility and family formation to more traditional, demographically healthy levels would eventually—against the resistance of the new cultural norm—reduce the current surplus of empathetic compassion in the public sphere. This in turn should make government policies and non-governmental actions aimed at “helping people” more judicious and sustainable, though of course Western societies face so many other problems that we may never experience a solution to this one.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;">***</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>MY SWEAT FOR YOUR SINS</title>
		<link>https://james-the-obscure.github.io/my-sweat-for-your-sins</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[JtO]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 15 Jul 2010 04:20:44 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[economics]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[politics & culture]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://james-the-obscure.github.io/?p=166</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[What ancient logic lies behind our modern endurance-for-charity events?   Originally published July 15, 2010 A couple of weeks ago in my town, someone organized a “Be Great 5K Run &#38; Fun Walk,” in which people ran and fun-walked, and a handful of businesses – a bank, a brewery, a sport shoe store – donated<p><a class="readmore" href="https://james-the-obscure.github.io/my-sweat-for-your-sins"><span class="arrow-right icon"></span>Read More</a></p>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><em>What ancient logic lies behind our modern endurance-for-charity events?</em></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a href="http://hereticalnotions.com/2010/07/15/my-sweat-for-your-sins/bergman-7th-seal/" rel="attachment wp-att-227"> </a></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img fetchpriority="high" decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-169" src="https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/mysweatforyoursins.jpg" alt="" width="600" height="450" srcset="https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/mysweatforyoursins.jpg 600w, https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/mysweatforyoursins-300x225.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 600px) 100vw, 600px" /></p>
<p><span style="color: #ff6600;"><span id="more-166"></span></span></p>
<p><span style="color: #ff6600;"><em>Originally published July 15, 2010</em></span></p>
<p>A couple of weeks ago in my town, someone organized a “Be Great 5K Run &amp; Fun Walk,” in which people ran and fun-walked, and a handful of businesses – a bank, a brewery, a sport shoe store – donated money to the local Boys &amp; Girls Clubs. The following week I learned that two teens from my local neighborhood have been cycling across the USA with Lance Armstrong’s foundation, to raise money for cancer research. It occurred to me that these ritualized suffering-for-charity events are now so common and popular that on any given weekend they must involve at least tens of thousands of people throughout the Western world. There are fun runs, walkathons, full and partial marathons, swim-a-thons, scuba-dive-a-thons, ski-a-thons, climb-a-thons, and bottom-chafing trans-continental bike-a-thons. Yet no one ever questions the behavioral logic of these things.</p>
<p>Typically for one of these events, a group of charitably-minded local people agrees to undergo some feat of minor endurance. There may be special inducements for the winners, but often there is none. In economic terms, the most important goal may be to create a local audience for advertisements&#8212;on banners, t-shirts, cups, etc.&#8212;which local donors will purchase. Thus the sweat of the sufferers is transmuted into dollars for charity.</p>
<p>It seems a clever way to crowdsource philanthropy. But there may be more to it than that. In many of these events, donors are not compensated with significant advertising or even recognition. Moreover, the donations are often made in the name of a particular participant, and linked to the level of endurance achieved&#8212;such as miles run or laps swum. This linkage is rather mysterious. One party deliberately suffers; another party correspondingly pays; a third party&#8212;a charity&#8212;benefits; and everyone ends up feeling that they have done something good for their fellow man.</p>
<p>I suspect that the logic at work here goes unsaid because it is essentially spiritual. And since these charity-endurance affairs are found predominantly in Western societies, I can’t help wondering whether they derive somehow from the original “West,” namely medieval Europe. In that environment, public acts of endurance and suffering for the common good were very prominent&#8212;not too surprisingly, since they represented the central theme of the dominant religion. Their logic also was widely understood: One’s material suffering could serve as a gift to God, who in return would grant benefits to the giver, or more broadly to his family or community.</p>
<p>This is the logic of sacrifice, and it has appeared in so many cultures that it is likely to have originated prehistorically. However, in medieval European societies, there were forms of public, charitable endurance that I think bear a particularly strong resemblance to those of today.</p>
<p>One example is the walkathon known as the pilgrimage, in which groups of people would spend weeks or months travelling hundreds of miles to places of special religious significance. Jerusalem ranked highest among these destinations, and wealthy nobles or merchants who could not be bothered to join these pilgrimages were often called upon to sponsor them. The payoff was a spiritual boost not only to the pilgrims and their sponsors but also to the friends and loved ones for whom the pilgrims offered prayers. Thus a pilgrimage could be a charitable act.</p>
<p>The odd medieval practice of self-flagellation, often practiced in groups, also bears a resemblance to our modern charity endurance events. It appears to have originated with certain monastic orders, who at times would emerge from their cloisters and parade through nearby towns, publicly scourging themselves and streaming with blood. In the late Middle Ages these monastic displays turned into a mass movement. According to the historian Norman Cohn, cults of “flagellants” roved from town to town and were popularly seen “not simply as penitents who were atoning for their own sins but as martyrs who were taking upon themselves the sins of the world…” The belief that the sins of the world had brought the deadly pandemic known as the Black Death made the flagellants’ public service seem especially important, and certainly worth paying for. “It became a privilege to welcome and assist such people,” wrote Cohn. Ordinary folk donated to the flagellants, and “even the urban authorities drew freely upon public funds” to do the same.</p>
<p>From the perspective of evolutionary psychology it is not hard to see how the old logic of sacrifice could have been both adaptive and culturally persistent: To believe that one’s suffering or loss can be used as a sort of currency, with which to buy benefits for oneself and others, should provide quite a psychological boost, potentially enabling one to bear severe hardships.</p>
<p>It would be easy to make too much of these resemblances between past and present, but some could give us practical insights. For example, one of the most common forms of self-sacrifice in medieval times was fasting, often of the severe and continuous variety. Even in extreme forms it was not viewed as an “eating disorder,” but instead as a mark of self-discipline and a way to overcome sin and guilt, thereby achieving a state of spiritual grace. Very similar themes of “discipline,” “purity” and “perfection” are emphasized by modern anorexics (e.g., on their websites), although the idea that they might be acting out an ancient reflex&#8212;meant to cleanse their sins and ours&#8212;does not yet seem to have occurred to at least the vast majority of those who treat them.</p>
<p>This comparative perspective might also help us to better understand the modern <em>jihadi</em> suicide bomber. The sacrificial aspect of his motives is obvious. But the resemblance of his journey to a pilgrimage doesn’t seem to have been widely noticed. In certain quarters of modern Islam the suicide bombing appears to be considered a special variant of pilgrimage, more exclusive than the traditional <em>Hajj</em> to Mecca but fulfilling a nearly identical spiritual purpose. “<em>Hajj</em> or <em>jihad</em>?” is a choice often posed to young Muslim men, and “Your <em>jihad</em> is <em>Hajj</em>” was Muhammad&#8217;s invocation to Muslim women, meaning that their spiritual struggles are best worked out in pilgrimage. Certainly among medieval Christians, the lines between pilgrimage and armed crusade were often blurred. Thus both the <em>jihadi</em> suicide bomber and our secular sufferers for charity may be moving along the same, well-worn path in the human psyche.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
