<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>JtO &#8211; JAMES THE OBSCURE</title>
	<atom:link href="https://james-the-obscure.github.io/author/fnenn77/feed" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://james-the-obscure.github.io/</link>
	<description>essays on culture, politics and technology</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Thu, 12 Dec 2024 20:27:41 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.7.1</generator>

<image>
	<url>https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/fav1-150x150.png</url>
	<title>JtO &#8211; JAMES THE OBSCURE</title>
	<link>https://james-the-obscure.github.io/</link>
	<width>32</width>
	<height>32</height>
</image> 
	<item>
		<title>DEMOCRACY IN AMERICA: THE PROBLEM OF ELECTORATE-PACKING</title>
		<link>https://james-the-obscure.github.io/electorate-packing-is-as-american-as-apple-pie</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[JtO]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 04 Nov 2024 23:08:13 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[politics & culture]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://james-the-obscure.github.io/?p=517</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[a short history &#160; Many were warning, before the recent election, that the Democrats’ open-borders “electorate-packing” strategy, if allowed to continue, would soon make them as dominant nationwide as they already were in immigrant-filled California. It would be hard to dispute that this has been the Democrats’ goal, since they no longer conceal their desire<p><a class="readmore" href="https://james-the-obscure.github.io/electorate-packing-is-as-american-as-apple-pie"><span class="arrow-right icon"></span>Read More</a></p>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><em>a short history </em><span id="more-517"></span></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>Many were warning, before the recent election, that the Democrats’ open-borders “electorate-packing” strategy, if allowed to continue, would soon make them as dominant nationwide as they already were in immigrant-filled California.</p>
<p>It would be hard to dispute that this has been the Democrats’ goal, since they no longer conceal their desire to give even illegal immigrants citizenship and voting rights, as well as other benefits that effectively buy their votes. Yet it seems worth pointing out that electorate expansion for partisan advantage is not a new feature of American politics. Indeed, America’s political history is, to a surprising extent, the history of the use of this tactic—by virtually all parties.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><strong>The First Era of Immigrant-Fueled Dominance</strong></p>
<p>The US at its origin was underpopulated, compared to most European countries. It also had enormous adjacent territories that it wanted to occupy, and expected to have to defend. It therefore needed more people, and, to attract them, had to offer them relatively quick acquisition of citizenship and voting rights.</p>
<p>Thus, in the country’s first decades, virtually all parties accepted, at least broadly, the necessity of electorate expansions, firstly from immigration and secondly from expansions of voting rights—rights that in most states had been given only to adult, white, property-owning males.</p>
<p>It wasn’t long, though, before electoral expansions began to be seen as helping some parties more than others. English, Scots, and Welsh immigrants, who were mostly Protestants, tended to prefer the Federalists of Hamilton and Adams, while the more numerous Irish and German immigrants—and Catholic immigrants generally—flocked to the Democratic-Republicans of Jefferson and Madison. The Federalists’ Alien and Sedition Acts of 1798, which greatly stiffened citizenship requirements, were, in part, reactions to an ongoing wave of Irish immigration—and when Jefferson’s party triumphed in the 1800 elections and repealed most of those measures or allowed them to expire, it effectively expanded the Irish vote in its favor.</p>
<p>The Democratic-Republican Party soon came apart, but its main successor, the Democratic Party, retained the allegiance of Irish and Germans, the top migrant ethnicities of that era. With their help, the Democrats dominated antebellum politics. Immigrant inflows were sometimes strong enough to provoke nativist movements, the largest, in the 1850s, being led by the anti-immigrant American (a.k.a. “Know-Nothing”) Party. But such movements tended to die out when immigrant waves subsided, and the Democrats’ electoral supremacy ended only when they split over slavery in 1860.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><strong>Blacks and Women</strong></p>
<p>The War Between the States was, in part, a continuation of the struggle that had emerged in the 1850s between Democrats and their up-and-coming rivals, the Republicans. Even many northern-state Democrats (known as “copperheads”) opposed the war and wanted to let the southern states go. In this sense, it is not too surprising that the Union army’s triumph on the field led to political maneuvers—including a colossal re-engineering of the southern electorate—aimed at ensuring GOP dominance.</p>
<p>President Lincoln had felt that African Americans, following emancipation, should live and govern themselves according to their own ways on their own lands, preferably in Africa. But after Lincoln’s assassination, radicals in the Republican-controlled Congress prevailed with their own plan for the freed slaves. They saw to it that Black men were given US citizenship and voting rights in southern states, even as southern White men’s voting rights were limited—and many former Confederates were barred from holding office. The Republicans set many of these measures in stone by forcing the southern states to ratify the Fourteenth and Fifteenth Amendments to the Constitution. There were moral justifications for all this. But the Republicans also had a strong partisan motive, which, to their political opponents, and to many subsequent historians, was the real driver of their policies and represented an enormous abuse of power.</p>
<p>As Black men became loyal Republican voters during Reconstruction, the many White women who had supported Black suffrage renewed their efforts to win their own voting rights. Here again, the Republicans saw an opportunity for electoral gains. Ultimately, they provided nearly three-quarters of the “yea” votes in Congress for the passage of the 19<sup>th</sup> Amendment, which outlawed voting rights restrictions based on sex, and thereby added tens of millions of women to the electorate.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><strong>A Reversal of Fortune</strong></p>
<p>The Democrats reversed these Republican advantages chiefly in three ways: The first was their effective opposition to Reconstruction, which led to their re-capture of southern states, the suppression of the Black vote in those states, and the establishment of the “Jim Crow” racial segregation system. The second, in the 1930s and 40s, was the welfarism of the New Deal, which attracted the votes of many African Americans as well as lower-income voters of all races. The third was the party’s transformation, in the 1960s, into a civil rights party—powered, as the Republican party had been a century before, by an unusual level of political dominance following a presidential assassination. By the 1968 election, Black neighborhoods were voting Democrat at rates approaching 100 percent. The Democrats’ welfare, affirmative action and feminist policies also increasingly endeared them to women.</p>
<p>The Democrats didn’t just capture voters from prior electorate expansions; they also turned this tactic decisively into their own again with the 1965 Hart-Celler Immigration and Nationality Act, which abolished country-of-origin restrictions on immigrants. Combined with affirmative action laws that extended preferences to immigrant nonwhites, this expansion brought another enduring electoral windfall for the Democrats.</p>
<p>In 1971, the Democrat-controlled Congress approved a constitutional amendment that expanded the electorate further by lowering the minimum voting age from 21 to 18. The “old enough to fight, old enough to vote” argument helped make it a relatively non-partisan event, but since younger people tended to vote left, it represented a net gain by the Democrats.</p>
<p>The Republicans, in the decades that followed, tried to improve their image among the newly enfranchised, for example by signing on to various immigration-liberalizing bills, including amnesties for illegal immigrants. It availed them little, as the Democrats maintained a tight grip on every group that had become voters through immigration and other electorate expansions. In the 2012 presidential election, the Democratic candidate (Obama) received 93 percent of the Black vote, 71 percent of the Hispanic vote, 73 percent of the Asian vote, 85 percent of the Muslim vote, 55 percent of the female vote, 63 percent of the low-household-income (&lt;$30K) vote, and 60 percent of the vote among 18-to-29-year-olds. The Republican candidate (Romney), an uncontroversial moderate, therefore lost badly despite getting 59 percent of the white vote—and 62 percent of the white male vote, representing the country’s pre-Civil-War electorate.</p>
<p><img fetchpriority="high" decoding="async" class="aligncenter wp-image-520" src="https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/filams.jpg" alt="" width="344" height="352" srcset="https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/filams.jpg 314w, https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/filams-293x300.jpg 293w" sizes="(max-width: 344px) 100vw, 344px" /></p>
<p><strong>Feature or bug?</strong></p>
<p>What happened next is very recent history: In the middle 2010s, Republicans belatedly saw how immigrant-fueled electorate expansion had imperiled them, and chose the most anti-immigrant leader available, overlooking his many flaws. He won an upset victory in the 2016 presidential election, but made no lasting progress in his first term, and when the Democrats took over again, they moved towards endgame with an overt open-borders policy. The Democrats’ power, however, was limited by their own dissident legislators (Manchin, Sinema) and the Republicans were spared the death-blow of mass amnesty for illegals. At the same time, the Democrats’ complacent extremism began to repel many of the voters they thought they owned <em>en bloc</em>. Thus, Republicans were given another reprieve in 2024—and vowed that this time they would really fix things.</p>
<p>It is tempting to conclude from all this that occasional electorate expansions, and subsequent partisan tussles over those new voters, may be messy but are essentially ordinary aspects of a modern republic. American politics has, at times, featured electoral cheats or hacks including vote-buying, ballot-harvesting, and the stuffing of ballot-boxes with fake ballots, yet the country is wealthy compared to most Western peers, and its citizens still consider it mostly functional and “democratic.” Also, few Americans now would question the legitimacy of all the citizenship and/or voting rights extensions since the USA’s founding.</p>
<p>On the other hand, all these extensions were at least somewhat controversial in their day. Most should have been, since electoral expansions that principally benefit one party have the same effect—and intent—as large-scale, long-term vote-buying, and are much less reversible. They are at least as objectionable as the “court-packing” that both FDR and Joe Biden threatened and backed away from. Perhaps most importantly, though, the Democrats’ aggressive electorate-packing attempts over the past four years have given us glimpses (e.g., Haitians in Ohio) of the <em>Camp of the Saints</em> dystopia to which this tactic will take us if it continues to be used.</p>
<p>This is, then, an issue that the incoming administration needs to consider seriously, since the Democrats can be expected to resume their open-borders electorate-packing measures, without compunction, the next time they control Congress and the White House. If Republicans want to talk about somehow blocking or outlawing this practice, though, they should probably start by acknowledging their party’s role in normalizing its use.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;">***</p>
<p><a href="#_ftnref1" name="_ftn1"></a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>BY THE HORNS</title>
		<link>https://james-the-obscure.github.io/by-the-horns</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[JtO]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 20 Jul 2016 19:47:49 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[politics & culture]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://james-the-obscure.github.io/?p=21</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Thoughts on tauromaquia. Originally published 20 July 2016 &#160; About a hundred fair Julys ago—it seems that long anyway—I ran with the bulls in Pamplona. If you&#8217;d asked me why back then, I would have said simply that it seemed a fun thing to do, a thrill, an &#8220;experience&#8221; to tick off a tourist&#8217;s list.<p><a class="readmore" href="https://james-the-obscure.github.io/by-the-horns"><span class="arrow-right icon"></span>Read More</a></p>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><span style="font-size: 14pt; font-family: book antiqua,palatino,serif;"><em>Thoughts on tauromaquia.</em></span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: 14pt; font-family: book antiqua,palatino,serif;"><span id="more-21"></span></span></p>
<p><span style="color: #ff6600;"><em>Originally published 20 July 2016</em></span></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><span style="font-size: 14pt; font-family: book antiqua,palatino,serif;">About a hundred fair Julys ago—it seems that long anyway—I ran with the bulls in Pamplona.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: 14pt; font-family: book antiqua,palatino,serif;">If you&#8217;d asked me <em>why</em> back then, I would have said simply that it seemed a fun thing to do, a thrill, an &#8220;experience&#8221; to tick off a tourist&#8217;s list. It would have felt silly to describe it as a chance to prove one&#8217;s courage. But I think that is mainly what it was.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: 14pt; font-family: book antiqua,palatino,serif;">We bull-runners were all men or boys. Nearly all of us wore the traditional uniform of the <em>encierro</em> (thin white cotton shirt, red bandanna). Many of us also carried a rolled-up newspaper, said to be useful for distracting the bull with a swat to the hindquarters if he happened to be goring a friend.</span></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-31" src="https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/pamplona1.jpg" alt="" width="400" height="266" srcset="https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/pamplona1.jpg 400w, https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/pamplona1-300x200.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 400px) 100vw, 400px" /></p>
<p><span style="font-size: 14pt; font-family: book antiqua,palatino,serif;">A rocket went off and burst to warn us as the first bulls were released from a pen into the zigzag course of the town&#8217;s narrow streets. The animals had to pound down a lane and round a corner before they encountered most of the human runners who waited for them.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: 14pt; font-family: book antiqua,palatino,serif;">Now here they came. Who knew how fast those half-ton monsters moved? We runners lurched forward, with the twin fears of injury on the one hand and cowardice on the other. To avoid both, it certainly helped to be in a group. Running alone, becoming the sole target of all those horned beasts, was almost inconceivable. But there was danger too in being amid a jostling pack: many runners stumbled and fell with, it seemed, too little time to rise and evade what approached with such inhuman speed.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: 14pt; font-family: book antiqua,palatino,serif;">And suddenly that first group of bulls and steers rumbled by, all hooves and bulk and undulant muscle. Like most of the runners, I had managed to get to one side of the narrow, cobblestoned street to let them pass. Some other runners, though, were caught in the middle and sent sprawling. A miraculous few stayed up, jogging gamely, as the great beasts missed them by inches.</span></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-467" src="https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/encierro1.jpg" alt="" width="400" height="596" srcset="https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/encierro1.jpg 400w, https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/encierro1-201x300.jpg 201w" sizes="(max-width: 400px) 100vw, 400px" /></p>
<p><span style="font-size: 14pt; font-family: book antiqua,palatino,serif;">I ran again, found daylight, heard the next pack coming, let them pass, and just managed to sprint into the <em>plaza de toros</em> before the last bulls entered and the gate closed behind them.</span></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-460" src="https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/Pamplona-1947.gif" alt="" width="320" height="240" /></p>
<p><span style="font-size: 14pt; font-family: book antiqua,palatino,serif;">To my surprise, if no one else’s, a series of younger bulls was then let out to confront the few dozen of us who had made it into the bullring. One of the first animals took aim at a German tourist—a scruffy-looking character, <em>borracho </em>and slow—and chased him down easily, driving him face-first into the dirt. The guy might well have been killed, had the young bull’s horns not been padded. Later the same animal, chasing one of us, leapt over the plaza&#8217;s <em>barrera</em> and raced around forcing panicked bullring staff and spectators to spill into the comparative safety of the bullring itself. We runners laughed with relief as we took a breather, but soon were eager for the next <em>novillo toro</em> to be let out so that this primal test of our courage could start again.</span></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><span style="font-size: 14pt; font-family: book antiqua,palatino,serif;"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-443" src="https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/goya.jpg" alt="" width="600" height="372" srcset="https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/goya.jpg 600w, https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/goya-300x186.jpg 300w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 600px) 100vw, 600px" /></span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: 14pt; font-family: book antiqua,palatino,serif;">At the time it seemed a forgiving test. It was clear that tourists in the <em>encierro,</em> especially the drunk ones, were routinely gored or trampled, but I assumed that truly serious or fatal injuries were very rare. There wasn&#8217;t yet an Internet with which one could immediately <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2015/aug/24/man-killed-during-bull-run-in-spain-pushes-death-toll-to-10-so-far-for-year">check </a>such <a href="http://abcnews.go.com/Travel/story?id=118926&amp;page=1">statistics</a>. Even at the real bullfights, in the afternoons at Pamplona, where the bulls were injured and maddened and vengeful, the matadors appeared to be in little danger; one of them kept such a cautious distance between the bull&#8217;s horns and his own costumed hide that the spectators began to hurl insults—<em>maric</em><em>ó</em><em>n! el peor!</em>—and even seat cushions into the ring.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: 14pt; font-family: book antiqua,palatino,serif;">However, some Spanish bullfighters were reputed to be very skillful and brave. Among them was Jose Cubero (“El Yiyo”) Sanchez. Later that summer, in southwestern France, I saw posters listing him in the lineup for a <em>corrida</em> to be held in Bayonne in September.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: 14pt; font-family: book antiqua,palatino,serif;">Alas, Sanchez didn’t make it to Bayonne, or even to September. On the 30<sup>th</sup> of August, in Madrid, he was nearing the end of a seemingly routine bout when he attempted the ritual sword-thrust, which is meant to go into the bull’s upper back and thence downward through the heart. He missed. The angry bull turned, charged, upended the matador, and—as the 21-year old tried to scramble away on all fours—stuck him with his left horn in the upper back. In full view of a large crowd, the bull lifted Sanchez completely off his feet so that he slid down the horn until his own heart was pierced.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: 14pt; font-family: book antiqua,palatino,serif;"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-444" src="https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/yiyomuerte.jpg" alt="" width="600" height="337" srcset="https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/yiyomuerte.jpg 600w, https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/yiyomuerte-300x169.jpg 300w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 600px) 100vw, 600px" /></span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: 14pt; font-family: book antiqua,palatino,serif;">Having done his work, the bull let the man go. Sanchez ran just a few steps before collapsing, famously gasping his last words, &#8220;este toro me ha matado,&#8221; as they rushed him in vain to the ring infirmary.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: 14pt; font-family: book antiqua,palatino,serif;">Those memories came back last week when I read about the unfortunate Victor Barrio, the first matador to die in the bullring since Sanchez.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: 14pt; font-family: book antiqua,palatino,serif;">It happened at a late-night <em>corrida</em> in Teruel. Towards the end of a fight with a bull called Lorenzo, Barrio goaded the bleeding, wary animal to charge the cape. The bull at last did as he was bidden, but as Barrio swiveled for the next pass, Lorenzo without warning shifted his attention from cape to matador—some later spoke of an unlucky, cape-lifting gust of wind—and with an upthrusting left horn to the back of the knee the bull sent his human tormentor leaping evasively into the air.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: 14pt; font-family: book antiqua,palatino,serif;"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-445" src="https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/barrio-upended.jpg" alt="" width="500" height="309" srcset="https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/barrio-upended.jpg 500w, https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/barrio-upended-300x185.jpg 300w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 500px) 100vw, 500px" /></span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: 14pt; font-family: book antiqua,palatino,serif;">It was a relatively minor goring, but the bull was not finished. The moment the matador hit the dirt, Lorenzo, using the same left horn, began trying to stab him in the chest. Barrio started to roll away but Lorenzo quickly hooked him below the right arm and, hopping on front hooves to make full use of his 529-kg weight, drove the horn most of the way through the man’s chest cavity.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: 14pt; font-family: book antiqua,palatino,serif;"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-446" src="https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/barrio-gored-600.jpg" alt="" width="600" height="327" srcset="https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/barrio-gored-600.jpg 600w, https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/barrio-gored-600-300x164.jpg 300w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 600px) 100vw, 600px" /></span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: 14pt; font-family: book antiqua,palatino,serif;">Lorenzo then jerked the embedded horn sideways for good measure, destroying Barrio’s right lung and thoracic aorta among other things, and violently lifting his body off the ground. When, just about six seconds after making that first sudden stab to the leg, Lorenzo flung his conquered adversary off his horn, the 29-year old matador had only enough time to pull his arm over the wound in his side and roll over, face down, before darkness overcame him. He died in full view of the crowd, his eyes opening sightlessly, his muscles relaxing into the flaccidity that in traditional societies marks the release of the soul to heaven.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: 14pt; font-family: book antiqua,palatino,serif;">In bullfights, incidentally, that is the ideal ending: the killer’s thrust swiftly stops the victim’s heart. Perhaps no bull has ever turned the tables as perfectly as Lorenzo.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: 14pt; font-family: book antiqua,palatino,serif;">And Lorenzo as far as I know had never practiced fighting humans. Like the brother taurus that killed Sanchez, he seemed to know from long-evolved instinct to use his horns to maximum effect by going, when he could, for his antagonist’s chest. As any hunter or soldier will tell you, the chest of a mammal is the prime kill zone, easily hit and especially vulnerable to mortal wounds.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: 14pt; font-family: book antiqua,palatino,serif;">In the <em>plaza de toros</em> at Teruel that night, it all happened too quickly for the spectators to process. Barrio had been gored somehow and was down&#8212;that was obvious. But there was no visible gush of blood. That this was because his heart had almost immediately been stopped was unimaginable. The man had been standing, smoothly handling the bull with his cape just a few moments before. His young wife, though she was seated even closer to the action than most other spectators, assumed her husband’s wounds <a href="http://www.dailymail.co.uk/news/article-3687837/Widow-Spanish-bullfighter-gored-death-eyes-reveals-couple-planned-try-children-September.html">couldn’t</a> be fatal.</span></p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px;"><span style="font-size: 14pt; font-family: book antiqua,palatino,serif;">“I was saying to myself, ‘It’s serious but he’s going to survive, he’s been gored, but nowadays no-one dies from being gored, there’ll be a solution.</span></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><span style="font-size: 14pt; font-family: book antiqua,palatino,serif;">**</span></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><span style="font-size: 14pt; font-family: book antiqua,palatino,serif;">No one dies? What then would be the point? As Hemingway observed, “Bullfighting is the only art in which the artist is in danger of death.”</span></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><span style="font-size: 14pt; font-family: book antiqua,palatino,serif;"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-447" src="https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/hemingway-encierro.jpg" alt="" width="574" height="402" srcset="https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/hemingway-encierro.jpg 574w, https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/hemingway-encierro-300x210.jpg 300w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 574px) 100vw, 574px" /></span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: 14pt; font-family: book antiqua,palatino,serif;">Barrio and Sanchez surely knew that—knew about the danger, at least, even if they also knew that bullfighting doesn’t always rise to the level of art.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: 14pt; font-family: book antiqua,palatino,serif;">Alas, these days, talk of danger and art are mostly lost on the audience beyond the bullring. The <em>bien pensants</em> of social media heaped scorn on Barrio and bullfighting in response to the story of his death.</span></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><span style="font-size: 14pt; font-family: book antiqua,palatino,serif;"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-448" src="https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/anti-tauromaq.jpg" alt="" width="400" height="334" srcset="https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/anti-tauromaq.jpg 400w, https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/anti-tauromaq-300x251.jpg 300w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 400px) 100vw, 400px" /></span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: 14pt; font-family: book antiqua,palatino,serif;">Even in Spain, the rapid modern shifts in customs—largely driven, as elsewhere, by the cultural ascendancy of women—have meant that bullfighting is treated more and more as a bloody relic of a barbarous past.</span></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><span style="font-size: 14pt; font-family: book antiqua,palatino,serif;"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-449" src="https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/peta-protesters.jpg" alt="" width="500" height="334" srcset="https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/peta-protesters.jpg 500w, https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/peta-protesters-300x200.jpg 300w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 500px) 100vw, 500px" /></span></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><span style="font-size: 14pt; font-family: book antiqua,palatino,serif;"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-450" src="https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/women-protesting-bullfights.jpg" alt="" width="574" height="352" srcset="https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/women-protesting-bullfights.jpg 574w, https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/women-protesting-bullfights-300x184.jpg 300w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 574px) 100vw, 574px" /></span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: 14pt; font-family: book antiqua,palatino,serif;">Bullfighting is undeniably cruel, and sometimes can seem irredeemably so. At Pamplona all those years ago, I saw one bull killed in a most unsporting way, which was nevertheless common: The swords had all missed so that the matador, amid the crowd&#8217;s jeers, had finally to sever the poor kneeling animal’s spinal cord with a dagger to put it out of its misery. And still the bloody travesty continued: When they tried to hook the bull’s carcass to a team of horses that would drag it from the ring, someone slapped the horses prematurely, before the attachment was made. The horses sprinted forward, unloaded and out of control, until the one on the far right smashed against the edge of the arena’s exit, and was left writhing on the ground with serious injuries. Someone then had to come out and put <em>it</em> out of its misery, with a pistol if memory serves. It seemed a horrible waste&#8212;though almost incredibly it was much worse a century ago, when the picadors&#8217; horses went unpadded and were often gored so badly that their intestines spilled out and dragged on the sand behind them.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: 14pt; font-family: book antiqua,palatino,serif;">And yet I can&#8217;t join the anti-tauromaquian chorus. I&#8217;m not a Spaniard and I&#8217;m generally loath to criticize other cultures&#8212;to each his own, I&#8217;m inclined to say. More specifically I think bullfighting is too ancient, and potentially too beneficial, to just throw away.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: 14pt; font-family: book antiqua,palatino,serif;">Bullfighting is many things. It is for example a drama&#8212;Hemingway called it a tragedy&#8212;symbolizing the eternal contest between man and beast: brains vs. brawn. Plausibly it also represents the higher, more hopeful struggle of mankind vs. its own mortality.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: 14pt; font-family: book antiqua,palatino,serif;">Most straightforwardly, though, bullfighting is a highly ritualized, indeed professionalized elaboration of simple, prove-your-courage-with-a-deadly-beast displays—displays that are still largely preserved in the public <em>encierros</em> at Pamplona and other Spanish towns, but that date back to prehistoric times. Ancient Mediterranean cultures are suffused with themes involving bulls and men, typically in conflict. The most famous surviving artifacts of the early bronze-age Minoan culture, of roughly 3,500 years ago, feature very <em>encierro</em>-like &#8220;bull leaping&#8221; activities.</span></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><span style="font-size: 14pt; font-family: book antiqua,palatino,serif;"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-451" src="https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/bull-leaper-fresco.jpg" alt="" width="900" height="554" srcset="https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/bull-leaper-fresco.jpg 900w, https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/bull-leaper-fresco-300x185.jpg 300w, https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/bull-leaper-fresco-768x473.jpg 768w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 900px) 100vw, 900px" /></span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: 14pt; font-family: book antiqua,palatino,serif;">Arguably the basic meme of man vs. bull dates back all the way to humans&#8217; earliest surviving narrative tale, the <em>Epic of Gilgamesh</em>, which is about 4,000 years old.</span></p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px;"><span style="font-size: 14pt; font-family: book antiqua,palatino,serif;">The Bull seemed indestructible, for hours they fought, till Gilgamesh dancing in front of the Bull, lured it with his tunic and bright weapons, and Enkidu thrust his sword, deep into the Bull&#8217;s neck, and killed it.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: 14pt; font-family: book antiqua,palatino,serif;">There is little in this rich history to suggest that bullfighting, or even the bull-running and bull-teasing of <em>encierros</em>, have as their aim the &#8220;torture&#8221; of beasts for perverse enjoyment, or the competition of “sport,” or even the attainment of &#8220;artistry.&#8221; All those can be (and generally are) realized in other ways that are much less dangerous to the practitioner.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: 14pt; font-family: book antiqua,palatino,serif;">It is that danger, that risk of grave injury or death, and the simple, primal manifestation of that risk in a powerful animal, that makes bullfighting and related amateur activities unique. One social benefit is that it teaches men the possibility of courage in themselves; it glorifies that courage as something worth having; and it evokes the ancient past in which such courage was utterly necessary.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: 14pt; font-family: book antiqua,palatino,serif;">Is courage so valueless these days that we can afford to part with practices that encourage it? How could we ever be sure?</span></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><span style="font-size: 14pt; font-family: book antiqua,palatino,serif;">**</span></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><span style="font-size: 14pt; font-family: book antiqua,palatino,serif;">If bullfighting statistics are any guide, then we the men of the West&#8212;considering matadors as our proxies&#8212;are losing our courage. <a href="https://thelastarena.wordpress.com/2015/02/25/533-professional-bullfighters-killed-in-the-ring-since-1700/">More than 500</a> professional bullfighters have been killed in the ring since 1700, but only a handful of those deaths have occurred in the last half-century. Better medical care for wounded matadors and an improving economy (which makes bullfighting less attractive as a career choice) have something to do with that discrepancy, but surely not everything.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: 14pt; font-family: book antiqua,palatino,serif;">Another factor seems to be that matadors are on average less willing to work in close proximity to bulls&#8212;that has been part of <em>aficionados&#8217;</em> litany for much of the past century, as the great names of bulfighting&#8217;s heyday have faded into memory. There have also been, it is said, more of the shady tricks that weaken bulls before they get to the ring. Among these is <a href="http://www.independent.co.uk/news/world/europe/out-of-spain-matadors-on-horns-of-a-dilemma-1393519.html">horn-shaving</a>, a practice that Hemingway <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Death-Afternoon-Ernest-Hemingway/dp/0684801450/">described </a>thusly:</span></p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px;"><span style="font-size: 14pt; font-family: book antiqua,palatino,serif;">To protect the leading matadors, the bulls&#8217; horns had been cut off at the points and then shaved and filed down so that they looked like real horns. But they were as tender at the points as a fingernail that has been cut to the quick and if the bull could be made to bang them against the planks of the barrera, they would hurt so that he would be careful about hitting anything else. . .</span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: 14pt; font-family: book antiqua,palatino,serif;">Even Manolete, often considered the greatest matador of all time, was sometimes protected this way. In the 1930s and 40s his bullfights brought in so much revenue that he became an industry in his own right&#8212;and that industry didn&#8217;t want to lose its key man.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: 14pt; font-family: book antiqua,palatino,serif;">But if Manolete&#8217;s reputation suffered a bit from the shaving, his fatal goring in 1947 redeemed it. Late in an August bout at Linares, boldly reaching over the bull&#8217;s head to drive in a sword, the 30-year old matador was nicked by a horn in his groin and began bleeding badly from his femoral artery. The bloodstain spread quickly down his left leg.<br />
</span></p>
<div style="width: 434px;" class="wp-video"><!--[if lt IE 9]><script>document.createElement('video');</script><![endif]-->
<video class="wp-video-shortcode" id="video-21-1" width="434" height="358" preload="metadata" controls="controls"><source type="video/mp4" src="https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/Manolete-Muerte-1.m4v?_=1" /><a href="https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/Manolete-Muerte-1.m4v">https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/Manolete-Muerte-1.m4v</a></video></div>
<p><span style="font-size: 14pt; font-family: book antiqua,palatino,serif;">Manolete nevertheless stayed up, kept the bull working, and finally, with the animal close to death, limped away and was carried to the infirmary.</span></p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px;"><span style="font-size: 14pt; font-family: book antiqua,palatino,serif;"><a href="http://whenwordsmatter.typepad.com/before_their_time/2012/12/manuel-rodriguez-sanchez-better-known-as-manolete-stepped-wearily-to-the-microphone-in-an-ante-room-of-the-san-sebastian.html">As he lay</a> in the infirmary, Manolete lit a cigarette and asked in a weak voice, &#8220;Is the bull dead?&#8221; After being informed that the bull was, indeed, dead, Manolete said that he could not feel his legs.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: 14pt; font-family: book antiqua,palatino,serif;">These days he would have survived such an injury, but his ultimate reputation would have suffered: his decline and death would have been more drawn-out, and certainly less interesting. As it was, Manolete (whose real surname was Sanchez) died of his injury the next morning, and passed into everlasting glory.</span></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><span style="font-size: 14pt; font-family: book antiqua,palatino,serif;"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-453" src="https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/death-of-manolete.jpg" alt="" width="359" height="322" srcset="https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/death-of-manolete.jpg 359w, https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/death-of-manolete-300x269.jpg 300w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 359px) 100vw, 359px" /></span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: 14pt; font-family: book antiqua,palatino,serif;">Juan Belmonte (1892-1962), the <em>other</em> greatest-ever matador, may have envied Manolete&#8217;s end. Belmonte despite a long career and many serious gorings retired safely, and, it seemed, lived a life not unlike that of the rare fighting bull that is spared death and put out to stud. He bought a ranch and raised horses on it, and was rich. But he kept un-retiring and resuming bullfighting again, and being injured again, and retiring again, and then un-retiring, and so on as if nothing else in life measured up to the fundamental challenge of the bullring.</span></p>
<p><span style="font-size: 14pt; font-family: book antiqua,palatino,serif;">Eventually in 1962, when Belmonte was 70 and in failing health, his doctor advised him to stop riding horses and performing other manly exertions. According to the dressed-up legend, which in a cultural sense may be more revealing than the facts, the old matador went defiantly out to his ranch, indulged one last time in horse-riding, cigar-smoking, drinking, and sex with a pair of young women, and then&#8212;like his late pal Hemingway&#8212;shot himself, there being no bull, or matador, available to take his life for him.</span></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><span style="font-size: 14pt;"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-454" src="https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/funeral-of-barrio.jpg" alt="" width="550" height="350" srcset="https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/funeral-of-barrio.jpg 550w, https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/funeral-of-barrio-300x191.jpg 300w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 550px) 100vw, 550px" /></span></p>
<p><span style="font-family: book antiqua,palatino,serif; font-size: 14px;"><em><span style="color: #ff0000;"> </span></em></span></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		<enclosure url="https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/Manolete-Muerte-1.m4v" length="2145482" type="video/mp4" />

			</item>
		<item>
		<title>CULTURE AND ANTI-CULTURE</title>
		<link>https://james-the-obscure.github.io/culture-and-anticulture</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[JtO]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 22 Nov 2015 07:58:17 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[politics & culture]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://james-the-obscure.github.io/?page_id=382</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Why they hate our freedoms Originally published Nov 22, 2015 It is now routine for Western governments to describe Islamic militants’ attacks on Western civilians as “cowardly.” Unfortunately that description tells us less about the militants than it does about the Western establishment: in particular its tendency towards doublespeak, self-contradiction, and head-in-the-sand ignorance. The acts<p><a class="readmore" href="https://james-the-obscure.github.io/culture-and-anticulture"><span class="arrow-right icon"></span>Read More</a></p>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><em>Why they hate our freedoms</em></p>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-121" src="https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/freedom-600x439.jpg" alt="" width="600" height="439" srcset="https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/freedom-600x439.jpg 600w, https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/freedom-600x439-300x220.jpg 300w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 600px) 100vw, 600px" /></p>
<p><span id="more-382"></span></p>
<p><span style="color: #ff0000;"><em>Originally published Nov 22, 2015</em></span></p>
<p>It is now routine for Western governments to describe Islamic militants’ attacks on Western civilians as “cowardly.” Unfortunately that description tells us less about the militants than it does about the Western establishment: in particular its tendency towards doublespeak, self-contradiction, and head-in-the-sand ignorance. The acts of people who willingly die for their beliefs are anything but cowardly.</p>
<p>The West’s leaders&#8212;showing off a trait of cultural blindness that dates back through Magellan and Columbus&#8212;cannot understand their foes. They cannot accept that a reasonable person could ever loathe the West&#8217;s &#8220;advanced,&#8221; &#8220;progressive&#8221; culture with its compassion for the oppressed and expansive civil liberties. “Don’t those Muslims get that they’re on the wrong side of history?”</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-122" src="https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/oppressed.jpg" alt="" width="600" height="300" srcset="https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/oppressed.jpg 600w, https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/oppressed-300x150.jpg 300w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 600px) 100vw, 600px" /></p>
<p>No doubt the pagan Romans were as puzzled by the martyrdoms of abstemious early Christians. Why die for a faith that “oppresses” you so?</p>
<p>The truth to which progressivism blinds the West is that Islam, like any historically normal culture, gives structure and meaning to the lives of its adherents. It does that in part by regulating what they must and must not do. Muslims want that structure and meaning more than they want personal freedom. In that sense, they do not see their culture’s rules as oppressions.</p>
<p>Indeed many of them would say that the West is the true oppressor, not only because it invades their lands, kills their children, and co-opts their leaders, but also because it exerts a corrosive and pervasive cultural influence. Even in the so-called Islamic world one cannot escape the smug droning of CNN, the licentiousness of Western advertisers, any more than Orwell’s Winston Smith could escape the ubiquitous telescreens and slogans of Big Brother.</p>
<p>But arguably Western progressivism is not just a culture engaged in the usual competition against other cultures. To the extent that it is about expanding individual liberties at the expense of traditional communal structures and meanings, it might best be described as an <em>anti-culture&#8212;</em>a dissolver of other cultures, not a true culture that can sustain itself in the long run. Its strictures concerning insensitive, politically incorrect speech suggest an attempt to entrench itself with Thou Shalt Not laws&#8212;the sort of thing that ordinary cultures do. But ultimately it doesn&#8217;t have a full and coherent set of the kinds of rules that hold societies together. How could it be a bona fide, logically consistent culture and still be &#8220;multicultural&#8221;? Also, like other forms of materialism (e.g., Marxism), progressivism denies and opposes key aspects of human nature, and thus for that reason too can&#8217;t be expected to last. Human nature is flexible, but has a tendency to snap back violently when pushed too far.</p>
<p>The evidence of the Western anti-culture’s severe conflict with its human hosts is all around us. There are, most obviously, the adverse reactions from Islamic and other societies whose traditional structures it threatens. There are many blowups too from Islamic and other traditional-society immigrants living in the anti-cultural West. But every few weeks now some native, nominally modern person in a Western country (usually the &#8220;freest&#8221; country, the USA) also goes berserk and starts shooting people. These modern shooters often are unable to articulate why they did what they did&#8212;the anti-culture has taken away their vocabulary for that; they have no equivalent of <em>Allahu Akbar</em>!</p>
<p>Progressives exploit these atrocities to advance their agenda by blaming &#8220;guns.&#8221; But there were plenty of guns in pre-anticulture America (say, the 1950s) yet there weren&#8217;t all these mass shootings. It seems much more plausible to blame these incidents on progressivism itself, for its dissolution of traditional Western culture has left nearly everyone in the West adrift and alienated to some extent. As in the Muslim world, some will experience that loss of structure and meaning more acutely than others, and will react with rage and despair.</p>
<p>The mass shooters and their victims are the most visible casualties of this rage and despair. But many thousands of others act it out by harming only themselves, using opioids, alcohol, excessive food, even guns. The mortality <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2015/11/03/health/death-rates-rising-for-middle-aged-white-americans-study-finds.html?_r=0">statistics </a>are now showing this curious manifestation of societal collapse. Meanwhile the morbidity <a href="http://www.nndc.org/initiatives/task-groups/women-mood-disorders/">statistics </a>reveal a mood and anxiety disorder pandemic among the West’s women&#8212;those lucky women whom modernity has “liberated” from traditional patriarchal oppression.</p>
<p>How does militant Islam most hurt the people of the modern West? By distracting them from their greater foe, their foe within.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>MOTHERLAND</title>
		<link>https://james-the-obscure.github.io/motherland</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[JtO]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 16 Jun 2014 13:50:52 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[politics & culture]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[women]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://james-the-obscure.github.io/?p=476</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Why has America changed so dramatically over the past fifty years? Originally published June 16, 2014. “Suppose truth is a woman—what then?” asked Nietzsche with a chuckle. His aim, in that opening line of Beyond Good and Evil, was to tell us something about truth. But in so doing he touched on some old assumptions<p><a class="readmore" href="https://james-the-obscure.github.io/motherland"><span class="arrow-right icon"></span>Read More</a></p>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><em>Why has America changed so dramatically over the past fifty years?</em></p>
<p><span id="more-476"></span></p>
<p><span style="color: #ff6600;"><em>Originally published June 16, 2014.</em></span></p>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-155" src="https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/motherland.jpg" alt="" width="400" height="514" srcset="https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/motherland.jpg 400w, https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/motherland-233x300.jpg 233w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 400px) 100vw, 400px" /></p>
<p>“Suppose truth is a woman—what then?” asked Nietzsche with a chuckle.</p>
<p>His aim, in that opening line of <i>Beyond Good and Evil</i>, was to tell us something about truth. But in so doing he touched on some old assumptions about women: their inconstancy, their irrationality. The dogmas of the day, Nietzsche meant, were neither as immutable nor as reasoned as people assumed.</p>
<p>That skepticism was a lit fuse that led to the destruction of many traditions, including, ironically, men’s traditional underestimation of the fairer sex. Women soon got the vote in Western countries. In one world war and then another, they entered the workforce en masse, and increasingly stayed there during peacetime. Slowly but surely they took positions of influence, becoming doctors and lawyers, editors and producers, novelists and journalists, CEOs and politicians—even presidential candidates.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-156" src="https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/fred-graph-men.png" alt="" width="380" height="233" srcset="https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/fred-graph-men.png 380w, https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/fred-graph-men-300x184.png 300w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 380px) 100vw, 380px" /></p>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-157" src="https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/fred-graph-women.png" alt="" width="378" height="228" srcset="https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/fred-graph-women.png 378w, https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/fred-graph-women-300x181.png 300w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 378px) 100vw, 378px" /></p>
<p>By 1985, a century after <i>Beyond Good and Evil</i> was published, more women than men were graduating from college in the United States—and that gender gap would keep getting bigger.</p>
<p>This relatively quick and historically unprecedented surge of women into public life—and, in recent decades, into positions of strong cultural influence—must have had significant cultural consequences. Culture regulates the way that people think and act, especially in public life, and women tend to think and act differently than men, so it follows that their new influence should have shifted Western culture, feminizing it to some degree. Why has so little, if anything, been written and said about this shift?</p>
<p>One could hardly argue that there is no shift to explain. Here are just some of the major social changes that have occurred in the past fifty years in the US—changes that seem quite sudden in historical terms:</p>
<p style="padding-left: 40px;">Widespread dependence on government: More than 100 million Americans now receive means-tested federal welfare <a href="http://www.census.gov/hhes/www/cpstables/032012/perinc/pinc07_000.htm">benefits</a>, which don’t include Social Security or veterans benefits. About 47 million Americans receive <a href="http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-srv/special/politics/food-stamps/">food stamp</a>s. Close to <a href="http://moneymorning.com/2013/04/10/5-charts-show-alarming-trend-in-number-of-americans-collecting-social-security/">six percent</a> of the U.S. working age population now receives <a href="http://www.newsmax.com/Newsfront/social-security-disability-depleted/2013/12/17/id/542390/">payments</a> from the Social Security disability fund, <a href="http://articles.baltimoresun.com/2013-04-03/news/bs-ed-goldberg-disability-20130404_1_disability-insurance-disability-program-social-security-disability-benefits">compared</a> to less than one percent in 1960. In <a href="http://object.cato.org/sites/cato.org/files/pubs/pdf/the_work_versus_welfare_trade-off_2013_wp.pdf">most states</a>, welfare recipients can receive income well above the minimum wage equivalent. All in all, entitlement spending (including related debt-servicing payments) now absorbs about 70% of the federal budget, up from about 30% in 1960. However, the poverty rate is <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Poverty_in_the_United_States#mediaviewer/File:Number_in_Poverty_and_Poverty_Rate_1959_to_2011._United_States..PNG">about the same</a> as it was in 1965. Meanwhile the labor participation rate for men (see blue chart above) has been falling more or less steadily and is at all time lows.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-158" src="https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/welfare-nation.png" alt="" width="237" height="281" /></p>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-159" src="https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/disability-nation.png" alt="" width="369" height="307" srcset="https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/disability-nation.png 369w, https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/disability-nation-300x250.png 300w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 369px) 100vw, 369px" /></p>
<p style="padding-left: 40px;">Civil rights expansions and set-asides: including minority-preference affirmative action hiring and contracting policies, “hate crime” laws, the Supreme Court finding that the Constitution effectively bars state laws against gay marriage (and child rearing), the admission of women into combat units in the military, plus the extralegal social ostracism of any public figure uttering politically incorrect speech.</p>
<p style="padding-left: 40px;">Abandonment of traditional restrictions on immigration: In the early 1960s most immigrants to the US came from Europe or Canada and thus reflected the ethnicities of the existing American population. Since 1965, immigration laws and policies have become much more liberal, resulting in a radical change in the ethnic/cultural influx. Now the top five sources of immigrants are Mexico (dwarfing all others), China, India, the Philippines and Vietnam. The foreign born population in the US, as a percentage of the total population, is almost three times what it was in 1960. From 1960 to now Hispanics have increased their percentage of the population from 3.6% to 16.4%. The number of illegal, undocumented immigrants in America is also now huge, apparently between 10 and 20 million—equivalent to a medium-sized city’s worth of illegals <em>per state</em>. Not only the dynamic economy but also the growth of welfare programs in the US have created huge incentives for immigrants both legal and illegal. Some states even allow illegal immigrants to have <a href="http://www.reuters.com/article/2013/10/04/us-usa-california-immigration-idUSBRE99301I20131004">driver’s licenses</a> and <a href="http://www.nysenate.gov/report/what-benefits-can-illegal-aliens-receive">taxpayer-subsidized benefits</a>.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-161" src="https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/immigrant-tuition.png" alt="" width="322" height="307" srcset="https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/immigrant-tuition.png 322w, https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/immigrant-tuition-300x286.png 300w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 322px) 100vw, 322px" /></p>
<p style="padding-left: 40px;">A decline in the acceptability of military deaths and judicial executions: In all the years of US military activity in Kuwait, Iraq and Afghanistan—which is to say, almost continuously from 1991 to the present—there have been only about 5,400 US combat deaths. And that has been scarcely tolerable, even though about 50,000 Americans died in Vietnam, 300,000 in World War II, and 600,000+ in the Civil War. Meanwhile capital punishment is clearly <a href="http://www.economist.com/news/leaders/21601258-how-america-canand-willabolish-death-penalty-dismantling-machinery-death">on the way out</a>.</p>
<p style="padding-left: 40px;">A nation of victims: Declaring oneself a victim of something terrible—even something <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/A_Million_Little_Pieces">self-inflicted</a>—has become a major theme in American culture: in media stories, in modern psychiatry (PTSD and other trauma-related ailments), and even in contemporary <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Lovely_Bones">literature</a> where it has dominated for years. Meanwhile on campus, some consider any text a potential source of trauma and victimization, requiring “<a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2014/05/18/us/warning-the-literary-canon-could-make-students-squirm.html?">trigger warnings</a>” to protect the sensitive.</p>
<p style="padding-left: 40px;">A shift in foreign policy: The US has always been evangelical about its ideals, sometimes to the detriment of relations with countries that would otherwise be allies. That is true more than ever today, but the “American ideals” being pushed on countries like Saudi Arabia and Afghanistan and Kenya now include <a href="http://www.state.gov/s/gwi/">women’s rights</a> and even <a href="http://www.state.gov/r/pa/prs/ps/2014/05/226253.htm">LGBT rights.</a> Since 1997, the State Department has usually been headed by a woman (Albright, Rice, Clinton).</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-163" src="https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/obamacares.png" alt="" width="335" height="244" srcset="https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/obamacares.png 335w, https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/obamacares-300x219.png 300w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 335px) 100vw, 335px" /></p>
<p style="padding-left: 40px;">Back to nature: From Rachel Carson to Global Warming and the <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2014/01/05/us/on-hawaii-a-lonely-quest-for-facts-about-gmos.html">anti-GMO movement</a>, Americans have become energized about environmental issues as never before. The increase in environmental consciousness has been accompanied by an increasing preference for more “natural” foods and medicines. At the same, more and more Americans have been joining New Ageish, nature-oriented religions, such as <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wicca">Wicca</a>, which is often described as the <a href="http://www.digitaljournal.com/article/267495">fastest-growing religion</a> in the country. This rise in freewheeling nature-oriented religions has been accompanied by declines in traditional, hierarchical Christian denominations such as <a href="http://www.pewforum.org/2013/03/13/strong-catholic-identity-at-a-four-decade-low-in-us/">Roman Catholicism</a>, <a href="http://www.christianpost.com/news/episcopal-church-continues-downward-trend-according-to-report-107906/">Episcopalianism</a> and <a href="http://juicyecumenism.com/2013/08/02/lutheran-exceptionalism-from-hope-to-decline/">Lutheranism</a>.</p>
<p style="padding-left: 40px;">New modes of public argument: Debate over public policy these days seems to have less and less to do with sober calculations of long term consequences, and more and more to do with dramatic anecdotes that make immediate appeal to our empathy: the poor immigrant yearning for a new start in the land of freedom; the inmate facing inhumane execution, who just might be innocent; the gay couple who want only to be treated the same as their straight-couple friends; the rape victims of Rwanda or the Congo, or the <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2013/10/11/us/2-ex-navy-football-players-face-court-martial-in-rape-case.html">US Naval Academy</a>. There is also now a heavy emphasis on protests and marches, <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2013/06/05/us/politics/michelle-obama-confronts-heckler-at-fund-raiser.html?">heckling</a>, <a href="http://archive.citizen-times.com/article/20110822/NEWS/308210061/Thousands-flock-Asheville-rally-see-women-bare-their-breasts">breast-baring</a>, blood- and egg-throwing, ad hominem attacks, silencings of would-be speakers, and other non-rational or even anti-rational tactics.</p>
<p><strong>Empathy and compassion</strong></p>
<p>Many of these changes are consistent with a cultural shift in favor of empathetic compassion. America over the past few decades has somehow acquired more and more sensitivity to the needs and claims of traditionally disadvantaged minority groups, would-be immigrants and illegals, those who claim to have experienced trauma or injury—basically anyone with a sob story.</p>
<p>This is the precisely the change that we should most expect as women gain greater influence over policy and the wider culture. A greater tendency towards empathy and compassion are among the most distinctive features of the female mindset. Even Aristotle, 2,400 years ago, noted that woman was “more compassionate” and “more easily moved to tears.”</p>
<p>This type of sensitivity presumably is a deep trait that evolved because it is adaptive for child-rearing. Certainly it is common for women to display that trait when raising a child, for example in shielding the child from challenges or risks to which a more coldly rational father is willing to expose him. The Cambridge University psychologist Simon Baron-Cohen, who researches gender differences, has long <a href="http://www.amazon.com/The-Essential-Difference-Female-Brains/dp/046500556X/">argued</a> that “[t]he female brain is predominantly hard-wired for empathy. The male brain is predominantly hard-wired for understanding and building systems.”</p>
<p>Note that the empathy that moves one to compassion tends to have a certain emotional narrowness and immediacy: “I feel your pain.” It’s not a deliberate, logical weighing of long-term consequences, and it typically is meant to ameliorate the plight of an individual or narrowly defined group, with little thought for wider implications.</p>
<p>America’s immigration policy, to take one example, was once largely based on considerations of long-term consequences, including the adverse social consequences of bringing in millions of people from Third World societies. That policy, now deemed racist, has been replaced by a policy that is to a great extent about satisfying the immediate needs and aspirations of individual immigrants. Ditto for welfare, where the policy tends to focus more on the immediate claims of claimants and less on the adverse society-wide consequences (reducing motivation to work, eroding families, busting budgets). Ditto again for admitting women to combat roles in the military—which is about fulfilling the aspirations of a small number of individuals rather than optimizing the services’ overall warfighting capability.</p>
<p>I would be surprised if the new influence of women on American culture were the <i>only</i> factor in this shift towards more empathy-based attitudes and policies. Television, for example, which spread widely into US homes beginning in the 1960s, has tended to bias debates in favor of the side that can muster more compelling visual images—and videos of people expressing strong emotions tend to be more compelling than, say, bar charts depicting long term consequences. But I wonder if TV’s influence could have been as great, had policymakers and persuaders not become so receptive to that influence—because they were increasingly female.</p>
<p><b>Environmentalism and witchery</b></p>
<p>Pregnancy brings out some remarkable instinctive behaviors that give us further hints about the “hardwired” traits of women. I am referring to the smell and taste aversions that appear mainly in the first trimester, and the “<a href="http://www.mayoclinic.org/healthy-living/labor-and-delivery/in-depth/signs-of-labor/art-20046184?pg=2">nesting instinct</a>” that occurs in the second or third. None of these behaviors is deliberate and rational—that is what can make them so disturbing to the pregnant woman and her loved ones—but they appear to have evolved to help keep the baby safe from toxins, germs and other harmful environmental influences.</p>
<p>I suggest—that is all I can do at this point; there is little published research in this area—that these deeply rooted traits, which appear to be influenced by levels of estrogen and related hormones, would also manifest to some extent outside pregnancy. They would show up, for example, in a tendency to be more concerned (than men are) about putative environmental threats.</p>
<p>Again, there is no definitive research on this question. But there is some evidence that women (compared to men) tend to put <a href="http://articles.latimes.com/2012/jun/13/opinion/la-oe-polakovic-gender-and-the-environment-20120613">more emphasis on pro-environmental issues</a>, are less likely to <a href="http://msutoday.msu.edu/news/2010/study-women-more-likely-than-men-to-accept-global-warming/">be global warming skeptics</a>, and are more likely to choose<a href="http://www.environmentalleader.com/2011/04/14/women-more-likely-to-choose-eco-packaging/"> eco-packaging</a>. Women also are heavily represented in pro-environment groups such as Greenpeace and the <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2014/01/05/us/on-hawaii-a-lonely-quest-for-facts-about-gmos.html?_r=0">anti-GMO</a> movement.</p>
<p>Related to this “green” tendency may be women’s seemingly greater aversion (on average, compared to men) towards modern, industrially produced foods and medicines, and the recent, swift rise in popularity of “natural” alternatives—purchased <a href="http://community.babycenter.com/post/a31051537/more_women_buy_organic_foods_than_men">mostly</a> by <a href="http://nccam.nih.gov/news/camstats/2007/camsurvey_fs1.htm">women</a>.</p>
<p>The trend towards natural remedies appears to be related to New Age and witchcraft religions with their pre-scientific, eye-of-newt style systems of “healing.” These alternative religions obviously strike other chords in some women, and while I’m no expert on the matter, presumably one attraction is that the new religions give women more interesting and flexible roles than they would have had in traditional, patriarchal Christianity (e.g., lusty witch vs. celibate nun).</p>
<p>The same suspicions of modern, technologically produced food and medicine appear to have encouraged the ongoing anti-vaccine <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2014/04/22/opinion/bruni-autism-and-the-agitator.html">movement</a>, and the <a href="http://www.mayoclinic.org/healthy-living/nutrition-and-healthy-eating/expert-answers/detox-diets/faq-20058040">spurious</a> “<a href="http://www.goodhousekeeping.com/health/diet-plans/gywneth-paltrow-diet-detox">detox</a>” intestinal cleansing fad, both of which have been largely female social phenomena, heavily promoted by female celebrities such as Jenny McCarthy and Gwyneth Paltrow.</p>
<p><strong>Unreason, contagion, victimization</strong></p>
<p>In the list of big social changes above, I mentioned an apparent trend towards the use of non-rational or even anti-rational tactics in public arguments: for example, the demonization and silencing of opponents as alternatives to reasoned debate, and the rejection of due process in many cases where women are the accusers and men the accused. Is this too part of our cultural feminization? Historically men have believed that women are less rational, less reason-guided, in contexts where they are trying to persuade. Obviously this notion is offensive to modern women and to a great extent it does stem from the casual misogyny of the past. Then again, every modern study I’ve seen that touches on this particular question—check out <a href="https://eric.ed.gov/?id=EJ914830">this one</a> from 2003—suggests that women are indeed markedly less supportive of free speech rights, and more emotionally sensitive to speech with which they disagree.</p>
<p><a href="https://www.thetimes.co.uk/article/women-students-are-more-likely-to-support-censorship-wvvsr6wfb"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-295" src="https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/women-and-censorship.jpg" alt="" width="300" height="308" srcset="https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/women-and-censorship.jpg 300w, https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/women-and-censorship-292x300.jpg 292w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /></a></p>
<p>From an anthropological perspective, it makes perfect sense that women and men in the course of human evolution would have acquired (again: on average—think of two overlapping Bell curves) cognitive and other psychological differences, stemming from differences in their traditional roles, e.g., women as nurturers vs. men as hunters, warriors and leaders. In particular, women’s apparently greater weighting of emotion and empathy implies a correspondingly <em>reduced</em> weighting of more abstract and emotionally neutral mental operations. It’s easy to imagine that throughout human history women in effect have been engaged in a “mental arms-race” with men, evolving their own distinctively female set of cognitive and persuasive weaponry. That we still tend to hold up the chief “male” weapon, reason, as the highest mental faculty, may be <a href="https://www.cambridge.org/core/journals/behavioral-and-brain-sciences/article/why-do-humans-reason-arguments-for-an-argumentative-theory/53E3F3180014E80E8BE9FB7A2DD44049">due</a> in large part merely to men’s historical hegemony in intellectual matters—so that, as that hegemony slips, the special status of reason can be expected to <a href="https://www.cambridge.org/core/journals/behavioral-and-brain-sciences/article/why-do-humans-reason-arguments-for-an-argumentative-theory/53E3F3180014E80E8BE9FB7A2DD44049">slip too</a>.</p>
<p>The late 20th and early 21st centuries also have been marked by tremendous social contagions, from epidemics of arguably fake diseases (e.g., multiple personality disorder) to routine media-driven outbreaks of “outrage,” particularly of the politically correct variety—commonly compared to the witch-hunts of old. Is the cultural ascendancy of women to blame for this trend too?</p>
<p>Perhaps it is. If empathy is the ability to feel what others are feeling, then a more empathetic person is mentally more connected—more <em>acutely</em> and <em>immediately</em> connected—to others and in general to her social surroundings. Though much of it is <a href="http://www.foxnews.com/health/2012/02/03/mass-hysteria-rare-but-usually-seen-in-girls/">anecdotal</a> (not nearly enough experimental work has been done in this area) there is some evidence that women do tend to have greater “connectedness” in this sense. For example: Women and girls, versus men and boys, are more likely (about twice as likely) to be diagnosed with PTSD after <a href="http://link.springer.com/article/10.1186%2F2042-6410-3-29">trauma</a>. They tend to be more interested in social <a href="http://www.pewinternet.org/Media-Mentions/2009/Women-Outnumber-Men-on-Social-Networking-Sites.aspx">networking</a>. They are more hypnotizable and suggestible (and become moreso when <a href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/19678556">pregnant</a>). They are <a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/2096969">more likely</a> to confabulate false memories and participate in mass <a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/3067396">psychosomatic incidents</a> of the kind that, for example, spuriously sicken anxious <a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/24138153">schoolchildren</a> every year.</p>
<p>Women moreover have been the initiators and principal transmitters of the most notorious hysterical contagions in history. These include the original witch-hunts—the convent <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Louis_Gaufridi">demon-possessions</a> of early 17<sup>th</sup> century France, for example, and the later, much more lethal bewitchment-accusation craze in Puritan New England—as well as the hysterical neurosis syndromes that so captivated Charcot and Freud, and the related recovered-memory epidemics of recent decades. (Although historically in the West these have seemed to be isolated outbreaks, there is a substantial anthropological <a href="http://www.jstor.org/discover/10.2307/3316878?uid=2129&amp;uid=2&amp;uid=70&amp;uid=4&amp;sid=21103863373051">literature</a> suggesting that women in premodern, patriarchal societies routinely—and competitively and contagiously—use “spirit possession” and similar tactics for mundane ends.)</p>
<p>Note that these female-driven contagions, across wide stretches of history and culture and including our modern outbreaks, have all in some way been about claiming the status of victim, for oneself or for someone else. I don’t know that “playing the victim” is a latent reflex in the female psyche, but it would make sense in terms of evolutionary psychology if the physically weaker sex, over tens of millenia of social evolution, had developed a reliance on such passive strategies. If it did, then women’s new cultural ascendancy would virtually guarantee that victimization stories become as prominent in media and influential on policymaking as they are.</p>
<p>Does all this strike you as unacceptably inflammatory and insulting speculation? If so, you’re in good company. Already many areas of scientific research (e.g., cognitive differences between men and women, or among ethnic groups) are <a href="https://www.dana.org/Cerebrum/2014/Equal_%E2%89%A0_The_Same__Sex_Differences_in_the_Human_Brain/">effectively off limits</a>, and the idea of <a href="http://blogs.scientificamerican.com/cross-check/2013/05/16/should-research-on-race-and-iq-be-banned/">overtly banning</a> certain types of inquiry is now almost mainstream. Interestingly, this trend has been pioneered by some of the institutions that should best symbolize the free-inquiry ideal.</p>
<p>Consider what happened at Harvard in 2005—a classic case of clashing mindsets. The Harvard President at the time, Lawrence Summers (later of the Obama Administration), was under pressure to increase female enrollment in technical degree programs. One day Summers gave a talk that touched on this delicate subject. He suggested, based on published data, that men as compared to women don’t necessarily have more aptitude on average for technical subjects—but they do have <i>a wider distribution</i> of aptitude, i.e., longer tails on their Bell curves, so that they are marginally more likely to be geniuses <i>or dullards</i>. The slight surfeit of male high-achievers, he went on, might help explain why men still dominate the very limited number of “tenured positions in science and engineering at top universities and research institutions.”</p>
<p>As tame and defensible as such a suggestion might seem, Summers’s willingness to contemplate any sort of gender-based difference in aptitude was enough to trigger outrage, and a long and painful inquisition. The psychologist <a href="http://pinker.wjh.harvard.edu/articles/media/2005_01_19_crimson.html">Steven Pinker</a> and a few others strongly backed Summers, and Summers himself made several abject public <a href="http://www.bloomberg.com/apps/news?pid=newsarchive&amp;sid=abdPmeSJADQ8">apologies</a> (“…I was wrong to have spoken in a way that has resulted in an unintended signal of discouragement to talented girls and women…”) but the Harvard faculty soon passed a motion of “lack of confidence” in his leadership. Summers resigned the following year.</p>
<p>In this episode the loudest cries of condemnation came from female academics, and the weird part of all this is how unselfconsciously some of them displayed a clichéd femininity—as if, in our brave, new, pink-tinted world, they had no further need to conceal their cognitive differentness, notwithstanding the issue at hand! Amid the uproar, for example, one woman professor dramatically <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/01/18/national/18harvard.html">told </a>a <i>New York Times</i> reporter: “When he started talking about innate differences in aptitude between men and women, <i>I just couldn’t breathe because this kind of bias makes me physically ill.</i>” [italics mine]</p>
<p><b>Here’s to the new boss</b></p>
<p>What I’ve written above will seem biased against women. But I could have constructed an argument about the negative features of Western societies before the recent ascendancy of women: much more violence and acceptance of violence, for example, and more susceptibility to complex, inhumane ideologies—given the dominance of a testosterone-driven, lower-empathy, compulsively system-building (i.e., male) brain.</p>
<p>Anyway this essay isn’t really about the rightness or wrongness of the social changes that have occurred in America. It is about the likely origins of those changes. Admittedly, though, if those changes arose mostly from a simple demographic shift, then that would tend to undermine the claim that they represent an inevitable Progress. Moreover, one might wonder whether, in the long run, a mindset that evolved not for the “understanding and building of systems” (Baron-Cohen’s words) but for tasks such as child-rearing can succeed in the management of complex modern societies and states. Conceivably it <em>will</em> succeed; conceivably it will turn out to be <em>better</em> suited (than the traditional male mindset) for a modern, relatively peaceful world. But just as conceivably, or maybe a lot more conceivably, empathy-driven feelgood policies in the long run will lead, even in countries that had been rich and stable, to fiscal and social collapses—creating opportunities that less feminized cultures will want to <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Submission-Novel-Michel-Houellebecq/dp/1250097347/">exploit</a>.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-307" src="https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/osamabinladen.jpg" alt="" width="343" height="180" srcset="https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/osamabinladen.jpg 343w, https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/osamabinladen-300x157.jpg 300w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 343px) 100vw, 343px" /></p>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-308" src="https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/xijinping.jpg" alt="" width="246" height="164" /></p>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-162" src="https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/patriarchal.png" alt="" width="319" height="241" srcset="https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/patriarchal.png 319w, https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/patriarchal-300x227.png 300w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 319px) 100vw, 319px" /></p>
<p>Even if such a cataclysm never comes, the fact is that something fundamental has changed in the inner workings of the modern world. The structures of societies are already adjusting and realigning in response. But, curiously, the nature of the change is such that no one seems to want to talk about it or even acknowledge it.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><em> </em></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>THE DEMISE OF GUYTHINK</title>
		<link>https://james-the-obscure.github.io/the-demise-of-guythink</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[JtO]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 27 Dec 2011 07:49:14 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[politics & culture]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://james-the-obscure.github.io/?page_id=375</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Empathy, political correctness and the feminization of Western culture &#8212; and why we should worry &#160; Originally published 27 December 2011 &#160; A few weeks ago Jeremy Clarkson, a well-known British TV personality, was asked on a BBC talk show what he thought of an ongoing strike by UK public-sector workers. He replied: I’d have<p><a class="readmore" href="https://james-the-obscure.github.io/the-demise-of-guythink"><span class="arrow-right icon"></span>Read More</a></p>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><em>Empathy, political correctness and the feminization of Western culture &#8212; and why we should worry<br />
</em></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-139" src="https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/Potbellied-Clarkson-endangered-species.jpg" alt="" width="333" height="500" srcset="https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/Potbellied-Clarkson-endangered-species.jpg 333w, https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/Potbellied-Clarkson-endangered-species-200x300.jpg 200w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 333px) 100vw, 333px" /></p>
<p><span id="more-375"></span></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><span style="color: #ff6600;"><em>Originally published 27 December 2011</em></span></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>A few weeks ago Jeremy Clarkson, a well-known British TV personality, was asked on a BBC talk show what he thought of an ongoing strike by UK public-sector workers. He <a href="http://www.telegraph.co.uk/culture/tvandradio/bbc/8927036/Jeremy-Clarkson-execute-public-sector-workers-says-BBC-Top-Gear-host.html">replied</a>:</p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px;">I’d have them all shot. I’d take them outside and execute them in front of their families. How dare they go on strike when they’ve got these gilt-edged pensions that are going to be guaranteed, while the rest of us have to work for a living …</p>
<p>Now, it was the sort of exaggerated remark that wouldn’t have seemed out of place at a pub or a even at a cocktail party. People would have understood it as an example of rhetorical excess&#8212;particularly coming from Clarkson, who indulges in it fairly <a href="http://www.mirror.co.uk/news/top-stories/2011/12/01/jeremy-clarkson-strike-gaffe-the-top-gear-presenter-s-top-10-most-outspoken-moments-115875-23602085/">often</a>. Somehow, though, Clarkson-style rhetorical excess is considered threatening to the fragile minds of UK TV viewers, and so this episode triggered the familiar expressions of outrage, demands for his firing, etc.&#8212;from the usual offense-takers and outrageists, who by now comprise a sort of immune response against any flareup of un-PC talk in the media. (Both the BBC and Clarkson had to apologize.)</p>
<p>The PC/un-PC battle of the past two decades is winding down, in favor of the former; and besides, it’s old news. But there is an aspect to this struggle that seems worth highlighting, because to my knowledge no one has picked up on it.</p>
<p>To begin with, the phrase “take them outside and execute them in front of their families”&#8212;like the classic “bomb them back to the Stone Age” (attributed to USAF General Curtis LeMay) – represents a distinct strain of un-PC talk. It offends not because it takes an archaic view of some minority group, but because it takes an archaic view of violence and punishment.</p>
<p>Note, however, that “take them outside and execute them in front of their families” is not just an impulsive, brutish expression of anger. It contains a far-sighted strategy: not simply to punish miscreants but also to make a public example of them, so that others will be discouraged from behaving in the same way. In this sense, it is rational and utilitarian, and aims to minimize net punitive force and pain in the long term.</p>
<p>What it lacks, of course, is empathy for those who would suffer in the near-term from such a course of action. The psychologist Simon Baron-Cohen has been arguing, for some years now and with evidence from his and other studies, <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Essential-Difference-Female-Brains-Autism/">that</a> too little empathy is a sign of too much “maleness,” cognitively speaking:</p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px;">The female brain is predominantly hard-wired for empathy. The male brain is predominantly hard-wired for understanding and building systems.</p>
<p>Baron-Cohen proposes that the autistic or Asperger’s brain is for the most part a hyper-male brain, with too much systematizing ability&#8212;though a high amount would be good for many modern high-tech jobs&#8212;and too little empathy. Even on ordinary personality tests, answering a utilitarian “yes” to a question such as “if you could save ten people by killing one in cold blood, would you do it?” is nowadays thought to indicate a disturbing lack of empathy. Answering “yes” to too many such questions can lead to a diagnosis of sociopathy, and these sociopathy tests are even used to <a href="http://www.npr.org/2011/05/26/136619689/can-a-test-really-tell-whos-a-psychopath">determine</a> whether or not criminals should be paroled.</p>
<p>Clearly, though, our views about what constitutes an acceptable level of empathy have changed greatly in recent centuries&#8212;even in recent decades. For example, we and other Western countries used to make quite free use of capital punishment, and in public spaces. Now capital punishment occurs only behind prison walls, and is much less common. Our wars too are far less bloody now, and though we care primarily about our own casualties, we also are far more sensitive to the harm caused to non-combatants than we used to be (think of LeMay’s deliberate fire-bombing of Tokyo civilians in 1944-45&#8212;and of course, Hiroshima and Nagasaki).</p>
<p>Un-PC speech&#8212;or speech that would now get that label&#8212;used to be common as well. We cringe at some of the things that men said (or did) to women or minorities in old Hollywood movies, or that politicians of even a few generations ago uttered in speeches while no one minded.</p>
<p>There has also been a feminization and de-martialization of public grieving following atrocities, e.g., the terrorist kind: the angry, vengeful speeches of yesteryear have been replaced by flowers, candles and &#8220;forgiveness.&#8221;</p>
<p>It has been clear for a while now that these empathy-related changes in public discourse are due in large part to the recent, unprecedented entry of women into public life in Western countries. Women have not only the right to vote but also a presence in key areas of society&#8212;science, law, business, politics&#8212;as never before, and it would be hard to believe that their influence has not changed the culture, bending it towards their own cognitive style. People now use the jokey phrase “endangered white male” to refer to guys like Jeremy Clarkson, but what may be truly endangered here is the male cognitive style.</p>
<p>That may not be a good thing, if the male cognitive style evolved to be optimal for managing societies, while the female cognitive style is tuned for the rearing of children. There is a tendency in our culture now to treat empathy as a trait to be simply maximized. But “understanding and building systems,” as Baron-Cohen puts it, is useful, too&#8212;and perhaps most if not all of our culture’s greatest failings now come not from a lack of empathy but from a failure to see how complex systems fit together, and how they may fly apart.</p>
<p>What also worries me is that too much empathy, or other related aspects of the female cognitive style, may be&#8212;we don’t know; probably no scientist would go near this question&#8212;less compatible with the reasoned debate and calm analytical thinking that are presumably needed in a healthy democracy, or in any mature society. Several years ago, then-Harvard President Lawrence Summers (who was later a White House adviser) referred rather delicately to the <em>possibility </em>that male/female cognitive differences <em>partly </em>explain the relative lack of female professors in math and science; he was, in effect, shouted down and forced from his post. A vocal minority on the faculty (representing the female cognitive style one might say) deemed Summers&#8217;s suggestion too offensive, the man himself too insensitive. Apparently it did not occur to them that they were helping to illustrate his point. (One female professor earnestly <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2005/01/18/national/18harvard.html">told </a>a reporter: &#8220;When he started talking about innate differences in aptitude between men and women, I just couldn&#8217;t breathe because this kind of bias makes me physically ill.&#8221;)</p>
<p>An inflexible, authoritarian, shout-them-down tendency is often said to be a feature of PC-think generally. PC-driven marches and protests (on campuses for example ) typically are meant not to broaden a discourse but, rather, to repel or suppress an unwanted speaker&#8212;much as a mother, without any pretense of democracy or debate, would try to protect her children from an unwanted influence or their own innate waywardness. (&#8220;Because I said so!&#8221;)</p>
<p>Americans on the whole appear to be getting more like this: more extreme and emotion-driven in their politics and public discourse, and less open to opposing views. Could the rising influence of the &#8220;fairer,&#8221; more nurturing, less violent sex be a major reason?</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>WHY A POLTERGEIST WON’T HURT YOU</title>
		<link>https://james-the-obscure.github.io/why-a-poltergeist-wont-hurt-you</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[JtO]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 29 Jul 2011 01:01:17 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[woo woo]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://james-the-obscure.github.io/?page_id=386</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[a ‘network hypothesis’ for psi phenomena Originally published 28 July 2011 &#160; One of the most striking and puzzling features of well-documented poltergeist cases concerns the trajectories of apparent polt-moved objects. Typically these objects travel not as if thrown but as if carried by someone, albeit at inhumanly high speed. Typically they are aimed at<p><a class="readmore" href="https://james-the-obscure.github.io/why-a-poltergeist-wont-hurt-you"><span class="arrow-right icon"></span>Read More</a></p>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><em>a ‘network hypothesis’ for psi phenomena</em></p>
<p><span id="more-386"></span></p>
<p><span style="color: #ff6600;"><em>Originally published 28 July 2011</em></span></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>One of the most striking and puzzling features of well-documented poltergeist cases concerns the trajectories of apparent polt-moved objects. Typically these objects travel not as if thrown but as if <em>carried </em>by someone, albeit at inhumanly high speed. Typically they are aimed at people too, and yet they almost never end up doing significant physical harm.</p>
<p>For those who are not well acquainted with the lore, I provide some snippets from Herbert Thurston’s <em>Ghosts and Poltergeists</em> (first <a href="http://www.jstor.org/pss/30095281">published</a> in a journal in the 1920s, and in <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Ghosts-Poltergeists-Kessinger-Publishings-Reprints/dp/1425452957/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1311851833&amp;sr=8-1">book</a> form in 1953):</p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px;">[quoting Sir William Barrett, FRS, of the Society for Psychical Research:] The movement of objects is usually quite unlike that due to gravitation or other attraction. They slide about, rise in the air, move in eccentric paths, sometimes in a leisurely manner, often turn around in their career, and usually descend quietly <em>without hurting the observers</em>. [p. 2, my italics]</p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px;">Dr. Schuppart [a respected professor of theology, in the late 1800s] … declares that every pane in his study window was repeatedly smashed, stones from six to ten pounds in weight were aimed at him but <em>seemed designedly to miss him by a hair’s breadth, his wife was struck with blows which resounded all through the house but which nevertheless inflicted relatively little pain</em>. [ p. 17, my italics]</p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px;">[quoting from a report of a case in Bristol in 1761-62:] In spite of the vexations to which the children were subjected, a certain consideration, as has often been noticed in other poltergeist manifestations, was shown by the spook <em>to prevent their sustaining serious injury to health</em>. [p 25, my italics]</p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px;">[from a case reported by an Austrian physics teacher in 1818:] A good deal of damage resulted, but it was noticed with some surprise that <em>no one present was seriously hurt, even when struck by a big “stone” which seemed to be deliberately aimed and to be traveling with great velocity</em>. Many of the moving objects upon contact with a living person or with a resisting surface fell dead <em>as if a hand had arrested them in their flight</em>. [ p 30, my italics]</p>
<p>What explains this?</p>
<p>The basic model that has come down from Thurston, SPR guys like Barrett, and more recently <a href="http://archived.parapsych.org/members/w_g_roll.html">William Roll</a>, is that a poltergeist manifestation is initiated and mediated by a person – sometimes called a ‘medium’ – in the vicinity. Unconsciously the medium ‘throws’ PK and ESP phenomena, as a ventriloquist ‘throws’ his voice; and typically the medium is a young child, an adolescent, a youngish servant, or some other youthful, stressed person who [see Note 1] uses the polt displays to ‘act out’ dramatically and deniably. Roll has suggested that in some cases the polt display could be due to an epileptic or Tourette’s-like seizure condition that hyperactivates the PK-mediating part of the brain; but to me polt displays seem more purposeful and controlled than a seizure phenomenon could be, and of course the seizure theory doesn’t explain polts&#8217; weird non-lethality.</p>
<p>Is this non-lethality due simply to the absence of malice in the youthful medium? I find that hard to believe. Even if they have no intention to cause harm, young people routinely do foolish, impulsive things that bring about serious injuries (or death) to other people. How do they manage to avoid that during polt displays, especially when the trajectories and impacts of polt-moved objects often seem designed to <em>look and sound</em> lethal?</p>
<p><strong>The network hypothesis</strong></p>
<p>I haven’t read all the polt lore and the theories, and so I apologize if someone else has come up with this idea before. Anyhow, it occurs to me that the polt’s refusal to cause serious harm to witnesses in these cases may be &#8212; in addition to the fact that its intention is only to frighten &#8212; an act of <em>self-preservation</em>. That would be the case not only when the chief medium is spared but also when additional witnesses are spared. In other words, although there may be a chief medium of the polt displays, further witnesses are recruited into the phenomenon too – invisibly and unconsciously in a psycho-psi realm that science has hardly touched – and they participate to some extent, even if they usually cannot initiate or fully control the displays.</p>
<p>According to this idea, the heavy rock aimed by a polt at a witness&#8217;s head and moved at high speed stops a millimeter from his scalp and falls to the floor harmlessly, in part because the witness (maybe with the &#8216;help&#8217; of other friendly witnesses) unconsciously stopped it.</p>
<p>I can only speculate wildly at this point about the mechanics of such an interaction among unaware brains. Perhaps the active psi-mediating brain areas would be like nodes making up their own local network, and the polt would be an emergent property of this network. [See note 2]</p>
<p>A more unsettling possibility is that the participants in some cases would also be joining a <em>non-local</em> network, an ancient Spooknet, with little or no firewall so to speak. But the Spooknet, demon-polt hypothesis seems to me to resemble <em>Exorcist</em>-style or Lovecraftian fiction more than real polt cases, and of course it fails to explain the benign-trajectory conundrum (unless there is some kind of don’t-kill-humans law that governs the denizens of Spooknet!).</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-389" src="https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/networking.jpg" alt="" width="600" height="379" srcset="https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/networking.jpg 600w, https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/networking-300x190.jpg 300w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 600px) 100vw, 600px" /></p>
<p>In any case, a general network hypothesis could help explain a lot of other curious paranormal phenomena, such as the apparent ability of some polts (or ‘possessing spirits’) to speak or write with an amazing range of knowledge, including secrets about members of their audience, but with some curious limitations which suggest that these communicative entities do not have perfect ESP for declarative knowledge or for skills such as languages, music, etc. According to this network hypothesis, these entities are acting mainly via telepathy in the local network that is made up of their audience, i.e., using the limited knowledge and skills in the available brains. The larger the audience, the greater the apparent range of their knowledge and skills.</p>
<p>This theory could also account for the seemingly greater likelihood of weird stuff happening when more than one of the right kind of person is brought together – in UFO-related close-encounter waves, <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Dark-White-Aliens-Abductions-Obsession/dp/0241134153/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1311860674&amp;sr=8-1">abductee</a>/<a href="http://www.amazon.com/Mothman-Prophecies-John-Keel/dp/0765341972/ref=sr_1_3?ie=UTF8&amp;qid=1311941465&amp;sr=8-3">contactee </a>scenarios, hypnotist-hypnotee relationships, <a href="http://realityshifters.com/pages/articles/spoonbendingparty.html">spoonbending parties</a>, spirit-possession cults, religious contexts (e.g., the Pentecost), Ouija board sessions, seances, and the reported ‘<a href="http://www.biomindsuperpowers.com/Pages/RVVsTelepathicOverlay.html">telepathic overlay</a>’ phenomenon in remote viewing.</p>
<p>It also might explain this rather spooky sentence in the Bible, attributed to Jesus Christ:</p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px;">For where two or three are gathered together in my name, there am I in the midst of them. [Matthew 18: 20]</p>
<p>Of course, the idea that telepathy can occur spontaneously among two or more people isn’t new at all. And even Thurston nearly a century ago seems to have allowed in at least one case – without further explanation, unfortunately – the possibility that two siblings were involved in generating a polt.</p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px;">The mediumistic power seemed to center in the boy Harry aged 12, but also in his sister Anna, who was four years older. [p 12]</p>
<p>In general, though, I think that we in the modern West, with our individualist, reductionist culture, prefer to break behavioral phenomena down to the single-brain level – so that even if we acknowledge that polt and other paranormal displays can be group phenomena, we don’t give this possibility nearly enough emphasis or really think through its implications.</p>
<p>Again, this is a very speculative hypothesis, but it could be used to guide experiments and observations in polt and other paranormal cases.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<hr size="1" />
<p>Note 1. We normally think of a person in terms of his or her aggregate mental &#8216;agency&#8217;, i.e., all the conscious and non-conscious drives and/or selves. However, in the case of poltergeists&#8212;and presumably for spirit possession, fugues, hypnotic and MPD-type phenomena, &#8216;voices&#8217; in schizophrenia and so forth&#8212;we seem to be dealing mainly (or exclusively) with the agencies that are not accessible to ordinary awareness, the &#8216;inner demons&#8217; as it were. Thus, when I refer to a person who is putatively involved in mediating poltergeist phenomena, I don&#8217;t mean that this person is aware of his or her involvement.</p>
<p>Note 2. For some reason this reminds me of so-called <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Quasiparticle">quasiparticles</a> from condensed-matter physics, which are emergent properties of macro material (e.g., ultracold superconducting metal), exist only virtually, and yet respond to their environment <em>as if</em> they are real.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><span style="color: #ff0000;"><em> </em></span></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>CELEBRITIES: A MODEST PROPOSAL</title>
		<link>https://james-the-obscure.github.io/celebrities-a-modest-proposal-2</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[JtO]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 01 Jun 2011 06:35:54 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[politics & culture]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://james-the-obscure.github.io/?page_id=369</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[A Modest Proposal for curbing the cult of Celebrity, and for making better social use of existing Celebrities. &#160; Originally published June 1, 2011 &#160; (With apologies to Jonathan Swift.) &#160; It is a melancholy object to those, who happen to possess televisions or iPads or other electronic media platforms, when they see their screens<p><a class="readmore" href="https://james-the-obscure.github.io/celebrities-a-modest-proposal-2"><span class="arrow-right icon"></span>Read More</a></p>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><em>A Modest Proposal for curbing the cult of Celebrity, and for making better social use of existing Celebrities.</em></p>
<p><span id="more-369"></span></p>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-247" src="https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/celebrities-a-modest-proposal.jpg" alt="" width="468" height="337" srcset="https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/celebrities-a-modest-proposal.jpg 468w, https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/celebrities-a-modest-proposal-300x216.jpg 300w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 468px) 100vw, 468px" /></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><span style="color: #ff6600;"><em>Originally published June 1, 2011</em></span></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>(With apologies to <a href="https://art-bin.com/art/omodest.html">Jonathan Swift</a>.)</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>It is a melancholy object to those, who happen to possess televisions or iPads or other electronic media platforms, when they see their screens crowded with sharp-elbowed contestants in search of Celebrity, or glossy stars preening in Celebrity&#8217;s possession. These persons instead of being able to work for an honest livelihood, are obliged by their sordid compulsion to employ all their time in the attainment or the maintenance of this rank, notwithstanding that Celebrity&#8217;s chief value to the publick comes in the general satisfaction produced when it is turned into Notoriety and Failure.</p>
<p>I think it is agreed by all parties, that the nature of Celebrity, until it is lost, is to belittle by implication those who do not have it; and moreover, that in the modern media marketplace, many more have Celebrity than have earned it. And therefore whoever could find a fair, cheap and easy method of putting these Celebrities to better social use, would deserve so well of the publick, as to have his statue set up for a preserver of the nation.</p>
<p>The number of souls in this republic being reckoned slightly above three hundred millions, of these I calculate there may be about five thousand Celebrities, nationally and in local media markets, whose renown and corruption are sufficient to cause a significant demoralization of our citizens, with particularly adverse effects upon our impressionable Youth.</p>
<p>I do therefore humbly offer it to publick consideration, that without undue delay, these persons of spuriously elevated rank should be forcibly employed in Entertainments that neither increase nor maintain their rank, but rather, graphically strip them of it.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-248" src="https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/in-the-stocks.jpg" alt="" width="208" height="242" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-249" src="https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/drawn-and-quartered.jpg" alt="" width="350" height="244" srcset="https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/drawn-and-quartered.jpg 350w, https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/drawn-and-quartered-300x209.jpg 300w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 350px) 100vw, 350px" /></p>
<p>I have been assured by learned sociologists as well as by experienced gossip-site proprietors and SEO-specialists that the publick punishment and humiliation of a Celebrity provide a deeper and more genuine pleasure, and therefore greater social utility, than our traditional Entertainments which elevate the Celebrity at the expense of the viewer.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-250" src="https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/burning-celebrity.jpg" alt="" width="157" height="160" /></p>
<p>There is likewise another great advantage in my scheme, that it will influence our citizens, and especially our impressionable Youth, to abandon their misbegotten misty-edged “dreams” of winning American Idol or having their own show on The Disney Channel, and will substitute for these aspirations myriad aversive nightmare-images of their erstwhile role models being publickly slapped, stoned, shaved, branded, soiled, boiled, bespittled, broiled, skewered, truncated, disemboweled, decapitated, drawn-and-quartered, and otherwise comprehensively cut down to size.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-251" src="https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/guillotine-celebrity.jpg" alt="" width="300" height="376" srcset="https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/guillotine-celebrity.jpg 300w, https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/guillotine-celebrity-239x300.jpg 239w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /></p>
<p>I think the advantages by the proposal which I have made are already obvious, as well as of the highest importance, and yet they may be augmented in a number of ways. The publick Punishments may be held in local parks, athletic facilities and community centers, without general media broadcast, to encourage citizens to attend in person and thereby regain some of that sense of natural Community, of which the growth of media and cult of Celebrity have largely deprived them.</p>
<p>It would also be to our nation’s considerable benefit to export some of these unwanted Celebrities, for direct profit and improvement of our trade balance, to countries where these famous persons&#8217; publick utilization would be even more thorough and spectacular than in our own; and additionally as a diplomatic goodwill offering, to certain conservative societies where our own decadent and encroaching culture has lately given offense. I have it on good authority from officials of our State Department that, for example, a quiet annual tribute of one or two well-known “tween” stars, in good health and fresh from rehab, would go a long way towards alleviating our present difficulties with the Taleban and their tribal allies.</p>
<p>I am not so violently bent upon my own opinion, as to reject any offer, proposed by wise men, which shall be found of equal constructive value, yet shall abstain from using these few thousand Celebrities in the rough manner I have described. But before something of that kind shall be advanced in contradiction to my scheme, I desire the author or authors will be pleased maturely to consider one point: As things now stand, not a few thousands but <em>tens of millions of our citizens</em>, comprising the youthful especially, but also the middle-aged and even elderly, will squander sizeable portions of their remaining lives and fortunes in fruitless, miserable pursuit of&#8212;or, at least, in slack-jawed, depression-inducing spectation of&#8212;this mirage-like attribute, whose existence depends entirely upon the foolish faith of those who do not have it.<a href="http://hereticalnotions.com/2011/06/01/celebrities-a-modest-proposal/charlie-sheen/" rel="attachment wp-att-2461"> </a></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-252" src="https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/miley-cyrus.jpg" alt="" width="300" height="300" srcset="https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/miley-cyrus.jpg 300w, https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/miley-cyrus-150x150.jpg 150w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-253" src="https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/tila-tequila.jpg" alt="" width="320" height="467" srcset="https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/tila-tequila.jpg 320w, https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/tila-tequila-206x300.jpg 206w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 320px) 100vw, 320px" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-254" src="https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/gary-busey.jpg" alt="" width="289" height="425" srcset="https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/gary-busey.jpg 289w, https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/gary-busey-204x300.jpg 204w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 289px) 100vw, 289px" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-255" src="https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/britney-spears.jpg" alt="" width="470" height="374" srcset="https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/britney-spears.jpg 470w, https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/britney-spears-300x239.jpg 300w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 470px) 100vw, 470px" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-256" src="https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/paris-hilton-scandal.jpg" alt="" width="400" height="311" srcset="https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/paris-hilton-scandal.jpg 400w, https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/paris-hilton-scandal-300x233.jpg 300w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 400px) 100vw, 400px" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-257" src="https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/Lohan-celebrity-casualty.jpg" alt="" width="396" height="425" srcset="https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/Lohan-celebrity-casualty.jpg 396w, https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/Lohan-celebrity-casualty-280x300.jpg 280w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 396px) 100vw, 396px" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-258" src="https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/celebrity-fail.jpg" alt="" width="300" height="319" srcset="https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/celebrity-fail.jpg 300w, https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/celebrity-fail-282x300.jpg 282w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="aligncenter wp-image-259 size-full" src="https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/look-at-me.jpg" alt="Look at me!" width="400" height="300" srcset="https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/look-at-me.jpg 400w, https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/look-at-me-300x225.jpg 300w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 400px) 100vw, 400px" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-260" src="https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/weiner-look-at-me.jpg" alt="" width="400" height="300" srcset="https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/weiner-look-at-me.jpg 400w, https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/weiner-look-at-me-300x225.jpg 300w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 400px) 100vw, 400px" /></p>
<p><span style="color: #ff0000;"><em> </em></span></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
