<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Uncategorized &#8211; JAMES THE OBSCURE</title>
	<atom:link href="https://james-the-obscure.github.io/category/uncategorized/feed" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://james-the-obscure.github.io/</link>
	<description>essays on culture, politics and technology</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Thu, 02 Jan 2025 23:54:38 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.7.1</generator>

<image>
	<url>https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/fav1-150x150.png</url>
	<title>Uncategorized &#8211; JAMES THE OBSCURE</title>
	<link>https://james-the-obscure.github.io/</link>
	<width>32</width>
	<height>32</height>
</image> 
	<item>
		<title>A QUANTUM OF DESPAIR</title>
		<link>https://james-the-obscure.github.io/a-quantum-of-despair</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[JtO]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 14 Dec 2024 23:36:35 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://james-the-obscure.github.io/?p=529</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[What if science is becoming toxic to human society? &#160; In the summer of 1950, Nobel-winning nuclear physicist Enrico Fermi didn’t understand the scale of the cosmos as we understand it today. But he knew that it was at least hundreds of millions of light-years across, encompassing thousands of galaxies and more than a trillion<p><a class="readmore" href="https://james-the-obscure.github.io/a-quantum-of-despair"><span class="arrow-right icon"></span>Read More</a></p>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><em>What if science is becoming toxic to human society?</em></p>
<p><span id="more-529"></span></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>In the summer of 1950, Nobel-winning nuclear physicist Enrico Fermi didn’t understand the scale of the cosmos as we understand it today. But he knew that it was at least hundreds of millions of light-years across, encompassing thousands of galaxies and more than a trillion stellar systems. Thus, he reckoned, unless Earth was a vanishingly rare exception the universe should be teeming with life-forms, and many of their civilizations would be far more advanced than ours.</p>
<p>And yet, as he asked his lunchmates at Los Alamos one day that summer, “where <em>is</em> everybody?” ET visitations to Earth were either absent entirely, or—assuming some were marked by UFO sightings—difficult to pin down as such. This discrepancy between the theoretical abundance of ETs on the one hand, and their actual scarcity or elusiveness on the other, became known as Fermi’s Paradox.</p>
<p>Over the years, there have been various proposed solutions to this paradox: Perhaps the Earth really is exceptional in its ability to support life. Or perhaps Earth isn’t so exceptional, but advanced species generally cause their own extinction through catastrophic climate change, or by using nuclear and other weapons of mass destruction. Or perhaps they mostly perish in statistically inevitable natural disasters such as asteroid strikes before they can become (as Elon Musk puts it) “multiplanetary.” Or perhaps the lightspeed limit makes interstellar travel impractical.</p>
<p>One thing that should be clear about our Fermi’s Paradox discussions is that they are inherently speculative: Our civilization is still decidedly <em>non</em>-star-faring, and thus even our “experts” cannot know what it is like to be star-faring.</p>
<p>The mainstream proposed explanations, moreover, often rest heavily on Western anxieties that have arisen quite recently and may be only temporary. They also tend to assume that as long as we humans continue to exist, the only barriers to our progress in space exploration will be technical barriers—in other words, we will always possess the motive to become star-farers.</p>
<p>But will we? My own view, for what it’s worth, is that humans have a substantial “internal conflict” in regard to space exploration and cosmology: a conflict that has been worsening for centuries, will eventually reach a crisis stage, and plausibly applies to any civilization-building species that arises in the cosmos.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><strong>Toxic Knowledge</strong></p>
<p>As we approach the level of knowledge needed to become star-faring, our scientific understanding of the cosmos, and of “the fabric of reality,” has started to clash more and more severely with our deep-set traditional ideas about ourselves and our place in the universe. In other words, our science—our physics and cosmology in particular—has become psychologically <em>toxic</em>. Since this conflict is essentially ignored by our contemporary elites, it affects people mainly at a subconscious level. But it is driven by the advance of science, and thus is progressive. Indeed, as an ever-worsening inducer of despair and demoralization, it must ultimately weaken civilization, and may have no “resolution” other than species extinction or a retreat to simple, static, low-tech social forms (think of the Amish, or the Taleban).</p>
<p>That science is psychologically problematic should be clear enough from the human experience. As certain universal themes in our mythologies and religions suggest, we have long had a need to believe or implicitly assume that we are special and at the center of things: that God and Creation are somehow about us, and confer purpose on our existence. Science—which, ironically, we developed in part to help us spread our religions across the globe—tends to contradict such beliefs and assumptions. Indeed, the revelation of human insignificance has been perhaps science’s most consistent theme. By now, cosmologically, it has located us in a nondescript arm of a nondescript galaxy, and taxonomically it has identified us as a species of ape.</p>
<p>The basic idea that science defies our need for purpose, meaning and self-importance, and thereby nourishes nihilism and despair, is hardly a new one; it has been worried over by philosophers as different as Pascal and Nietzsche. But even now, hundreds of years after their warnings, this process might still be in its early stages.</p>
<p><strong> </strong></p>
<p><strong>From “Billions and Billions” to Infinite Infinities</strong></p>
<p>Big new ideas about our species and its place in the cosmos can take generations, even centuries, to be assimilated into our internal models of reality and our systems of morality; and in many cases it is those models and moral systems that have to change.</p>
<p>I suspect that Darwin’s theory of evolution, as well as neuroscientific demonstrations about the illusion of free will, still haven’t been fully assimilated in this sense. But what about Copernicus? Didn’t he demote us from the center of the universe half a millennium ago? Didn’t we cope with that pretty well?</p>
<p>Arguably we did, but Copernicus’s theory was less revolutionary than it has been portrayed. The traditional, pre-Copernican model of the cosmos, which was based on our instinctive anthropocentrism and a naïve interpretation of the apparent movements of stars, moon and planets, held that the Earth with its God-chosen beings lay at the center of existence, while all else revolved around it. Copernicus’s model made just one change, putting our sun at the center, which allowed a simpler, more elegant account of celestial motions even as it kept our stellar system in its place of supreme privilege.</p>
<p>It was only much more recently that the traditional (and literal) anthropocentrism of our cosmological models was conclusively overturned. Until almost exactly a century ago—the mid 1920s—leading astronomers believed that our universe consists only of our Milky Way galaxy, with our stellar system at or near the center. Around that time, better techniques for estimating stellar distances revealed that Earth, in fact, lies far from the Milky Way’s center, while the Milky Way is just one of multiple galaxies.</p>
<p><img fetchpriority="high" decoding="async" class="aligncenter  wp-image-538" src="https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/hubble.jpg" alt="" width="408" height="351" srcset="https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/hubble.jpg 476w, https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/hubble-300x258.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 408px) 100vw, 408px" /></p>
<p>That was a major change, but when I was coming of age a half-century later, the scale of the universe still seemed somewhat manageable. Like millions of others, I watched Carl Sagan’s <em>Cosmos</em> documentary series in 1980-81, learning, for example, that the universe contains not just a handful of galaxies but at least tens of thousands of them, and I wouldn’t say that put an irreparable dent in my belief in human potential. It still seemed conceivable that mankind, with exponentially improving scientific knowledge and technology, could spread outward and someday comprehend it all.</p>
<p>But cosmologists and cosmology-minded physicists were still just getting started. By the turn of the millennium, with the help of tools like the Hubble Telescope, their models were assuming billions of galaxies. Astronomers also were starting to use terms like “visible universe” and “known universe” to delineate the portion their telescopes could reach, which, despite its vastness, was apparently incomplete. Indeed, they increasingly embraced the idea that the universe is ever-expanding, and is not just tens or hundreds of billions of light years across but <em>infinite</em>—in all dimensions, presumably including dimensions we can’t perceive. In a truly infinite cosmos, as many of them noted, any local reality would have essentially identical variants elsewhere: “parallel worlds.” As physicist Brian Greene put it in his 2011 book <em>The Hidden Reality</em>, “I find it both curious and compelling that numerous developments in physics, if followed sufficiently far, bump into some variation on the parallel-universe theme.”</p>
<p><strong> </strong></p>
<p><strong>MWI</strong></p>
<p>The best-known parallel-world theory these days, the “Many Worlds Interpretation” (MWI), was devised by Hugh Everett III (1930-1982) in the mid-1950s while he was a physics PhD student under John Wheeler at Princeton. Everett’s work was mostly ignored while he was alive, though other physicists, notably Bryce DeWitt and David Deutsch, did much to popularize it later among physicists and the general public—and to extend it and give it its present name.</p>
<p>Everett formulated his theory as an explanation for a long-standing conundrum at the heart of quantum mechanics: Any quantum-scale particle seems to possess an innate, default multiplicity, existing not as a discrete, solitary particle but as a ghostly cluster of variants, which in certain experiments can be revealed by their wave-interference pattern. Only when an experimenter tries to detect the particle more directly does this cluster “collapse” to just one discrete particle. When Everett developed his theory, the prevailing interpretation of such experiments among physicists was, firstly, that the other variant particles are, in a sense, not real, and, secondly, that the “collapse” of the ghostly cluster to just one “real” particle requires—somewhat spookily—an observing experimenter.</p>
<p>Everett felt that this need for an observer was problematic—<em>who sits outside the universe, observing it?</em> he asked—and offered a more parsimonious interpretation that didn’t require this assumption: He considered the initial, ghostly, mutually-interfering cluster of particles totally real, and held that the apparent “collapse” of this ensemble to just one discrete particle was due essentially to that particle’s chance interaction with, and, in effect, <em>capture</em> by, other particles (such as in the measuring apparatus) of the particular universe in which the experimenter happened to exist. As for the apparently unrealized particles in the original cluster, they would manifest as discrete particles in <em>other universes</em> populated by other variants of the experimenter and his measuring apparatus. In short, Everett’s theory held that reality consists of multiple universes—in which, collectively, anything that can happen does happen.</p>
<p>Everett’s idea was opposed, as brave new ideas that threaten the status quo and its defenders typically are. But the opposition to MWI wasn’t just the usual circling of the wagons by the old guard. Even many who admired its elegance were discomfited by it. As Oxford philosopher of physics Simon Saunders said to a reporter in 2007, “The multiverse will drive you crazy if you really think about how it affects your life, and I can’t live like that. I’ll just accept Everett and then think about something else, to save my sanity.”</p>
<p>Still, MWI was and remains elegant and robustly consistent with experimental results. As alternative theories have fallen by the wayside, it has steadily risen in popularity, not just among physicists but among science popularizers—and popular audiences, for example of the recent MWI-themed movie <em>Everything Everywhere All at Once</em>.</p>
<p>A few days ago as I write, MWI received what some considered major support when Google reported a “quantum supremacy” demonstration by its experimental quantum computer Willow. A feat of quantum supremacy is a feat that a quantum computer—whose computational bits exist not as discrete 0 or 1 bits but in ghostly superpositions of both—can do that an ordinary “classical” computer can never match. It is regarded as an empirical proof that quantum computing is real, which for many physicists also bolsters the validity of MWI, because the idea of quantum computing—first developed by Deutsch in the mid 1980s—is that such computers gain their advantage in effect by performing computations across different universes.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-530" src="https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/hn-quote.jpg" alt="" width="764" height="165" srcset="https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/hn-quote.jpg 764w, https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/hn-quote-300x65.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 764px) 100vw, 764px" /></p>
<p style="text-align: center;">—from Google Quantum AI blog post 9 Dec 2024</p>
<p><strong> </strong></p>
<p><strong>A Toxic Science</strong></p>
<p>Popularizers of physics and cosmology, under the influence of the media industries that nourish them, tend to look on the sunny side. They celebrate the “beauty” of the cosmos in all its vastness and complexity. They applaud our ability as a species to transcend our humble origins, and species-centric biases, as we start to apprehend and explore that cosmos. As I was rewatching <em>Cosmos</em> (1980) recently, I noticed it was now prefaced by Ann Druyan, Sagan’s widow and a writer and director on the series, who invokes the “soaring spiritual high” of science’s “central revelation: our oneness with the universe.”</p>
<p>To me this is hand-waving self-delusion, or, worse, window-dressing to protect media consumers’ feelings. Our science-revealed insignificance—and for MWI this is not just a relative insignificance but an <em>absolute</em>, one-over-infinity insignificance—cannot co-exist forever with our needs for purpose and meaning.</p>
<p>The MWI cosmos is, in a technical sense, more splendid and elegant than anything found in human religion. What could be more perfect, what could be more complete, than an infinitude in which everything that can happen does happen? The problem is that this perfect completeness, or maybe unendingness, leaves nothing of substance for us to achieve. It mocks our conceit that we could somehow explore—let alone “conquer”—it all.</p>
<p>In fact, MWI implies that there is no higher purpose or meaning to any human being’s actions or existence, other than by filling out, in an infinitesimal way, the infinite space of possibility. Are you a good person in this universe? Are you “successful”? How can this be substantially meaningful (especially from the perspective of a God that transcends the multiverse), if otherwise indistinguishable variants of you are bad and unsuccessful in other universes—and presumably average to a mediocrity across all instances? When you combine this “MWI view” with the modern neuroscientific view of behavior—as being determined moment to moment by innumerable, mostly subconscious factors while our conscious selves stand by as purblind spectators—you start to get a picture of humans as “non-player-character” automata in a sort of video game with infinite parallel playthroughs.</p>
<p>To the extent that people can see themselves and their lives from this perspective, they are likely to lose a lot of their motivations for doing things—and not just great and ambitious things but also the ordinary, pro-social behaviors that keep societies from coming unglued. Such behaviors are rooted in concepts of good and bad, meaning and purpose, and MWI erodes all that as completely as would a revelation that we live in a simulation.</p>
<p>MWI defies our traditional views so starkly and extensively that it also calls into question the “<em>sapiens sapiens</em>” label we have given ourselves. Perhaps, when compared to other civ-building species in our galaxy, we aren’t very smart at all. Perhaps our simple ape brains are already nearing the limits<a href="#_ftn1" name="_ftnref1">[1]</a> of what they can do—limits that fall well short of what even the most basic star-faring endeavors require.</p>
<p><strong> </strong></p>
<p><strong>Fermi revisited</strong></p>
<p>Again, big changes in our understanding of ourselves and our place in the cosmos can take generations to sink in, and the entry of MWI and other infinite-cosmos notions into the popular mind began only recently. It may be that only children born very recently, or even around now, will be forced to confront these ideas in a substantial way during the impressionable years when their models of the world and moral structures come together. Maybe only in the Western world of twenty or thirty years hence will we start to see clear signs of its impact.</p>
<p>In the meantime, it’s surely fair to say that despair and nihilism already seem abundant, particularly among the young.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-531" src="https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/nihil-trend.jpg" alt="" width="769" height="226" srcset="https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/nihil-trend.jpg 769w, https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/nihil-trend-300x88.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 769px) 100vw, 769px" /></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="aligncenter  wp-image-540" src="https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/nihil2.jpg" alt="" width="580" height="76" srcset="https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/nihil2.jpg 504w, https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/nihil2-300x39.jpg 300w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 580px) 100vw, 580px" /></p>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-539" src="https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/nihilism-1.jpg" alt="" width="776" height="331" srcset="https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/nihilism-1.jpg 776w, https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/nihilism-1-300x128.jpg 300w, https://james-the-obscure.github.io/wp-content/uploads/nihilism-1-768x328.jpg 768w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 776px) 100vw, 776px" /></p>
<p>While much of that is due presumably to the many other disruptions to social and economic traditions and structures in recent decades, perhaps some already is being caused (again: even among people who are not consciously aware of it) by science—which after all has been moving in its current direction, displacing religiously based beliefs and ethics, for centuries now. In any case, despair caused by other factors is treatable in principle, whereas the one served up by science seems incurable.</p>
<p>Couldn’t we create advanced AI-based robots that self-replicate, develop their own new tech, and relentlessly explore outer space, without regard for the apparent pointlessness of the endeavor—indeed, without any emotion at all? Yes, in theory, if we could remain motivated long enough to develop the necessary AI and robotics tech. But robots’ exploring the cosmos is not the same as humans exploring the cosmos. Moreover, it’s not hard to imagine these metal creatures eventually finishing off their depressed, listless, impotent creators, in a perfect and final example of a “cure” that kills the patient.</p>
<p>The idea that physics and cosmology eventually become toxic to society offers a solution to Fermi’s Paradox because it is plausible that not only humans but also other intelligent species that emerge in the cosmos and start venturing into space face this same problem—this fundamental conflict between, on the one hand, the psychology they need to develop civilization and science, and, on the other, the science they need to go further and become star-faring.</p>
<p>Incidentally, MWI’s hint at our inferiority as a species offers another, complementary solution: The few star-faring civs that do exist in our vicinity either do not care about us, or, even if they are curious enough to visit, don’t waste time trying to communicate—firstly because we are too primitive to process what they would have to say, and secondly because almost anything they <em>could</em> convey, particularly regarding cosmology and the nature of reality, would injure us.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;">***</p>
<p><a href="#_ftnref1" name="_ftn1">[1]</a> “However high mankind may have evolved—and perhaps at the end it will stand even lower than at the beginning!—it cannot pass over into a higher order, as little as the ant and the earwig can at the end of its &#8216;earthly course&#8217; rise up to kinship with God and eternal life.” From Nietzsche, <em>Daybreak: Thoughts on the Prejudices of Morality</em>, 1:49, trans. R. J. Hollingdale, Cambridge Univ. Press 1997.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
